<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vita sana &amp; longa the preservation of health and prolongation of life proposed and proved : in the due observance of remarkable præcautions, and daily practicable rules, relating to body and mind, compendiously abstracted from the institutions and law of nature / by E. Maynwaringe ...</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 219 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41734</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355844</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110713</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1747:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vita sana &amp; longa the preservation of health and prolongation of life proposed and proved : in the due observance of remarkable præcautions, and daily practicable rules, relating to body and mind, compendiously abstracted from the institutions and law of nature / by E. Maynwaringe ...</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
                  <author>White, Robert, 1645-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 160 p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. Sold by the Booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes frontispiece portrait of the author, signed: R. White, sculp.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Longevity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vita Sana &amp; Longa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Preſervation of <hi>Health,</hi> AND Prolongation of <hi>Life.</hi> Propoſed and proved. In the due <hi>obſervance</hi> of <hi>Remarkable Praecautions.</hi> And daily practicable <hi>Rules,</hi> Relating to <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Mind,</hi> compendiouſly abſtracted from the <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> of Nature.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. Maynwaringe,</hi> Dr. in Phyſick.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Non accepimus brevem vitam, ſed fecimus.</p>
               <bibl>Senec.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> Sold by the Bookſellers, 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>EVERARDUS · MAYNWARINGE · MEDICINAE · DOCTOR. · AETATIS · SUAE · 38 · 1668.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:4"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſome Years ſince put forth a rough draught, or indigeſted Notions, upon this <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject:</hi> with intentions then to reviſe and finiſh at more leaſure, when opportunity was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded me: yet other <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> ſo put me by, as I thought not at all to reaſſume this matter again, nor make any farther proſecution. But being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by ſeveral, that this <hi>Subject,</hi> and the managing of it, was acceptable to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and that no <hi>Copies</hi> was remaining with the <hi>Book-ſellers,</hi> but clear ſold off, and yet inquired for, but not to be had: I was <hi>ſollicited</hi> and <hi>deſired</hi> to reprint it, for the publick good and ſatisfaction of
<pb facs="tcp:110713:5"/>
thoſe that deſire to be regulated in the courſe of their lives, and to be informed the right way for preſerving of <hi>Health,</hi> and <hi>prolonging</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſidering then that <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>long-life,</hi> are the two great deſiderable enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and perfection of <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> coveted and aimed at by all: and that I might not be taxed as refractory and obſtinate, refuſing to gratifie ſuch reaſonable Deſires, for the acquiring thoſe laudable ends: I was hereby moved to ſet upon the <hi>Work</hi> again, for improvement and finiſhing what I had left imperfect and defective in the <hi>former Tract.</hi> But upon reviſing thoſe ſheets, much came in my mind to <hi>add</hi> and to <hi>alter;</hi> ſo that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the old ſtock would remain: I then thought it beſt to lay a new foundation or <hi>Platform</hi> of Title; that I might not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to the <hi>Order, Rule,</hi> or <hi>Matter</hi> of the old Structure; but have full liberty to manage the Work as my <hi>genius</hi> ſhould lead me.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, and with this freedom, I have here proceeded, to draw forth and preſent to you this delectable <hi>Theam</hi> of <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Long-life,</hi> with the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:110713:5"/>
profitable advantages the Subject imports, and eaſe of acquiring, your capacities will admit.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever therefore deſires to <hi>live</hi> long, to ſee their <hi>Childrens Children;</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their <hi>youth, ſtrength</hi> and <hi>beauty;</hi> to be free from moleſting <hi>pains</hi> and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>Diſeaſes;</hi> to preſerve their <hi>ſenſes,</hi> and enjoy the perfection of mind to the extremity of Age; let them conform and be obedient to the <hi>Hygiaſtick</hi> Laws and Rules hereafter preſcribed; and they may expect what is here propoſed for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Nor ſhall I exact and require of you an irkeſome ſtrictneſs, or <hi>Leſſian</hi> preciſeneſs to eat and drink by <hi>weight</hi> and <hi>meaſure:</hi> but a reaſonable obſervance, ſuteable and well agreeing with a ſober ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional perſon, not <hi>reſtraining</hi> convenient liberty, and the lawful pleaſure of life. Nor can a <hi>regular</hi> courſe of life be thought troubleſome, as a difficult and hard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint; but moſt pleaſant and free,<note place="margin">Quod aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcenti primum difficile; non erit aſſueto.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to thoſe accuſtomed to the contrary; and the leaving of thoſe ill cuſtoms is the difficulty; but the Rules injoyned be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile and eaſie to obſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:110713:6"/>And having once acquired a good ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and conſtant uſe; to return to an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular intemperate living, would be a far greater burthen and irkeſome, if enjoyned and impoſed, then the declining and deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deſtructive courſe, for a laudable wholeſome regimen, moſt conſonant to a rational Creature.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui medicè vivit, ſine medicis diu vivet:</l>
               <l>Qui non medicè vivit, cum medicis ſaepe, ſed non diu erit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He that lives by Rule and wholeſome Precepts; takes the beſt courſe of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting Phyſick: he's a Phyſician to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and needs not the help of others: but they that live careleſly and irregularly, contemning Phyſical Rules as unneceſſary Obſervations; ſhall be conſtrained to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Remedies, as neceſſary helps; and muſt often reſign into the hands of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. M.</signed>
               <dateline>LONDON, <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Clarkenwell-Cloſe.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:6"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 4th, 1669.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>ROGER L'ESTRANGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:110713:7"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. line 19. read <hi>illae.</hi> p. 21. l. 17. <hi>immetho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically.</hi> p. 27. <hi>poſitivè,</hi> in the Margent. p. 39. l. 13. <hi>parts.</hi> p. 36. l. 17. <hi>aromatical.</hi> p. 72. <hi>inimicum</hi> in the Margent. p. 151. l. 29. <hi>quis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond Part.</p>
            <p>Page 24. line 27. read <hi>eradicate.</hi> p. 30. l. 14. <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant.</hi> p. 32. l. 15. <hi>deobſtruct.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110713:7"/>
            <head>Long Life, AND Means to attain it.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section,</hi> I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the <hi>Primitive</hi> Age of the <hi>World,</hi> mans <hi>life</hi> was accounted to be about 1000 <hi>Years:</hi> but after the <hi>Flood,</hi> the Life of Man was <hi>abreviated</hi> half;<note place="margin">Mans Age ſhortned.</note> and none then attained to the <hi>tearm</hi> of the firſt <hi>Age,</hi> except <hi>Noah,</hi> who lived 950 Years: and after three <hi>Generations</hi> from the <hi>Flood,</hi> their lives were reduced to a <hi>fourth</hi> of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:110713:8"/>
Age; and their <hi>lives</hi> ordinarily exceeded not two hundred Years.</p>
               <p>About <hi>Moſes</hi> his time, the <hi>Age</hi> of Man was yet ſhorter, commonly not exceeding 120 <hi>Years,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mans Age <hi>120</hi> years.</note> which alſo was <hi>his Age</hi> when he died: yet we find up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record in <hi>Sacred Writ,</hi> and from <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Writers,</hi> that after <hi>Moſes</hi> ſome lived 240 and 260, yet that was <hi>rare;</hi> but more <hi>frequently</hi> 120, which was then the <hi>common</hi> Age.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Age</hi> of Man is reduced to <hi>half</hi> that:<note place="margin">Mans Age <hi>60</hi> years.</note> 60 or 70 years we count up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But although in <hi>general</hi> we find this <hi>gradual declenſion</hi> and abreviation of mans <hi>Life,</hi> in the ſeveral Ages of the <hi>World;</hi> yet muſt underſtand it was not <hi>equally</hi> ſo in all <hi>parts</hi> of the World to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but <hi>places</hi> and <hi>climates,</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>living</hi> of a people, cauſe much <hi>difference</hi> in the <hi>protraction</hi> of their <hi>lives,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Age of man differ in ſeveral places.</note> that at the ſame time ſome people of <hi>peculiar places,</hi> were longer lived, by a <hi>third</hi> or <hi>fourth</hi> part, then others of another <hi>Climate</hi> or <hi>Region,</hi> as the <hi>Northern</hi> People: and in <hi>colder</hi> Countreys, they are longer lived then in the <hi>hot Climates,</hi> and this by reaſon of the <hi>heat</hi> that <hi>opens</hi> the <hi>Pores,</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110713:8"/>
cauſeth ſo great a <hi>tranſpiration,</hi> that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiccates</hi> and <hi>enervates</hi> the body: but a <hi>cooler Air</hi> prohibits and reſtrains ſuch <hi>immoderate tranſpiration</hi> and exhauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; keeps the <hi>ſpirits</hi> vigorous and <hi>united,</hi> and preſerves the <hi>alimentory Juyces</hi> of the body from too frequent and <hi>immoderate exſudation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we examine into the <hi>Ages</hi> of other <hi>Creatures,</hi> we find little difference in their <hi>durations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Other Creatares keep their Age.</note> to what they were in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Times, and <hi>infancy</hi> of the World; who keeping to the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> implanted in them, do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their <hi>Beings,</hi> and degenerate little from the <hi>integrity</hi> of their <hi>durations,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to them from the <hi>beginning.</hi> Now why mans days <hi>ſhould</hi> be thus <hi>abreviated</hi> and ſhortned from what they were and the <hi>tearm</hi> of his life reduced to ſo ſhort a <hi>continuance,</hi> gradually declining in the ſeveral <hi>Ages</hi> of the World, is fit matter to inquire into.</p>
               <p>The <hi>cauſes</hi> of the <hi>abreviation</hi> of mans <hi>life</hi> will appear,<note place="margin">Why mans life is ſhortned.</note> if we <hi>compare</hi> the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our <hi>living</hi> now with that of the <hi>firſt Age</hi> of the World; and from thence, how every <hi>generation,</hi> have <hi>worſted</hi> themſelves by a <hi>degenerate</hi> condition of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110713:9"/>
life, <hi>unſutable</hi> to the <hi>inſtitutions</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And ſince we muſt of neceſſity allow and admit of <hi>hereditary infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and <hi>traductive</hi> debilities of Nature; we cannot but expect (unleſs by <hi>great reformation</hi> of the injurious <hi>cuſtoms</hi> and vices of theſe latter Ages) but that <hi>we</hi> and our <hi>poſterity</hi> ſhall <hi>degenerate</hi> yet ſtill into a <hi>worſe</hi> &amp; <hi>ſooner fading</hi> ſtate of life.<note place="margin">Mans life likely to be yet ſhorter.</note> For, as the <hi>principles</hi> of our Nature are <hi>more infirm,</hi> tainted, and <hi>debauched</hi> from our Parents and Progenitors, then <hi>thoſe</hi> of former <hi>Ages,</hi> of more <hi>vigour, ſoundneſs</hi> and <hi>integrity;</hi> are likewiſe <hi>more propenſe,</hi> and liable <hi>worſe</hi> to be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved</hi> and degenerate, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of <hi>ſhorter duration</hi> and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now</hi> if we inquire into the <hi>condition</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>living</hi> of the <hi>Antients,</hi> comparing with the <hi>cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> of this <hi>Age;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Different living now to that of former times.</note> we ſhall find ſo much <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> and <hi>irregularity</hi> from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and <hi>injunction</hi> of Nature, that may give full ſatisfaction to the <hi>quaery</hi> and matter in hand.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>infancy</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and ſought after the neceſſary <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites</hi> for his <hi>Being,</hi> and was conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110713:9"/>
with a <hi>competent ſubſiſtence</hi> which Nature did <hi>purely</hi> require: but in <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> of time, Man was not ſatisfied with the <hi>bare reparations,</hi> and <hi>neceſſary props</hi> of Nature, moſt wholeſome and <hi>conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative</hi> of his <hi>Being;</hi> but hunted after <hi>variety</hi> and <hi>exceſs,</hi> to pleaſe and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his <hi>ſenſitive Appetite.</hi> Thus one <hi>Age</hi> taught <hi>another</hi> to be irregular and <hi>diſordered;</hi> and ſtill dictated <hi>novel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions</hi> to the ſucceeding Generation, to fill up and perfect what their <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors</hi> had prompted and begun; whoſe lives were not <hi>long enough</hi> to lay a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat platform</hi> of debauched Nature, but muſt <hi>tranſmit</hi> their <hi>ruining practices</hi> to the following Ages to <hi>immitate</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hinc illaec lachrymae,</hi>— Thus, and after this manner, by ſuch means, is <hi>mans life</hi> beſet with many <hi>cruciating ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies,</hi> which have <hi>ſhortned</hi> the dayes of his abode here; and of <hi>latter Ages</hi> acts but a <hi>ſhort</hi> part upon the <hi>ſtage</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is procured by the <hi>variety</hi> and <hi>exceſs</hi> in <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drink:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brevity of mans life how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured.</note> by <hi>unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> and <hi>immoderate ſleeping</hi> and <hi>watching;</hi> turning <hi>day</hi> into <hi>night,</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110713:10"/>
                  <hi>night</hi> into <hi>day:</hi> by <hi>ſluggiſh</hi> &amp; unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>eaſe,</hi> inſtead of due <hi>exerciſe</hi> and <hi>motion:</hi> or <hi>toyling unſeaſonably,</hi> and <hi>wearing</hi> out the <hi>body</hi> when it requires <hi>natural reſt</hi> and refreſhment: by <hi>living</hi> in <hi>unwholeſome</hi> places, ſucking in <hi>noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome deſtructive Air;</hi> preferring <hi>profit</hi> and by <hi>intereſts,</hi> before <hi>health</hi> and long life; indulging <hi>Venus</hi> too much, by <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate</hi> and too <hi>frequent</hi> repeated <hi>acts,</hi> thereby <hi>enervating</hi> all the <hi>faculties, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiriting</hi> and <hi>waſting</hi> the body: by <hi>wearing</hi> and <hi>fretting</hi> the <hi>mind</hi> with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>paſſions,</hi> changing from one <hi>exceſs</hi> to another, and <hi>wracking</hi> the <hi>body</hi> with ſeveral <hi>diſturbing moods,</hi> and <hi>paſſionate humours:</hi> by <hi>exhauſting</hi> the ſtrength, in a <hi>prodigal expence</hi> of the <hi>vital ſtream,</hi> with <hi>frequent</hi> and unneceſſary <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:</hi> by <hi>infecting</hi> the body, and ſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>exotick impreſſions,</hi> too frequently, with the common <hi>virulent purgatives,</hi> that alienate the <hi>craſes</hi> or <hi>ferments</hi> of the parts; and ſuch like injurious <hi>Drugs,</hi> not rightly <hi>corrected,</hi> and ill <hi>prepared</hi> Medicines, that bring <hi>detriment</hi> and <hi>damage</hi> to the body by their uſe. To theſe may be added the <hi>injurious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement</hi> of <hi>Infants,</hi> by <hi>careleſs</hi> or <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110713:10"/>
Nurſes;</hi> and <hi>fond Mothers</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injuring their Children by a <hi>deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive indulgence,</hi> and erroneous <hi>affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate uſage,</hi> in the ordering and <hi>educating</hi> them, who for the moſt part live not ſo long as others.</p>
               <p>Having ſet forth how <hi>mans Life</hi> hath declined and <hi>ſhortned</hi> in the ſeveral <hi>Ages</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and pointed at the chief <hi>procuring Cauſes,</hi> of ſuch <hi>abrevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and change, (which hereafter we ſhall proſecute more fully) it remains to tell you how this <hi>evil</hi> may in part be <hi>remedied,</hi> and ſomething <hi>regained</hi> that hath been <hi>loſt,</hi> and is ſtill upon the <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> ſide, except <hi>recovered</hi> by a more <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent</hi> and <hi>prudent courſe.</hi> And here I muſt <hi>premiſe</hi> a few things before I come to the <hi>point,</hi> preſcribing the <hi>Rule</hi> to walk by, and means for attaining <hi>long life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the <hi>Creatures</hi> have their <hi>definite</hi> times of <hi>duration</hi> allotted them by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſome <hi>longer,</hi> others a <hi>ſhorter</hi> tearm:<note place="margin">Creatures differ in their term of being.</note> and this from the <hi>principles</hi> of their <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> &amp; <hi>ſeminality</hi> from whence they ſpring. In the <hi>Mineral Family,</hi> we find the <hi>longeſt</hi> durations, being <hi>ſolid, denſe bodies,</hi> of more <hi>ſimple</hi> natures, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110713:11"/>
                  <hi>homogenious,</hi> do preſerve their Beings <hi>longeſt</hi> from ruine and diſſolution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vegetables</hi> are of a <hi>ſhorter duration,</hi> yet not all alike; ſome <hi>preſerve</hi> their beings <hi>hundreds</hi> of years, as the <hi>Cedar</hi> and <hi>Oak.</hi> Others continue but a <hi>few years;</hi> ſome a <hi>year.</hi> Amongſt the <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Creatures,</hi> we find that ſerveral <hi>ſpecies</hi> have their <hi>peculiar</hi> durations, which in the common <hi>courſe</hi> of nature are obſerved to continue; ſome a <hi>longer Age,</hi> others a <hi>ſhorter.</hi> The <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> is ſloweſt in riſing to <hi>maturity</hi> and perfection, but continues <hi>longeſt</hi> in that <hi>ſtate.</hi> The <hi>Vegetable</hi> (in the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) is <hi>quickeſt</hi> in the <hi>aſcent</hi> to the <hi>top</hi> of perfection, but keeps not its ſtation long: ſome whereof fade and wither every <hi>year,</hi> but renew their <hi>verdure</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at the <hi>Spring,</hi> until a <hi>few years</hi> hath ſpent that <hi>ſeminal</hi> power and fertile blooming virtue. The <hi>Senſitive Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and perfect <hi>Animals,</hi> are ſlower in their <hi>riſe</hi> to perfection, which having attained, ſtay but a <hi>while</hi> in that full ſtrength, do <hi>gradually</hi> deſcend again, decline and periſh.</p>
               <p>So that all <hi>living Creatures</hi> by nature have their <hi>riſings</hi> and <hi>ſettings,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110713:11"/>
times <hi>fixed</hi> for their growth and <hi>duration:</hi> from their <hi>beginning</hi> they have a <hi>gradual aſcent,</hi> until they have attained the <hi>vigor</hi> and <hi>exaltation</hi> of their Natures; and having gained the <hi>top</hi> of their <hi>perfection,</hi> they ſtay not <hi>long</hi> there, but <hi>gradually deſcend</hi> again, and are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded</hi> of the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> of their Natures, and tend to their <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>diſſolution:</hi> nor are the <hi>Creatures</hi> limited <hi>alike</hi> to the ſame <hi>duration,</hi> but do <hi>extend,</hi> and are <hi>ſhortned</hi> variouſly, according to their <hi>Principles</hi> and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>Being,</hi> as Nature hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them with a proviſion <hi>permanent</hi> and <hi>ſutable</hi> for ſuch a <hi>duration</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now of all the <hi>Creatures,</hi> we find Man moſt <hi>uncertain</hi> in his <hi>being</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance,</hi> (although the <hi>Age</hi> of Man be limited to ſixty years) and is moſt lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>alteration</hi> and a <hi>periſhing</hi> ſtate, upon theſe four accounts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe Man <hi>derives</hi> from his <hi>Parents</hi> by a <hi>ſeminal propagation,</hi> and <hi>inherits</hi> the <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> of their <hi>vitious</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Natures <hi>radicated</hi> in him: to which his own <hi>enormous</hi> acts being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, does <hi>multiply</hi> and heighten the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110713:12"/>
                  <hi>corruption</hi> of his <hi>Nature;</hi> hence the <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding</hi> Generations becomes more <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, infirm, diſeaſed,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of <hi>ſhorter</hi> duration then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For that the <hi>ſtructure</hi> of his body, is the moſt <hi>wonderfully</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived of all the <hi>Creatures;</hi> containes the <hi>greateſt curioſity</hi> and variety of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chination;</hi> ſuch admirable <hi>Conduits</hi> and <hi>Contrivances;</hi> ſuch <hi>Offices</hi> and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>elaboration, ſubſervient</hi> to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>communicable:</hi> that therefore this <hi>Machine,</hi> is moſt <hi>difficult</hi> to keep in <hi>order,</hi> and ſooneſt put out of <hi>frame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Does <hi>require</hi> and uſe more <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>ſupports</hi> and neceſſary <hi>requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites</hi> to preſerve and <hi>ſupply</hi> him; and therefore <hi>more ſubject</hi> to errors, failings and <hi>diſcompoſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Becauſe Man <hi>wilfully, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly,</hi> or <hi>ignorantly,</hi> does not <hi>regulate</hi> and govern himſelf, according to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> dictated to him; but <hi>deviating</hi> from thoſe rules of <hi>preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> does <hi>diſcompoſe</hi> the regular <hi>Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> of his body, and introduce <hi>various Diſeaſes</hi> and diſorders, which <hi>precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates</hi> Nature in the <hi>current</hi> and courſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110713:12"/>
life, which otherwiſe more equally and evenly would glide on: and ſometimes by <hi>violence</hi> offered to Nature, in ſome ſtrange <hi>unnatural</hi> actions and <hi>exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> the life is <hi>forced</hi> out, and death oft <hi>procured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now other Creatures are ſo tyed up to the <hi>rule</hi> of Nature,<note place="margin">Creatures conformity to Nature.</note> which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but <hi>obſerve</hi> for their preſervation both <hi>individual</hi> and <hi>ſpeciſick;</hi> and have not a <hi>power</hi> of <hi>electing good</hi> and <hi>evil</hi> to themſelves; but <hi>naturally</hi> and <hi>ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneouſly</hi> do proſecute that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and <hi>conſervative,</hi> and avoid what is <hi>noxious:</hi> but Man having a greater liberty by the <hi>prerogative</hi> of his <hi>rational Soul,</hi> does make his <hi>choice,</hi> and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders amongſt varieties both <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> and often deceives himſelf, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what is deſtructive to his <hi>Being:</hi> So that breaking the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which he ought to obſerve as <hi>bounds</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> to his actions, making them <hi>ſanative</hi> and <hi>preſervative;</hi> does on the contrary <hi>alter</hi> and <hi>change</hi> thoſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>appointments</hi> and <hi>ſupports;</hi> renders them <hi>deſtructive</hi> by his <hi>irregular incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous</hi> uſe, <hi>vitious</hi> cuſtoms, and <hi>impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> choice.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110713:13"/>The moſt <hi>conſiderable things</hi> to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by Man, as <hi>conducing</hi> and <hi>tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the <hi>lengthening</hi> or <hi>ſhortning</hi> of his life, according to their <hi>mannagement</hi> and procurement, well or ill, do fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Heads.<note place="margin">Diaetetick regiment to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</note> 
                  <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>drink; place</hi> of <hi>abode; ſleep</hi> and <hi>watching; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> and <hi>reſt; excretions</hi> and <hi>retenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; paſſions</hi> of <hi>mind.</hi> In the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, uſe and choice of theſe (which particularly hereafter ſhall be handled) conſiſts the <hi>length</hi> and <hi>brevity</hi> of life, <hi>per modum aſiſtentiae,</hi> and as <hi>cauſae ſine qua non,</hi> being auxiliary <hi>requiſites,</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>ſupports</hi> of life, appointed by Nature for the <hi>continuation, aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>preſervation</hi> thereof. But the <hi>length</hi> and <hi>brevity</hi> of life, <hi>fontaliter &amp; radicaliter,</hi> conſiſts in the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Principles,</hi> and <hi>vital powers</hi> variouſly <hi>radicated</hi> and planted <hi>ab ortus</hi> in mans <hi>generation</hi> and <hi>fabrication.</hi> But this being not in the choice and power of man to alter or change, we ſhall proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute upon the former Heads.</p>
               <p>Man conſiſting of <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> and this body compounded of <hi>heterogeneous</hi> &amp; diſſimilar parts, <hi>deſtinated</hi> to various actions and offices, dependent in <hi>Being</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110713:13"/>
and conſervation; will neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>ſupply,</hi> proportionable and ſuiting to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>purpoſes, faculties, properties,</hi> and <hi>temperatures;</hi> in <hi>matter, manner, times,</hi> and <hi>order;</hi> for their maintenance and ſuſtentation in the integrity of their <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, offices</hi> and <hi>duties,</hi> conſtitutional <hi>diſpoſitions</hi> and <hi>Craſes,</hi> peculiarly <hi>conſervative</hi> of themſelves, <hi>reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>conſequently</hi> of the whole: And by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> (being ſubject to corruption and diſſolution, through the <hi>fragility</hi> of <hi>conſtitutive</hi> parts, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion</hi> and <hi>fabrication</hi>) is bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>Rules, Orders</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> moſt conſonant for preſervation and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in <hi>Being.</hi> Now if there be a <hi>diſproportion</hi> or <hi>unfitneſs,</hi> in the <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>quantum;</hi> or <hi>irregularity</hi> in the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, times</hi> or <hi>order</hi> of the auxiliary <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites</hi> and <hi>conſervatives,</hi> contrary to what the <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>neceſſity</hi> of his Nature <hi>requires</hi> and <hi>commands;</hi> there ariſeth <hi>Diſtempers, Ataxies</hi> and diſcord, the <hi>praeludiums</hi> to ruine and diſſolution. And this body being in a <hi>continual flux</hi> and <hi>reflux,</hi> converſant in <hi>viciſſitudes</hi> and <hi>variations</hi> of <hi>oppoſites, diſſimilars,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110713:14"/>
contraries</hi> and <hi>privations,</hi> as <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>cold, ſiccity</hi> and <hi>humidity, filling</hi> and <hi>emptying, reſt</hi> and <hi>motion, ſleeping</hi> and <hi>waking, inſpiration</hi> and <hi>expiration,</hi> and the like; could not ſubſiſt amidſt theſe <hi>various ſubalter nations</hi> and changes, if they were not <hi>bounded</hi> and <hi>regulated</hi> by <hi>due</hi> order of <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> to <hi>fit</hi> and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient times, that they might not claſh <hi>interfere,</hi> and <hi>encroach</hi> upon each others priviledges, due <hi>times</hi> and <hi>proprieties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>heat</hi> exceeds; the natural <hi>moiſture</hi> dries up, the <hi>ſpirits evaporate,</hi> and the body withers.</p>
               <p>If <hi>cold;</hi> the faculties are <hi>torpid</hi> and <hi>benum'd,</hi> the <hi>ſpirits</hi> being frozen up to a <hi>ceſſation</hi> from their duties.</p>
               <p>If <hi>moiſture</hi> prevails; the <hi>ſpirits</hi> are clogged, <hi>ſuffocated</hi> and <hi>drowned</hi> in the <hi>chanels</hi> of the body.</p>
               <p>If <hi>ſiccity</hi> and <hi>dryneſs;</hi> the <hi>organical</hi> parts are ſtubborn, <hi>unpliable</hi> and <hi>unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable</hi> of their regular <hi>motions</hi> and due <hi>actions;</hi> the <hi>vital ſtreams</hi> being drank up that ſhould <hi>irrigate,</hi> refreſh and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple them.</p>
               <p>Were the body alwayes <hi>taking in</hi> and ſending nothing <hi>forth,</hi> it would either <hi>increaſe</hi> to a monſtrous and vaſt <hi>magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude;</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:110713:14"/>
or fill up, <hi>ſuffocate</hi> and ſtifle the <hi>ſoul:</hi> were it alwayes in <hi>excretion</hi> and <hi>emiſſion,</hi> the body would <hi>waſte</hi> away and be <hi>reduced</hi> to nothing.</p>
               <p>Nor is the receiving <hi>in</hi> of any thing, <hi>ſufficient</hi> and <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> to the body for its preſervation; but <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi> by Nature, <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>ſutable:</hi> nor <hi>emiſſion</hi> or <hi>ejection</hi> of <hi>any</hi> thing, but <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> and <hi>unneceſſary</hi> to be retained.</p>
               <p>If <hi>ſleep prevails</hi> contrary to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> the body in a <hi>lethargick ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriferous</hi> inactivity, ſtupefied and <hi>ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> lies at the gates of death.</p>
               <p>If <hi>watching</hi> exceeds the <hi>limits,</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth and <hi>ſteals</hi> away the due time for <hi>ſleep;</hi> the faculties are <hi>debilitated</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ervated, the <hi>ſpirits tyred,</hi> worn out and impoveriſhed.</p>
               <p>If <hi>inſpiration</hi> were conſtant without <hi>intermiſſion,</hi> the body would <hi>puff</hi> up and be <hi>blown</hi> like a Bladder.</p>
               <p>If <hi>expiration</hi> were <hi>continual,</hi> the ſoul and ſpirits would ſoon <hi>quit</hi> their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and come forth.</p>
               <p>If alwayes <hi>exerciſed</hi> in <hi>motion,</hi> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy would <hi>pine</hi> and <hi>wear</hi> away: if alwayes at <hi>reſt,</hi> it would <hi>corrupt</hi> and ſtink.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110713:15"/>There is a <hi>rule</hi> therefore, <hi>proportion, meaſure</hi> and <hi>ſeaſon</hi> to be obſerved, in all the requiſite <hi>ſupports</hi> &amp; <hi>auxiliary</hi> helps, <hi>belonging</hi> to our <hi>preſervation;</hi> and by <hi>how much,</hi> or often, any of theſe neceſſary <hi>alternative</hi> ſucceſſions are <hi>extravagant</hi> and <hi>irregular,</hi> exceeding the <hi>bounds</hi> and <hi>limits</hi> preſcribed by Nature, <hi>juſtling</hi> out the <hi>ſucceſſive</hi> appointed <hi>action, duty,</hi> or <hi>cuſtom,</hi> from its <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> exerciſe and <hi>due</hi> execution; by ſo much is the <hi>harmony</hi> of Nature diſturbed, <hi>vigor</hi> aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and duration <hi>ſhortned,</hi> by theſe <hi>jars, diſcords</hi> and <hi>encroachments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>thwarting</hi> and <hi>croſſing</hi> of Nature in any thing ſhe hath enjoyned, either in the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> or <hi>circumſtance,</hi> is <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> offered to Nature; &amp; is <hi>deſtructive</hi> more or leſs according to the <hi>dignity</hi> or <hi>quality</hi> of the thing appointed: For, Nature was not <hi>ſo indifferent</hi> in the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of theſe <hi>duties</hi> and <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> that they might be <hi>done</hi> or not <hi>done;</hi> or ſo <hi>careleſs</hi> and <hi>irregular,</hi> to leave them at your pleaſure, <hi>when</hi> and <hi>how;</hi> or to be uſed <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> &amp; <hi>prepoſterouſly</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>order,</hi> at the liberty of your <hi>will, fancy</hi> and <hi>occaſions:</hi> for, as you may ſee in all other creatures, <hi>exactneſs</hi> of <hi>rule,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110713:15"/>
method</hi> and conſtant <hi>order</hi> impreſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>radicated</hi> in their natures, by which they act <hi>alwayes</hi> ſutable, regular, and conſtant: you may not imagine ſo <hi>choice</hi> and <hi>exquiſite</hi> a piece as <hi>Man,</hi> to be left without a <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> to <hi>guide</hi> and <hi>ſteer</hi> him in the neceſſary actions concerning <hi>Life;</hi> and that he ſhould <hi>rove</hi> in <hi>uncertain, unconſtant, unlimited</hi> quantities, times, orders, manners, and the like; but is <hi>bounded</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained</hi> upon <hi>penalties</hi> and <hi>forfeitures</hi> of <hi>Being, well being,</hi> and <hi>long being,</hi> to the nice and ſtrict <hi>obſervance</hi> of theſe <hi>laws</hi> and <hi>cuſtomes</hi> neceſſary for the <hi>tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> of humane frailty.</p>
               <p>As <hi>moral</hi> good <hi>actions</hi> are placed in a <hi>mediocrity</hi> between two <hi>vitious</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams; ſo <hi>natural</hi> actions and <hi>auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> requiſites <hi>conſervative</hi> of life, have their <hi>golden meane</hi> digreſſion from which, on either ſide, leads to ruine and deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Too</hi> much <hi>ſleep,</hi> or <hi>too</hi> little; <hi>too</hi> much <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drink,</hi> or <hi>too</hi> little; <hi>too</hi> much <hi>reſt,</hi> or <hi>too</hi> much <hi>motion; too</hi> much <hi>Air,</hi> or alwayes <hi>cloſe</hi> pent up; <hi>too</hi> great <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions,</hi> or <hi>too</hi> long <hi>retentions; too</hi> much
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110713:16"/>
                  <hi>heat,</hi> or <hi>too</hi> much <hi>cold;</hi> either of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams lead to ruine. And as <hi>Nature</hi> hath not appointed <hi>any thing,</hi> or <hi>every thing</hi> to be food, but <hi>this</hi> and <hi>that;</hi> ſo likewiſe not at <hi>any time</hi> to be received, not in <hi>any quantity,</hi> after <hi>any manner</hi> prepared, or in <hi>what order</hi> you pleaſe, but <hi>proportionable, ſuteable</hi> and <hi>conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As there is <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>diſpoſitions</hi> and <hi>inclinations</hi> of mind agreeing with, and likeing one thing, but <hi>diſagreeing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting,</hi> and <hi>diſliking</hi> another: ſo is it in the <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>food:</hi> one <hi>body</hi> is of this <hi>conſtitutional</hi> propriety, temper and appetite; will ſute and agree well with this <hi>meat,</hi> and <hi>diſagree</hi> with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for if all <hi>meats</hi> were <hi>convenient</hi> for <hi>all</hi> bodies, to be uſed <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> without <hi>choice,</hi> how comes it to paſs the <hi>antipathy, reſiſtance,</hi> and <hi>abhorrency</hi> of ſome <hi>bodies</hi> againſt ſome <hi>particular meats?</hi> And this not from a <hi>fancy</hi> and <hi>conceit,</hi> but radicated in the <hi>conſtitution;</hi> that if it be eaten, though <hi>unknown,</hi> ſhall produce <hi>Fluxes, Vomitings, Swoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>effects:</hi> here is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted the <hi>oppoſition, diſagreement,</hi> and <hi>diſtance</hi> between this <hi>conſtitution</hi> and this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110713:16"/>
kind of <hi>meat;</hi> which being ſo great, that the <hi>diſlike</hi> and <hi>diſcordancy</hi> appears preſently: other <hi>diſagreements</hi> which are in a <hi>lower</hi> degree of <hi>oppoſition,</hi> do not manifeſt themſelves <hi>immediately,</hi> yet they produce ill <hi>effects</hi> in the body, <hi>plus minus, pro viribus;</hi> which diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>gradually,</hi> at <hi>times,</hi> and <hi>ſeaſons,</hi> and <hi>occaſions.</hi> If you acknowledge the former, you muſt admit of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the reaſon is, <hi>á majori ad minus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As <hi>ſleep</hi> is appointed by Nature, to <hi>refreſh</hi> the ſpirits, &amp; repair loſt ſtrength: ſo the <hi>time</hi> for <hi>ſleep</hi> is appointed and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited; not when you pleaſe: the <hi>Sun,</hi> that glorious Light, was not made for you to <hi>ſleep by,</hi> nor the <hi>night</hi> for ſports, and revells, or buſineſs, but for <hi>reſt.</hi> Nature does not onely command <hi>what</hi> to be done, but <hi>when, how much, how long,</hi> after <hi>what manner,</hi> in <hi>what order;</hi> the <hi>modification, circumſtances</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite qualifications,</hi> as well as the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf, are to be regarded. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by a diligent <hi>inquiſition,</hi> and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>ſpeculation</hi> into the <hi>works</hi> of Nature, you may as much <hi>admire</hi> the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>preſervation, government, order, weight,</hi> and <hi>meaſure, regular viciſſitudes, alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110713:17"/>
and <hi>ſucceſſions,</hi> as the <hi>excellency</hi> and <hi>contrivance</hi> of the things themſelves in their <hi>creation</hi> and <hi>generation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatever is appointed by Nature as <hi>neceſſary</hi> for <hi>conſervation</hi> and <hi>ſupport</hi> of <hi>Being,</hi> though never ſo good; yet if it be <hi>unſeaſonable,</hi> out of <hi>courſe, immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> in <hi>quantity, quality</hi> or <hi>duration;</hi> alters the <hi>property</hi> and <hi>intention</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>converts</hi> good <hi>purpoſes</hi> to bad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
               <p>We ſay every thing is beſt in its own kind; and of <hi>continuance</hi> in its own <hi>Element:</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> is moſt chearful, vigorous and durable in the <hi>courſe</hi> and <hi>method</hi> of her own <hi>injunctions:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put by, thruſt out of her own way, is not of <hi>long duration:</hi> the Birds can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live in the <hi>Sea,</hi> nor the Fiſh upon the <hi>Land;</hi> nor your <hi>Nature</hi> continue long in an <hi>unnatural way</hi> againſt her ſelf. Are you compoſed of <hi>natural principles,</hi> and will you not live conformable to what you are? Do you not live by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> aſſiſtance and <hi>natural means,</hi> and do you think to continue long in a <hi>Counter-motion</hi> againſt the nature of your Compoſition? They that invert natures courſe, prepoſterouſly, promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110713:17"/>
and incongruouſly uſing the neceſſary <hi>conſervatives</hi> of life; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are deprived of their benefit, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo receive a <hi>poſitive hurt;</hi> diſordering the conſtant <hi>regular motions</hi> in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and diſcompoſing the <hi>harmonious</hi> and <hi>ſociable</hi> aſſiſtance of the parts in their Offices.</p>
               <p>There is a <hi>rule</hi> therefore, <hi>method, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> and <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> in all the requiſite <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports</hi> and auxiliary <hi>helps</hi> belonging and neceſſary unto life, or natural <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>cuſtoms</hi> whatſoever; which duely obſerved, are of much <hi>advantage</hi> for the <hi>preſervation</hi> of the body in its true <hi>natural ſtate, vigor</hi> and <hi>prolongation</hi> of <hi>Being:</hi> but otherwiſe, a <hi>methodically</hi> and <hi>inordinately</hi> uſed, diſturbs <hi>Natures courſe, uniformity</hi> and <hi>regularity</hi> of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, raiſeth unnatural motions, <hi>commotions</hi> and <hi>ceſſations;</hi> introduceth <hi>diſorders,</hi> and <hi>disjoynes</hi> the frame of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, accelerates and haſtens the <hi>diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:110713:18"/>
                  <hi>The Impediments of long Life, are,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>An infirm and weak conſtitution from the <hi>Womb;</hi> derived from tender, imbecile and infirm <hi>Parents.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Irregular and unfit tractation of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,</hi> whoſe tender bodies are ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed &amp; diſordered by bad <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> their erroneous <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> and the ill <hi>properties</hi> of their Milk.</item>
                     <item>Noxious and intemperate Air.</item>
                     <item>Irregular <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Immoderate and unſeaſonable <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe,</hi> motion or <hi>labour.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Too much; or unfit <hi>reſt,</hi> in the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances attending.</item>
                     <item>Sleeping and waking in extreams.</item>
                     <item>Immoderate <hi>Venus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Undue <hi>excretion</hi> and <hi>retention</hi> of Excrements.</item>
                     <item>Inordinate <hi>paſſions,</hi> and perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>mind.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>All unneceſſary and bad <hi>cuſtoms,</hi> as virulent <hi>Purgations;</hi> frequent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary <hi>Phlebotomies;</hi> immoderate uſe of <hi>Tobaco.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110713:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> The Preſervation of Health.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIu &amp; bene Valere;</hi> To live <hi>long</hi> and in <hi>health,</hi> ſaid <hi>Plato,</hi> is the beſt thing in the World: and <hi>Thales Mileſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> one of the ſeven <hi>Greek Sages,</hi> being asked who was the <hi>happy Man?</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, He that hath a <hi>healthy body:</hi> preferring <hi>health</hi> before <hi>riches</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> or any <hi>earthly enjoyment.</hi> The truth of this <hi>Opinion</hi> will beſt be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and proved, by conſulting with the <hi>ſick man,</hi> who is <hi>beſt able</hi> to judge of <hi>health,</hi> and knows rightly the <hi>value</hi> of it. <hi>Experimentally</hi> he hath found, that a <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Scepter,</hi> gives no <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> nor <hi>eaſe</hi> to a <hi>pained languiſhing</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Health.</note> and <hi>beauty</hi> brings no <hi>pleaſure</hi> to a <hi>ſick Bed:</hi> and <hi>dainty Diſhes</hi> affect not the <hi>diſtemper'd Pallate</hi> with delight. Nor the <hi>ſweeteſt Muſick</hi> can recreate a <hi>reſtleſs faint-ſick-man:</hi> but the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>health alone</hi> is more <hi>ſweet</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110713:19"/>
                  <hi>pleaſant,</hi> and far more <hi>deſirable</hi> then <hi>all theſe</hi> without it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet</hi> who is <hi>he</hi> that values <hi>health</hi> at the <hi>rate</hi> it is <hi>worth?</hi> Not <hi>he</hi> that hath it; <hi>he</hi> reckons it amongſt the <hi>common ordinary</hi> enjoyments; and takes as <hi>little notice</hi> of it, or <hi>leſs</hi> regards it, then his long <hi>worn Cloathes:</hi> perhaps more <hi>careful</hi> of his <hi>Garments,</hi> remembring their <hi>price;</hi> but thinks his <hi>health</hi> coſt him <hi>nothing;</hi> and coming to him at ſo eaſie a <hi>rate,</hi> values it accordingly, and hath little <hi>regard</hi> to keep it; is never truly <hi>ſenſible</hi> of what he <hi>enjoyed,</hi> until he finds the <hi>want</hi> of it by <hi>ſickneſs;</hi> then <hi>hoc unum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>health</hi> above <hi>all things</hi> is earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and wiſhed for.</p>
               <p>This great concernment <hi>Health,</hi> falls under a <hi>three-fold</hi> conſideration: Firſt, In its cauſes from whence it does <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately</hi> ariſe in the body. Secondly, In its <hi>effects,</hi> the <hi>conſequents</hi> and <hi>benefits</hi> that <hi>accrue</hi> to us by it, and what is the <hi>ſtate</hi> of a <hi>healthy</hi> man. Thirdly, The right <hi>courſe</hi> to obtain, and <hi>means</hi> to <hi>preſerve</hi> this invaluable <hi>treaſure,</hi> ſo long as the <hi>capacity</hi> of <hi>humane nature</hi> will admit.</p>
               <p>And firſt, Here we muſt <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> of <hi>Health,</hi> which may be taken either
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110713:19"/>
                  <hi>ſtrictly</hi> or <hi>largely:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Health di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> 
                  <hi>health</hi> in the <hi>ſtricteſt acceptation,</hi> admits of no <hi>organical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition, morbous</hi> effect, or <hi>morbifick Seminary</hi> to abide in the body; that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though no <hi>ſenſible</hi> injury, or <hi>inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> alteration may appear; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding a <hi>perſon</hi> may be ſaid not to be in <hi>perfect health:</hi> as when the <hi>latent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries</hi> of Diſeaſes are not <hi>budded,</hi> do not <hi>ſprout</hi> forth ſo as to be <hi>dolorous,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedite any <hi>faculty,</hi> or make ſome <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance</hi> or <hi>alteration;</hi> yet they are <hi>planted</hi> in the body, and have a <hi>real Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> as <hi>haereditary Diſeaſes,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries</hi> are obſcured, do not come to <hi>maturity</hi> of <hi>production</hi> until ſuch an <hi>Age</hi> of the Perſon, or ſome <hi>irritating occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> given to <hi>produce</hi> it <hi>ſooner</hi> or <hi>later,</hi> as the perſon is ordered <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill</hi> in the <hi>diaetetick regiment.</hi> So likewiſe the firſt <hi>ground-work</hi> and foundation of the <hi>ſtone</hi> is not <hi>perceptible,</hi> until ſome time and progreſs give it <hi>perfection;</hi> during which <hi>time</hi> that perſon is not in a <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>health</hi> in a <hi>ſtrict ſence.</hi> So likewiſe ſome <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> do lie <hi>dormant</hi> for a <hi>time,</hi> and diſcover <hi>nothing</hi> during that <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> and have their <hi>periodick motions,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they <hi>awake,</hi> and are <hi>ſtirred</hi> up to ſhew
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110713:20"/>
themſelves, upon ſome <hi>irritating provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> and occaſions given: as the <hi>epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſie,</hi> the <hi>Gout, Hyſterical paſſions,</hi> and ſuch like, that have their times of <hi>ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> and <hi>returns:</hi> yet theſe during their <hi>intermiſſions</hi> and <hi>ceſſations</hi> from hoſtility, are in <hi>being,</hi> although they do not <hi>act</hi> ſo as to <hi>injure</hi> and <hi>deprave</hi> any function <hi>ſenſibly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Health</hi> may be taken <hi>largely,</hi> and in the common <hi>acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> as when no <hi>function</hi> is <hi>impedited,</hi> or <hi>ſenſible alteration</hi> from a good <hi>ſtate</hi> does appear: we ſay then, ſuch a man is in <hi>health.</hi> In the firſt and ſtricteſt <hi>ſenſe,</hi> few can be ſaid to be in <hi>health;</hi> but in the latter, many are to be accounted <hi>healthful.</hi> And this is the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>health</hi> underſtood by <hi>Galen, Avicen,</hi> and <hi>Averrboes,</hi> in their <hi>definitions</hi> of it. Which imports thus much.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Health what it is.</note>
                  <hi>Health</hi> is a due <hi>power</hi> and <hi>aptitude</hi> for the exerciſe &amp; diſcharge of all the <hi>facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> in the body. So that when every part and <hi>faculty</hi> perform their duty <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly</hi> and <hi>vigorouſly,</hi> that man is ſaid to be in <hi>health:</hi> but when any <hi>faculty</hi> is <hi>impedited,</hi> ill <hi>affected,</hi> or <hi>depraved</hi> in its <hi>function,</hi> the man then is not in <hi>perfect
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110713:20"/>
health.</hi> So that the <hi>actions</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> and <hi>mind</hi> are the chief diſcoverers of <hi>health</hi> and <hi>ſickneſs:</hi> And here we ſee that <hi>health</hi> is <hi>ſeated</hi> in the <hi>faculties,</hi> and does <hi>aſſurge</hi> or <hi>reſult</hi> from the <hi>regular</hi> diſcharge of their <hi>functions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As when the appetite is <hi>ſharp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Signs of Health.</note> the <hi>digeſtion</hi> not <hi>ſluggiſh</hi> and heavy: the <hi>belly</hi> ſoluble; the <hi>ſenſes</hi> perfect, free from <hi>pain</hi> in all <hi>parts:</hi> the <hi>mind</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; <hi>quiet ſleeps;</hi> the <hi>ſpirits</hi> brisk and lively; the whole <hi>body</hi> ſtrong, nimble and vigorous in motion; theſe are <hi>ſigns</hi> of <hi>Health:</hi> ſo that examining all <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>faculties,</hi> we find nothing <hi>preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> or <hi>irregular;</hi> but in every <hi>part</hi> and <hi>faculty</hi> we find a good <hi>diſcharge</hi> of their <hi>Office:</hi> then that perſon is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted in a <hi>right ſtate</hi> of health, ſo far as is <hi>diſcoverable</hi> by any <hi>manifeſt</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural ſign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>benefits</hi> and <hi>excellencies</hi> of this <hi>health</hi> is beſt known to thoſe that have loſt it; <hi>Carendo magis quam fruendo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Excellency of Health poſitive.</note> 
                  <hi>quid valeat cognoſcimus:</hi> You that have it and know not how to <hi>prize</hi> it, I'le tell you what it is, that you may love it better, put a higher <hi>value</hi> upon it, and endeavour to <hi>preſerve</hi> it with a more <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110713:21"/>
ſtrict</hi> obſervance and tuition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Health</hi> is <hi>that</hi> which makes your <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> both <hi>ſavory</hi> and <hi>pleaſant;</hi> elſe Natures injunction of <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking,</hi> were a hard task and ſlaviſh cuſtom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Health</hi> is <hi>that</hi> which makes your <hi>bed eaſie,</hi> and your <hi>ſleep refreſhing:</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news your <hi>ſtrength</hi> with the riſing Sun; and makes you <hi>chearful</hi> at the light of another <hi>day:</hi> 'tis that which fills up the hollow and uneven places of your <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe,</hi> and makes your body <hi>plump</hi> and <hi>comely:</hi> 'tis that which <hi>dreſſeth</hi> you up in Natures <hi>richeſt Attire,</hi> and <hi>adorns</hi> your face with her <hi>choiceſt</hi> colours.</p>
               <p>'Tis <hi>that</hi> which makes <hi>exerciſe</hi> a <hi>ſport;</hi> and walking abroad, the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of your <hi>Liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis <hi>that</hi> which makes <hi>fertile,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the natural <hi>endowments</hi> of your mind, and preſerves them <hi>long</hi> from <hi>decay;</hi> makes your <hi>wit</hi> acute, and your <hi>memory retentive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis <hi>that</hi> which ſupports the <hi>fragility</hi> of a corruptible body, and <hi>preſerves</hi> the <hi>verdure, vigour</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> of youth.</p>
               <p>'Tis <hi>that</hi> which makes the <hi>ſoul</hi> take
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110713:21"/>
delight in her <hi>manſion;</hi> ſporting her ſelf at the caſements of your eyes.</p>
               <p>'Tis <hi>that</hi> which makes <hi>pleaſure</hi> to be <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and delights delightful; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which you can ſolace your ſelf in nothing of <hi>terrene</hi> felicities and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Having curſorily glanced at the <hi>excellencies</hi> of <hi>Health,</hi> in this ſhort <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative</hi> and <hi>Epitome</hi> of its <hi>worth;</hi> it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains we ſhould next draw forth and preſent to your view, the <hi>wayes</hi> and <hi>means</hi> to obtain and preſerve this inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable enjoyment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Health,</hi> as it is the <hi>reſult</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> in her <hi>integrity</hi> and <hi>perfection;</hi> is <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> and <hi>kept</hi> in that <hi>order</hi> and due <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy,</hi> by the regular and right uſe of thoſe <hi>natural</hi> ſupports that our bodies daily require and do depend on in <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> as <hi>Air, Food, Sleep, Exerciſe,</hi> &amp;c. Now thoſe things that do <hi>neceſſarily</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and daily attend us, ought <hi>ſo</hi> to be <hi>choſen</hi> and <hi>mannaged,</hi> as does beſt <hi>conduce</hi> and <hi>ſute</hi> with the <hi>inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> to which they are appointed; but if otherwiſe, <hi>unſeaſonably, diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> or <hi>immoderately</hi> uſed; they then prove <hi>pernicious</hi> and <hi>deſtructive,</hi> more
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110713:22"/>
or leſs, according to the <hi>degree</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance</hi> of their <hi>irregularity</hi> and <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruouſneſs.</hi> Nature hath appointed both <hi>times</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> and ſet a regular courſe, how and when every thing ſhould be uſed in its proper <hi>mode</hi> and <hi>ſeaſon:</hi> There is a <hi>moderation</hi> alſo <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned,</hi> and <hi>limits preſcribed</hi> by Nature in the uſe of theſe things, which if we <hi>exceed</hi> and run into <hi>exceſs,</hi> we then put <hi>Nature</hi> out of her <hi>mediocrity</hi> and <hi>equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> in which <hi>courſe</hi> ſhe cannot long continue; and that alſo with much trouble to us, by <hi>bodily diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities,</hi> the neceſſary <hi>conſequents</hi> of ſuch <hi>irregularities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> is as a curious <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine</hi> or <hi>Clook-work,</hi> moving with divers <hi>Wheels,</hi> and various internal <hi>motions,</hi> ſubordinate to each other, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the general deſign of the whole; in a compleat order and exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite method of contrivance, promoting and moving one another in their <hi>diſtinct Offices.</hi> Now if one <hi>Wheel</hi> goes too <hi>faſt,</hi> too <hi>ſlow,</hi> or <hi>ſtops,</hi> the reſt that depend upon that <hi>motion</hi> alſo, are <hi>diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered</hi> and move <hi>irregular.</hi> So is it in the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Man:</hi> If the <hi>Stomach</hi> be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110713:22"/>
clogged, and the digeſtion ſluggiſh; the ſupply from thence will not come in due time to the other <hi>faculties</hi> to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate upon: and if the <hi>Chyliferous</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent from the <hi>Stomach</hi> be not well <hi>tranſmuted</hi> and <hi>qualified,</hi> the reſt of the digeſtive <hi>faculties</hi> cannot <hi>ſo well</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their task, becauſe the <hi>alimentary</hi> matter is not <hi>tranſmitted</hi> to them <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>ſuteable,</hi> but <hi>imperfect, aliene</hi> and <hi>degenerate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt <hi>experimentally</hi> and <hi>ſenſibly</hi> know; that <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing either in quantity or quality, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably taken, does abate and injure a good <hi>Stomach,</hi> and depraves the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion: which defect redounds to the detriment of the <hi>whole,</hi> and all the body ſuffers by it, and every <hi>faculty</hi> in time will ſhare in the <hi>prejudice:</hi> So that of neceſſity there muſt be <hi>rules</hi> obſerved, and <hi>bounds</hi> ſet in the uſe of theſe things, without which mans <hi>body</hi> is ſoon put out of frame, and the <hi>regular Oeconomy</hi> thereof diſcompoſed and diſordered.</p>
               <p>To prove and illuſtrate this farther by inſtance: freſh <hi>Air</hi> is neceſſary to <hi>ventilate</hi> the body, and chear the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> of man; and he that is <hi>pent</hi> up
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110713:23"/>
within <hi>doors,</hi> is deprived of that great enlivener and refreſher of <hi>Nature:</hi> but on the contrary, he that is expoſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to the <hi>night Air,</hi> is as much dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged as the other; and both prove <hi>injurious</hi> and <hi>deſtructive:</hi> So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the open <hi>Air</hi> be <hi>good</hi> and <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> for the <hi>healthful being</hi> of Man, yet not at all <hi>times,</hi> not in any <hi>condition,</hi> and upon any <hi>tearms,</hi> but <hi>ſuteable</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient</hi> with the <hi>ſtate</hi> of our bodies, as <hi>Nature</hi> hath <hi>appointed</hi> for you, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe for <hi>Exerciſe</hi> and <hi>Reſt, Method</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> is to be obſerved: for if there be not <hi>ſeaſons</hi> allotted, and a <hi>moderation</hi> uſed in theſe, they both are <hi>deſtructive,</hi> though in a <hi>contrary</hi> way, and by <hi>different mediums.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The order of Nature to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</note>To <hi>ſleep</hi> when you ſhould <hi>wake,</hi> or <hi>wake</hi> when you ſhould <hi>ſleep,</hi> are <hi>both</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious and impairing of <hi>health:</hi> to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> the <hi>order</hi> of Nature, by <hi>ſleeping</hi> in the <hi>day,</hi> and <hi>watching</hi> in the <hi>night,</hi> is <hi>incongruous</hi> and <hi>unſuteable</hi> with your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; becauſe it <hi>croſſeth</hi> the <hi>deſignment</hi> of <hi>Nature.</hi> When the <hi>Sun</hi> riſeth, the ſpirits of Men are then moſt <hi>apt</hi> and <hi>fit</hi> for Action; are then moſt <hi>lively, brisk</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:110713:23"/>
and <hi>chearful</hi> in their <hi>functions:</hi> but when the <hi>Sun ſets,</hi> and the <hi>Air</hi> cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>darkneſs;</hi> the <hi>ſpirits</hi> then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to <hi>droop,</hi> grow more <hi>dull</hi> and <hi>heavy,</hi> incline to <hi>reſt, retirement</hi> and a <hi>ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Now to <hi>ſpur</hi> up and <hi>rouſe</hi> the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> when they naturally would be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>reſpite;</hi> or laying a <hi>clog</hi> upon them, by your <hi>ſluggiſhneſs</hi> and <hi>ſomnolent poſtures,</hi> when <hi>Nature</hi> calls upon them for <hi>action,</hi> (by darting the <hi>glittering light</hi> through the <hi>Air,</hi> with which they are <hi>affected</hi> and <hi>raiſed</hi> up) theſe are great <hi>injuries</hi> and <hi>affronts</hi> to Nature, in acting <hi>counter</hi> to her <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> and <hi>inſtitutions;</hi> for which you muſt ſuffer the <hi>penalty;</hi> and that is the <hi>forfeiting</hi> your <hi>health,</hi> for this <hi>unnatural</hi> diſobedience, and <hi>irrational</hi> courſes.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Precautions</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> I will aſſure you are not the <hi>inventions</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> to <hi>curb</hi> your darling <hi>inclinations,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain</hi> you of your juſt <hi>liberty;</hi> but they are the <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> enjoyned to be <hi>obſerved,</hi> for your own <hi>preſervation</hi> and well-<hi>being;</hi> and as <hi>bounds</hi> ſet to <hi>check</hi> your <hi>extravagant pernicious actions;</hi> and all for the <hi>tuition</hi> and <hi>ſafety</hi> of your <hi>life</hi> and <hi>health;</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110713:24"/>
to <hi>preſerve</hi> the <hi>regular harmony</hi> through the whole <hi>courſe</hi> of <hi>Nature.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be an old ſaying, as <hi>fooliſh</hi> as <hi>common; Qui Medicè vivit, miſerè vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit;</hi> He that lives ſtrictly by rule, lives miſerably: yet I muſt affirm the <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> grounded upon pure <hi>reaſon,</hi> and the preceding <hi>diſcourſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an irregular life.</note> that he which does not obſerve the <hi>injunctions,</hi> the due <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> and <hi>regular courſe</hi> of <hi>Nature;</hi> does both <hi>ſhorten</hi> his <hi>life,</hi> and takes away much of the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of it, by procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring an <hi>uncomfortable</hi> and <hi>unhealthy</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>I know every of you would live <hi>long;</hi> but eſpecially in <hi>health:</hi> you would fain <hi>continue</hi> and <hi>prolong</hi> your <hi>youth;</hi> your <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>ability</hi> of <hi>parts:</hi> you are <hi>frighted</hi> at the thoughts of a <hi>wrinkled face,</hi> or a <hi>reſtleſs bed;</hi> an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſom diſeaſed</hi> body, and a <hi>decrepid loathſom</hi> old <hi>Age:</hi> But yet you will not avoid theſe <hi>evils</hi> that you ſo much <hi>fear:</hi> you will not take the <hi>pains</hi> to <hi>prevent</hi> them, and <hi>ſecure</hi> your ſelf: you rather take <hi>more pains;</hi> undergoe <hi>more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to <hi>procure</hi> them, then there can be in <hi>avoiding</hi> them: nay, you loſe the true <hi>pleaſure</hi> of your <hi>life</hi> to <hi>purchaſe</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:110713:24"/>
theſe <hi>inconveniencies.</hi> Now what <hi>thoſe</hi> things are, which ſo <hi>warily</hi> and <hi>choicely</hi> you are to <hi>obſerve,</hi> (wherein <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts</hi> your <hi>health</hi> and <hi>well-being</hi>) have been <hi>hinted</hi> before: the due <hi>method, courſe,</hi> and <hi>cautions,</hi> you are to take in the <hi>uſe</hi> of them, particularly ſhall be <hi>handled</hi> in their due <hi>place</hi> and <hi>order.</hi> But firſt we muſt briefly treat of <hi>Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and a <hi>valitudinary</hi> life; and ſhew you the great <hi>difference</hi> between that <hi>decaying</hi> condition, and a <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>health;</hi> which <hi>Antitheſis</hi> will prepare and <hi>ſtir</hi> you up to the <hi>ſtrictneſs</hi> of <hi>duty;</hi> make you more <hi>cautious,</hi> and <hi>ſollicitous</hi> for the <hi>preſervation</hi> of your <hi>health,</hi> and <hi>prize</hi> it as the <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> your greateſt <hi>enjoyment</hi> in this <hi>life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110713:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Of Sickneſs, and a Valetudinary State.</head>
               <p>IN the preceding Section, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a brief <hi>ſurvey</hi> of natural life in the beſt eſtate; graced and adorned with the ſociety of <hi>health,</hi> and its great <hi>attendants;</hi> the concomitant benefits, <hi>priviledges</hi> and enjoyments: now take a view of your ſelf when <hi>health</hi> hath turn'd its back upon you, and deſerts your <hi>company;</hi> ſee then how the <hi>Scene</hi> is changed; how you are rob'd and ſpoiled of all your comforts and <hi>enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>want</hi> of <hi>health</hi> makes food to loſe its wonted <hi>reliſh,</hi> and is become <hi>diſguſtful</hi> and <hi>unſavoury:</hi> the <hi>ſtomach</hi> now refuſeth to receive its daily charge; no longer able to perform the <hi>task,</hi> but deſires a <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> from the office.</p>
               <p>Sleep that was ſtretcht out from <hi>even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to the fair <hi>bright day,</hi> is now broken into pieces, and <hi>ſubdivided,</hi> not worth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110713:25"/>
the accounting: the <hi>night</hi> that before ſeemed <hi>ſhort,</hi> is now too <hi>long;</hi> and the downy bed preſſeth hard againſt the bones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exerciſe</hi> now is <hi>toyling,</hi> and walking abroad the carrying of a <hi>burthen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The body that moved ſo <hi>light,</hi> and readily obeyed the ſteerage of the <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot;</hi> is now over-<hi>ballac'd</hi> with its own <hi>weight,</hi> and ſlowly tugs as againſt the ſtream.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conjugal imbraces</hi> are now but the faint offers of <hi>love;</hi> the ſhadows and repreſentations of former kindneſs.</p>
               <p>The body that had the <hi>magnatiſm</hi> and ſecret attraction of ſouls; may now be approached without loſs; or danger of being ſnared and fettered as a <hi>bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Lilly</hi> and the <hi>Roſe</hi> that Nature planted in the higheſt <hi>Mount,</hi> to ſhew the World her pride and glory; is now <hi>blaſted</hi> and <hi>withered</hi> like long blown flowers.</p>
               <p>The <hi>eye</hi> that flaſht as lightning, is now like the <hi>opacous</hi> body of a thick Cloud, that roled from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt</hi> ſwifter then a <hi>Celeſtial Orb;</hi> is now tyred and weary, but ſtanding ſtill; that penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110713:26"/>
the <hi>Center</hi> of another <hi>microcoſm;</hi> hath loſt its Planetary influence, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obtuſe and dull.</p>
               <p>The hollow ſounding breaſt that <hi>echoed</hi> to the chanting <hi>Bird;</hi> and warb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led forth delightful tunes; now runs <hi>diviſions</hi> with coughing ſtrains, and pauſes with a deep fetch't ſigh for <hi>breath,</hi> to repeat thoſe <hi>notes</hi> again.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Venal</hi> and <hi>Arterial</hi> Rivulets that ran with <hi>vital</hi> ſtreams, bedewing the adjacent parts with fruitful moiſture, is now drunk up with <hi>parching heat;</hi> or muddied and defiled with an <hi>inundation</hi> of excremental humours.</p>
               <p>The want of <hi>health</hi> converts your Houſe into a <hi>Priſon;</hi> and <hi>confines</hi> you to the narrow compaſs of a <hi>Chamber;</hi> 'tis that which ſowers the ſweeteſt and moſt beloved <hi>enjoyments:</hi> 'tis that which <hi>diſunites</hi> and breaks the league of <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partnerſhip</hi> between <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>body;</hi> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enates and makes them at <hi>jars;</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſeth their <hi>harmony,</hi> and weary of their wonted ſweet ſociety.</p>
               <p>A ſick man is like a <hi>Clock</hi> out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and due motion; which is of little worth or uſe, ſo long as it continues in that condition; ſo is man uſeleſs both
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110713:26"/>
to himſelf and others in ſuch a <hi>ſtate:</hi> one <hi>Wheel</hi> being faulty or defective, puts the reſt out of order and regulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that depend upon that motion: and one <hi>part</hi> or <hi>faculty</hi> of Mans body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſordered and irregular; ſeveral others conſent with, or ſhare in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſure <hi>more</hi> or <hi>fewer;</hi> as the part is more <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>principal,</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome chief Region of the Body; or <hi>inferior,</hi> and of a lower <hi>orb,</hi> or private ſtation. The reaſon of this <hi>ſympathy</hi> and conſent of patts is; firſt, From the <hi>general agent</hi> and <hi>principle</hi> of life, which is one and the ſame throughout the whole: Secondly, Becauſe all the <hi>parts</hi> of <hi>mans</hi> body, though they have their <hi>peculiar</hi> and different motions to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and <hi>ſpecial properties;</hi> yet they are all concurrent and cooperating; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately or ſubordinately, ſerving to the general deſign of <hi>Nature,</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of the whole body; and are ſo concatenated and linked together, in the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of office, that their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are <hi>dependant,</hi> and of mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for each others wellfare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humane bodies</hi> being in a fluxible ſtate, and apt for mutation and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110713:27"/>
are not long in a <hi>through</hi> ſtate of health; but ſome part or other, by ſome accident, natural debility, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly living; is diſcompoſed and jarring, whereby the <hi>Oeconomical har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> is diſturbed. The <hi>ſigns</hi> of ſuch <hi>defections,</hi> and a preternatural change of the body approaching, is diſcovered by the <hi>ſenſes,</hi> our own, or others, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king obſervation. And theſe <hi>ſignal marks</hi> are very apparent to reaſonable diſcerning perſons; that every one may have ſome apprehenſions (if they will be <hi>cautilous</hi>) of <hi>ſickneſs</hi> coming upon them, and a <hi>diſcraſyed</hi> body.</p>
               <p>As a ſtate of <hi>Health</hi> is known by all <hi>parts</hi> acting in their Offices unblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; that viewing and examining from <hi>head</hi> to <hi>foot,</hi> nothing appears unwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or diſordered: So on the contrary, when any <hi>part</hi> declines its duty, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears any way unwonted from its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral condition; declares the beginning of a <hi>degenerate valetudinary</hi> ſtate; which in time will dammage and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>whole;</hi> if not prevented in that particular <hi>part,</hi> and a ſtop given to that defection. Now what this part is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther principal or inferior; of a general
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110713:27"/>
or more <hi>private</hi> uſe; and how the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice does ariſe, is neceſſary to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; which will diſcover whether the infirmity be of <hi>greater</hi> or <hi>leſſer</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern; of <hi>ſpeedy</hi> or <hi>ſlower</hi> danger: So that by noting ſuch <hi>ſigns,</hi> which are the fore-runners, and warnings of great <hi>diſeaſes</hi> coming on, every one may in time look out for means to check the preſent evil, and avoid the greater threatned.</p>
               <p>If the Body which was <hi>fat,</hi> or <hi>plump</hi> and <hi>fleſhy;</hi> afterwards grows <hi>lean</hi> and <hi>thin:</hi> or if <hi>lean</hi> and <hi>ſpare</hi> bodies grow <hi>big</hi> and <hi>corpulent;</hi> here is juſt cauſe of ſuſpition, that all is not right, although no great prejudice at preſent, or ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble injury by the alteration: yet theſe <hi>caſes</hi> require due examination, from whence they do proceed. If the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite</hi> abate; or unwonted heavineſs and fulneſs follow eating, argues the <hi>dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> not good, and the <hi>Stomach</hi> falling from the due diſcharge of its duty and office. The Conſequents of which are very conſiderable. If <hi>ſleepineſs</hi> exceed the Cuſtom and Age of the Perſon; or <hi>watchfulneſs</hi> and <hi>indiſpoſition</hi> to reſt; both <hi>preſage</hi> no good. So
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110713:28"/>
likewiſe in other particulars, which for brevity ſake I ſhall not inſtance. In general therefore, whatever alterations happens in any <hi>part</hi> or <hi>faculty</hi> of the body, unuſual and contrary to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of Nature in her integrity; does not only declare for its <hi>ſelf,</hi> as a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular infirmity of that part where it buds forth; but does <hi>preſage</hi> (upon the continuance) ſomething worſe to come: and that the <hi>root</hi> from whence it ſprings is of a <hi>ſpreading</hi> Nature, able to bring forth more then what is manifeſt at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: in as much as the parts are <hi>depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> upon each other, in office, and uſe; and <hi>dammage</hi> to one, brings <hi>detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:110713:28"/>
               <head>Precautions and Rules for the preſervation of Health, and Prolongation of Life; <hi>In the choice of Air, and places of abode.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AIR is ſo neceſſary to <hi>Life,</hi> that without it we cannot ſubſiſt: which ſurrounding us about, and being continually ſuck't and drawn in, muſt needs <hi>affect</hi> the <hi>body</hi> with its conditions and properties; and by obſervation you may find the <hi>body,</hi> by the various con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and changes in the <hi>Air;</hi> to be variouſly affected, well and ill diſpoſed; of which, <hi>infirm parts</hi> are moſt ſenſible, that they <hi>prognoſticate</hi> before an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion come: the <hi>mind</hi> alſo by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpirits is drawn into conſent, and hath its diſpoſitions and variations: when the Air is cloſe, thick and moiſt, the <hi>ſpirits</hi> are more dull, heavy, and indiſpoſed; but at the appearance of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110713:29"/>
the <hi>Sun,</hi> and a ſerene <hi>Skie;</hi> the <hi>Spirits</hi> are unfettered, vigorous and active; the <hi>mind</hi> more chearful, airy and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spirits</hi> are of an <hi>aetherial</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and therefore do much <hi>ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize</hi> with the preſent conſtitution, and change of <hi>Air:</hi> for of the <hi>Air</hi> drawn in by the motion of the vital parts, are the <hi>vital ſpirits</hi> ventilated, &amp; the blood volatiſed; therefore the pureneſs of the <hi>Air,</hi> makes much for the purity of the ſpirits and maſs of blood.</p>
               <p>A groſs impure and noyſom <hi>Air,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunds and deads the <hi>ſpirits;</hi> makes a ſlow <hi>pulſe,</hi> obſtructs the Pores, and hinders ventilation; generates ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous humours, and cauſeth putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>A ſerene ſweet thin <hi>Air</hi> perfumes and purifies an unwholſome <hi>body,</hi> che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth the heart, makes a lively pulſe, and much enliveneth the <hi>vital ſpirits;</hi> rarifies and volatizeth a groſs coagulate blood; opens the pores for tranſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of putrid and offenſive vapours, acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates and ſharpens the <hi>Appetite,</hi> and helps digeſtion.</p>
               <p>The beſt <hi>Air,</hi> and moſt agreeable to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110713:29"/>
temperate bodies, is in temperate Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, for <hi>heat, cold, wet,</hi> and <hi>dry;</hi> not ſubject to ſudden and violent changes, as in ſome parts of <hi>America,</hi> and other Countries very frequent; not groſs and turbulent, infected with putrid vapours and noxious exhalations; from ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ditches, Lakes, Boggs, Carrions, Dunghills, Sinks and Vaults; for which cauſes great Cities, and the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent places are not ſo healthful, nor the people ſo long liv'd.</p>
               <p>Change of <hi>Air</hi> ſometimes is very neceſſary for the conſervation of <hi>health,</hi> and the recovery of it declining and loſt: for, temperate <hi>bodies</hi> by an intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>Air,</hi> ſhall gradually and in time become <hi>intemperate:</hi> intemperate bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, by the contrary intemperate Air ſhall be reduced to temperature; at leaſt, ſhall conduce much, and be very <hi>Auxiliary</hi> for the reduction. Therefore bodies declining from exact tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are beſt preſerved in that <hi>Air</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to their declenſions; as <hi>cholerick,</hi> hot and dry bodies, in a moiſt and cool <hi>Air;</hi> Phlegmatick, cold and moiſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, in a dry and warm <hi>Air.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not therefore of ſmall <hi>moment,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:110713:30"/>
in what place you live; and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch, who labour of, or are more ſubject to, any <hi>pectoral infirmity:</hi> for the Lungs being of ſo tender a ſubſtance and porous, continually drinking in the <hi>Air,</hi> is moſt apt to receive impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from it, according to the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties it is pregnant with and infeſted; and many diſeaſes of the <hi>breaſt</hi> ariſe from this ſole cauſe; and many exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by it and continued: hence it is <hi>Aſthmatick, Phthiſical</hi> and <hi>Conſumptive</hi> perſons ſhall not be cured in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but may have cure in another.</p>
               <p>Be cloathed according to the <hi>clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſeaſon</hi> and <hi>temperature</hi> of the <hi>Air,</hi> your <hi>Age,</hi> and <hi>habit</hi> of body: lean thin bodies, and pervious, <hi>(corpora rarae texturae)</hi> and whoſe skin are looſe and lax; may wear thicker cloathing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch are more perſpirable, do <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis emittere &amp; tranſpirare;</hi> and are alſo more penetrable and ſubject to injury of the <hi>Air.</hi> Fat and fleſhy people, and whoſe bodies are <hi>ſolid, firm</hi> and <hi>hard;</hi> are more impenetrable and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervious, and may wear thinner Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Infants</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> lately che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the ſtove of the Womb, being
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110713:30"/>
of tender ſoft bodies, are eaſily expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the prejudice of the Air. Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>youth,</hi> and <hi>middle Age</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to all weathers, whoſe ſpirits abounding, do ſtrongly reſiſt and keep out the aſſaults and injuries of an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive <hi>Air,</hi> may beſt indure hardſhip. <hi>Old Age,</hi> whoſe natural heat is abated, and ſpirits exhauſted; ſtands in need of good defenſatives againſt external cold, and to cheriſh internal heat.</p>
               <p>Obſerve the <hi>ſeaſons</hi> and <hi>changes</hi> of the <hi>Air,</hi> and be then moſt careful, for at ſuch times you are in moſt danger to exchange <hi>health</hi> for <hi>ſickneſs:</hi> hence it is that <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>Autum</hi> abounds moſt with Diſeaſes; the <hi>Air</hi> then aſſuming new properties oppoſite to its former conſtitution; ſets new <hi>impreſſions</hi> upon our <hi>bodies;</hi> which occaſions the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>aeſtuations</hi> and turgid <hi>fermenting</hi> of humours, producing divers ſymptoms according to the variety of their nature; the organical difference, office and conſtitution of the ſeveral parts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sun</hi> being riſen, and the <hi>Air</hi> clear, open your Chamber-windows, that the freſh <hi>Air</hi> may perfume your <pb n="48" facs="tcp:110713:31"/>
                  <hi>Room,</hi> and the cloſe <hi>Air</hi> and incloſed Vapours may go forth.</p>
               <p>Bad ſmells and putrid vapours being drawn in with the <hi>Air,</hi> are very injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>Lungs</hi> and <hi>vital parts;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminating the ſpirits, and impreſſing upon the Craſis of thoſe parts their <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid</hi> nature, are oftentimes the original of a <hi>Conſumption;</hi> and if the <hi>Lungs</hi> be weak and infirm, are more apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the prejudice then others. But <hi>fragrant ſmells</hi> refreſh and chear the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſpirits, and are very wholſom, breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the vertue of thoſe things from whence they do proceed.</p>
               <p>Be not late abroad, nor very early: before Sun riſing, and after ſetting, the <hi>Air</hi> is not ſo good; being infeſted with noxious vapours, until the <hi>radient</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the <hi>Sun</hi> diſpells and purifies: and thoſe whoſe cuſtom it is to be often abroad at ſuch times, are moſt frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moleſted with <hi>Rheums</hi> and <hi>Rheuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Diſeaſes; which their declining years will more evidently manifeſt the prejudice. Likewiſe in <hi>moiſt, foggy dark weather,</hi> 'tis better being within then abroad; and if it be a cool ſeaſon,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110713:31"/>
good fires and fragrant fumes are then both pleaſant and very wholſom.</p>
               <p>Be frequent abroad in the Fields when a <hi>clear Skie</hi> invites you forth, and let the freſh <hi>Air</hi> fan you with its ſweet breath; but more eſpecially in the <hi>morning;</hi> the <hi>Air</hi> is ſofter and more pleaſant then your Bed, and ſure I am, far more wholſom.</p>
               <q>Temperie Coeli corpuſque Animuſque juvatur.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>In the choice of <hi>places</hi> to live in and abide;<note place="margin">The choice of places to inhabit.</note> theſe things are to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>principally:</hi> Firſt, The <hi>Climate;</hi> that it be temperate, and ſuting with the <hi>nature</hi> of the perſon; for ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may agree well with one Climate, which another cannot: <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>moiſt</hi> bodies agree beſt with a <hi>warm</hi> and <hi>dry Air; hot</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> bodies with a <hi>moiſt</hi> and <hi>cooler Air.</hi> Secondly, The <hi>ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> of the place and ſoyl is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for as much as <hi>low, wet</hi> and <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> Lands; is not ſo wholſom to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, as <hi>gravelly</hi> Plains, and <hi>dry high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Countreys. Thirdly, In relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Countrey</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> regard is to be had; and here the <hi>Countrey</hi> does
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110713:32"/>
prevail over the <hi>City</hi> for Health; and is to be accounted the beſt place of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode. The continual ſmoke and anoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances that are inſeparable from great <hi>Cities,</hi> make thoſe places to abound more with infirm people. Fourthly, The <hi>Waters</hi> that ſupply a place, do make it better or worſe to live in, as they are <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad;</hi> Water being of ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and general uſe, is much to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, though little taken notice of, and procures many diſeaſes from the <hi>variety</hi> of its <hi>nature;</hi> being <hi>impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted variouſly</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om the <hi>Earth</hi> it paſſeth through; or <hi>accidents</hi> that happen to change it from its natural properties; by the admixture of any <hi>filth, carrion,</hi> or what elſe ſhall fall into it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>River Waters</hi> that lie open to ſuch injuries, are much to be ſuſpected of unwholſomneſs. And this is a great procurer of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> in many places: as <hi>Pliny</hi> relates, that <hi>Caeſars</hi> Army, by drinking of <hi>bad Water</hi> but a few dayes, had the <hi>ſymptoms</hi> of that Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>The commendations of a place, in rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on to <hi>health</hi> and <hi>long life,</hi> are theſe: A <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mperate Air,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beſt place of abode</note> 
                  <hi>dry ſerene</hi> and <hi>clear; Champion,</hi> or <hi>high Lands;</hi> a <hi>gravelly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110713:32"/>
dry ſoyl;</hi> watered with <hi>pure good Springs;</hi> remote from the <hi>Sea, Lakes,</hi> or <hi>Marſhes:</hi> not frequented with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſom Winds</hi> and <hi>ſtormy blaſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So conſiderable is the <hi>Climate</hi> and <hi>Air</hi> in relation to our <hi>Being,</hi> that it not only changeth and altereth our <hi>bodies,</hi> but alſo our <hi>minds</hi> are wrought upon by it: in as much as the <hi>wit, inclinations</hi> and <hi>manners</hi> of a people are different upon this ſcore. And for <hi>long life,</hi> we find that in ſome Countreys the people are <hi>longer lived</hi> by much then in other; and this from the wholſomneſs of the <hi>place,</hi> and purity of the <hi>Air:</hi> therefore the choice of places to live in, is of great concernment, and much to be regarded, by thoſe whoſe Fortunes permits them to pitch in any place, for the advantages of <hi>health</hi> and <hi>long life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:110713:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Preſervation of <hi>Health</hi> in the choice of <hi>Meats;</hi> and Regular Eating.</head>
               <p>THat which properly may be called <hi>Food</hi> or <hi>Aliment,</hi> is of that nature, as may fitly be tranſmuted and changed into the ſubſtance of the body which receives it: ſo that what ever will not be <hi>reduced</hi> and <hi>ſubdued</hi> by the digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for ſuch a tranſmutation and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milation, is not <hi>proper</hi> nor <hi>convenient food</hi> for that body: becauſe the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of eating is to repair the loſs that Nature ſuſtains daily; and if <hi>food</hi> will not be <hi>converted</hi> into the ſubſtance of the body, it anſwers not that intention, and is fruſtraneous: ſo that <hi>every meat</hi> which enters mans body, is not <hi>aliment,</hi> does not nouriſh; but that which yeelds <hi>obedience</hi> to the digeſtions, and is <hi>aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milated.</hi> And that which may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted proper food for the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> mankind; may be unfit for ſome <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduums,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:110713:33"/>
this or that man, as common experience ſhews: the reaſon of this is from the <hi>peculiar properties</hi> of mens bodies that differ;<note place="margin">Idioſyn Craſia,</note> elſe the choice of Meats need not to be inſiſted on.</p>
               <p>In regular eating, you are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; Firſt, The <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>quality</hi> of the food. Secondly, The fit <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> and <hi>proportion.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> and <hi>due times</hi> for eating.</p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt; That every one may be ſomething inſtructed in the <hi>election</hi> of <hi>meats,</hi> this or that, moſt proper and ſutable: take theſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations for a general guide. Firſt,<note place="margin">Paulo pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or ſed ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior cibus &amp; potus, meliori, at ingrato praeferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> Try by your <hi>Pallate;</hi> eat no meats that does <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> the <hi>Guſt,</hi> for a common food.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Examine your <hi>Stomach,</hi> whether ſuch meats do not <hi>oppreſs,</hi> or <hi>riſe</hi> in the Stomach, and cauſe a trouble; or is <hi>long</hi> in paſſing off, and <hi>flatulent:</hi> If any ſuch <hi>ſymptom</hi> as theſe do follow, (and not upon other meats) then ſuch food is not convenient, becauſe it puts a <hi>difficulty</hi> upon the Stomach to digeſt; the conſequents of which are bad.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Inquire into the <hi>conſtitution</hi> or <hi>condition</hi> of your body, and have ſome reſpect to that in the election of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110713:34"/>
meats: for <hi>Phlegmatick cold</hi> bodies, and <hi>cholerick hot</hi> and dry bodies, will not well be dieted both alike; but (as commonly) they have <hi>different in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations</hi> to meats; ſo Nature hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and is furniſhed with <hi>variety</hi> to ſute ſuch ſeveral bodies and <hi>appetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Therefore make choice of ſuch for the moſt part as is commended to you, <hi>ſuting</hi> (commonly,) and <hi>conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> for that conſtitution you are of; as you will find preſcribed in the ſeveral <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> or <hi>Conditions</hi> of body fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p>Now by theſe three <hi>Rules,</hi> every one may make a good choice of meats in a <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>health;</hi> and reaſonably inſtruct himſelf, for the preſervation thereof.</p>
               <p>Next the <hi>quantity</hi> is to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that you do not exceed ſuch a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion,</hi> as is agreeable to your Nature, for a due ſupply, and not overcharge the body. And here I muſt commend to you <hi>temperance</hi> and <hi>moderation</hi> in eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as a great preſervative of Health; not a <hi>Leſſian diet</hi> to pine and enfeeble the body; not ſo <hi>preciſe,</hi> but a <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> allowance, proportionable to the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ability</hi> of the Stomach to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110713:34"/>
digeſt; conſidering alſo other <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of body, and manner of life, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>active</hi> and <hi>laborious,</hi> or <hi>ſedentary</hi> and <hi>idle.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plures gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la quam gladius.</note> The contrary irregular pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice hath deſtroyed the lives of many. Some may think, the more <hi>plentifully</hi> they eat, the <hi>better</hi> they ſhall thrive in body, be more nouriſhed, and the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for it: but it will not prove ſo; a <hi>little</hi> well <hi>digeſted</hi> and <hi>aſſimilated,</hi> ſhall maintain the body in a ſtronger and more vigorous condition; then being <hi>glutted</hi> with <hi>ſuperfluity;</hi> moſt of which is turned to <hi>excrementitious</hi> (not <hi>alimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary juyce</hi>) and muſt be caſt out, elſe ſickneſs ſoon after will follow.</p>
               <p>For quantity, your own <hi>ſtomach</hi> muſt meaſure to you what is convenient; which is a certain rule of proportion, if you obſerve not to eat to a <hi>ſatiety</hi> and <hi>fulneſs;</hi> but deſiſt with an <hi>appetite,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refreſhed light and chearful; not dulled, heavy and indiſpoſed to operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and action, either of mind or body.</p>
               <p>A ſet quantity or meaſure of <hi>meat</hi> or <hi>drink,</hi> cannot be preſcribed as a <hi>general rule</hi> and <hi>obſervation</hi> for all to follow; in regard of the variety and great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of perſons, in <hi>Conſtitution, Age,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110713:35"/>
ſtrength</hi> of <hi>Nature, condition</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>infirmities;</hi> that what is conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for <hi>one,</hi> is too much for <hi>another,</hi> and too little for a <hi>third;</hi> the <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>healthy</hi> cannot conform to the <hi>ſickly, weak</hi> and <hi>infirm</hi> in quantity; nor the <hi>labouring man</hi> to the <hi>ſedentary</hi> and <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,</hi> or the <hi>idle:</hi> therefore every ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach is to be its own judge: and every one ought to moderate themſelves by the cautions before mentioned.</p>
               <p>Indulge not the cravings of an irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſenſitive appetite; but allow ſuch a ſupply of daily food, as will <hi>ſupport</hi> and <hi>maintain</hi> bodily ſtrength,<note place="margin">Quicquid plus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geritur, gravat na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam, non juvat.</note> and not <hi>over-load</hi> it: thereby the ſpirits will be <hi>vigorous</hi> and <hi>active; humors</hi> attenuated and abated; <hi>crudities</hi> and <hi>obſtructions</hi> prevented; many infirmities checkt and kept under; the ſenſes long preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their integrity; the ſtomach clean, the appetite ſharp, and digeſtion good. But by the <hi>ſurpluſage</hi> and over-charge, the <hi>ſtomachical ferment</hi> is over-laid, and its <hi>inciſive penetrative</hi> faculty <hi>obtunded;</hi> the appetite and digeſtion abated, the ſtomach nauſeating, fluctuating, and belching with crudities; from whence <hi>Gripes, Fluxes</hi> and <hi>Feavers:</hi> the ſpirits
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110713:35"/>
clogged, dull and ſomnolent; by their indiſpoſition and inactivity, humors <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, degenerate, incraſſate, obſtruct;</hi> from whence various <hi>ſymptoms</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved effects throughout the body; debilitating and decaying the ſenſes,<note place="margin">Noxa etſi ad tempus fortaſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteſcit; temporis tamen ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſu ſeſe exerit.</note> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ervating and ſtealing away the ſtrength of the body, by defrauding it of good nutriment, haſtning old age, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning life.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Winter</hi> you may eat more freely; but in <hi>Summer</hi> the ſpirits are dilated, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted and drawn forth by the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal heat opening the pores; wherefore the appetite is not ſo ſharp, nor digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo quick. And the Rule is true, though heat be not the principal cauſe of concoction, yet it is a neceſſary A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, Excitor and Cooperator.</p>
               <p>Change your <hi>dyet</hi> according to the <hi>ſeaſons</hi> of the year, the <hi>variation</hi> of your body, and inclination to this or that diſtemper: in <hi>Winter</hi> more <hi>meat</hi> and leſs <hi>drink;</hi> in <hi>Summer</hi> leſs <hi>meat</hi> and more <hi>liquids:</hi> in <hi>Summer</hi> meats oftner boiled, in <hi>Winter</hi> roaſted: a <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> body muſt have a <hi>cooling</hi> and <hi>moiſt</hi> diet; a <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>moiſt</hi> body, a <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> dyet: temperate bodies are preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110713:36"/>
by temperate things and their like; diſtempered bodies are rectified and reduced by diſſimilars.</p>
               <p>The more <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>ſingle</hi> your dyet is, the better and more wholſom: but if your ſtomach muſt have <hi>variety,</hi> let it be at ſeveral meals, and ſo you may pleaſe your Pallat without prejudice. Accuſtom not your ſelf to delicacies and compound diſhes, the <hi>heterogenity</hi> of their nature, begets a diſcordant fermentation in the ſtomach troubling concoction; from whence eructations, nauſeous belchings, and offenſive riſings in the throat,<note place="margin">Aphor.</note> 
                  <hi>Quo ſimplicior victus ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eo melior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of all meats, <hi>fleſh</hi> affords the moſt nouriſhment and the ſtrongeſt.</p>
               <p>If your dyet ſometimes be not ſo good and proper for you in the <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance;</hi> make amends in the <hi>quantity,</hi> and eat the leſs.</p>
               <p>Of all Sauces, a good <hi>ſtomach</hi> is the beſt; but if you muſt have other, let it be <hi>acide</hi> ſharp or biting.</p>
               <p>Accuſtom ſtrong ſtomachs, to ſtrong meats; the weaker to lighter of dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: very light meats in ſtrong ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs are ſoon digeſted, but withal
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110713:36"/>
parched and corrupted, and turn to a bitter and cholerick juyce: ſolid hard meats in weak ſtomachs lie long and heavy, and paſs away crude and undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meats</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>facility</hi> and <hi>difficulty</hi> in digeſtion, are termed hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and light.</p>
               <p>Heavy meats be ſuch as are more <hi>dry, hard, ſolid</hi> and <hi>denſe, groſs, courſe</hi> and <hi>tough,</hi> or over <hi>moiſt, ſlimy</hi> and <hi>cold:</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring a longer time in fermentation, volatization and digeſtion, before they be fit to paſs off the ſtomach.</p>
               <p>And they are either ſo in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: as all <hi>old fleſh, Bull-Beef</hi> and <hi>Oxe, Brawn, Pork, Veniſon, Hare, Gooſe, Duck, Swan, Crane, Bittern, Heron,</hi> and moſt Water Fowl: <hi>Eels, Lobſter, Lampreys, Tench, Stock-fiſh: Beans, Peaſe</hi> when they be ſomthing old: <hi>brown Bread, Barley</hi> and <hi>Rie Bread:</hi> Alſo ſome parts are of harder digeſtion then other: as <hi>Brains, Hearts, Livers,</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of tame Fowl, Birds, and ſome very young fleſh) <hi>Milts, Kidneys, Skin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meats</hi> made <hi>heavy</hi> (or made <hi>worſe</hi> then in their own nature) by preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110713:37"/>
keeping and dreſſing: as <hi>dryed, fryed</hi> and <hi>broyled</hi> meats: meats long <hi>ſalted</hi> and <hi>kept,</hi> as <hi>Bacon, hang'd Beef,</hi> and long <hi>powdered; old Ling, ſalt Cod, Haberdine, pickled Herrings, red Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, pickled Scallops, Sturgion, ſalt Salmon, hard Egs, toſted Cheeſe, toſted Bread,</hi> eſpecially if it be <hi>ſcorched; Cruſts, Pye-cruſt,</hi> Bread not well <hi>baked, unlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened:</hi> meats over-<hi>baked, hard</hi> and <hi>dry;</hi> long kept, meats roſted <hi>dry,</hi> or <hi>ſcorched.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Light <hi>meats</hi> and of quicker digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be ſuch as are moſt <hi>ſoft</hi> and <hi>tender, rare</hi> as it is oppoſed to <hi>denſity;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſooner penetrated by the ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical ferment; <hi>ſucculent, volatile,</hi> ſoon fermenting and yeelding to digeſtion.</p>
               <p>As young tender fleſh: of <hi>Veal,</hi> young <hi>Mutton, Lamb, Kid, Pullet, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, Chicken, Conies, Turkie, Pheaſant, Partridge, Plover, Woodcock, Snite, Heath-Cocks,</hi> and ſmall Birds: <hi>Whiting, Smelt, Oiſter, Flounder, Soles, Plaiſe, Thornback, Turbut, Trout, Carp, Pike, Bream, Pearch,</hi> and ſuch like: <hi>Rere Egs, Milk, Wheat Bread, white, light,</hi> and well <hi>baked;</hi> alſo <hi>Oaten</hi> Bread well made: and theſe may be divided into
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110713:37"/>
two ſorts: that is, meats very light, as <hi>Rere Egs,</hi> ſucking <hi>Rabbits, Chickens, Whitings:</hi> and meats indifferent light, as <hi>Mutton, Lamb, Veal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Very light meats are ſoon digeſted,<note place="margin">Quae faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le digerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, facile etiam cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> apt to be corrupted in ſtrong ſtomachs; breeds tender and effeminate bodies, ſoft and looſe fleſh eaſily loſt: ſolid ſtrong meats are ſlower in digeſtion, not eaſily corrupted, ſlow in diſtribution, makes ſtrong bodies, firm, hard fleſh and durable.</p>
               <p>Uſe not meats that hath any quality in <hi>extream;</hi> as very <hi>ſalt,</hi> very <hi>hot, ſower, binding,</hi> or the like, but keep to thoſe that are moderate.</p>
               <p>Let your Bread be of Wheat, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, well kneaded and baked, light and white; which you may eat new, but not hot; nor ſtaler then two dayes old, and chuſe the crumb rather then the cruſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seaſonings</hi> of <hi>meat</hi> are uſed either as <hi>preſervatives</hi> to keep them from putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and decay; or as <hi>correctives,</hi> to alter and change ſome ill quality, and promote digeſtion; or for <hi>delight</hi> to gratifie the pallat; as <hi>Sugar, Salt, Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Muſtard, Pepper, Cloves</hi> and other Spices.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:110713:38"/>Meat moderately ſalted, having time to <hi>digeſt, ferment, volatize,</hi> and alter the <hi>crude</hi> qualities, is better and wholſomer then freſh: but to eat <hi>Salt</hi> at the Table is not ſo good, if the condition of the meat be ſuch as to allow a praevious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion and ſeaſoning. Salt is grateful to the pallate and ſtomach, <hi>excites</hi> the appetite, concocts crude flegmatick matter that lies upon the ſtomach, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders putrefaction, and is <hi>abſterſive:</hi> but immoderately uſed, corrodes and frets, cauſeth itching and breakings out; very bad for thin lean bodies; it heats and dries the blood and natural moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sugar</hi> in a temperate clean body, moderately uſed, nouriſheth and is good; but in a foul body is ſoon cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, degenerates and makes the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more impure; turns to choller, and inflames cholerick hot bodies. The frequent and immoderate uſe in any, obtunds and abates the appetite, cauſeth putrid humours, and makes an unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vinegar</hi> and ſower juyces, as of <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Verjuce,</hi> and the like; procure appetite, and help the ſtomach in dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110713:38"/>
of groſſer meats: but the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and frequent uſe, cooles, dries, conſtringeth and bindes the body, hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Nerves and nervous parts; very bad for Women, and thoſe that are ſubject to the <hi>Gout, Aſthmaes</hi> and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings in the breaſt, or in other parts; and for lean and dry bodies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſtard</hi> quickens the appetite, warms the ſtomach, dries up ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous moiſture, helps the ſtomach, digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard meats, opens ſtoppings in the breaſt and head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mace, Ginger, Nutmeg, Pepper</hi> and <hi>Cloves,</hi> they help a cold ſtomack, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the heart and brain, refreſh the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits by their atomatical odour, are grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful upon the Pallate, and very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Phlegmatick cold bodies.</p>
               <p>In the uſe of the forementioned, I ſhall give this <hi>caution:</hi> that young ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs, and ſtrong healthy bodies which need not a ſpur to their appetite, nor a help to digeſtion; that they frequent not the uſe of theſe ſeaſonings and ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but reſerve them for Age, deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſtomach, and other infirmities: for, if you accuſtom your ſelf to them in <hi>youth</hi> and <hi>ſtrength,</hi> to pleaſe your
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110713:39"/>
pallate, and intice your ſtomach, there being no need: when the <hi>condition</hi> of your body does <hi>require</hi> them, you ſhall not find that benefit and aſſiſtance from them, which otherwiſe you might have expected and received, had you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born the uſe of them when it was not neceſſary.</p>
               <p>When you come to <hi>Meat,</hi> leave your <hi>care</hi> and <hi>buſineſs;</hi> but bring in your <hi>friend,</hi> and be as merry as you can: mirth and good company, is a great help to a dull ſtomach both for appetite and digeſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eat</hi> not preſently after exerciſe, and when you are <hi>hot,</hi> but forbear till the ſpirits be retired and ſetled in their ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eat</hi> not <hi>haſtily,</hi> but chew your meat well; 'tis a good preparation for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, and your ſtomach will more eaſily and ſooner digeſt it; but if it be half chewed, the ſtomach muſt have the labour to chew it over again with its <hi>inciſive ferment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Drink</hi> a little and oft at meat, to macerate and digeſt, eſpecially if your meat be dry and ſolid, and to help di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of aliment; but great draughts cauſe <hi>fluctuations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:110713:39"/>
                  <hi>Haſty motion</hi> opens the Orifice of the ſtomach, precipitates and vitiates dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>Forbear <hi>reading, writing, ſtudy,</hi> or <hi>ſerious cogitations</hi> for two hours after meat; elſe you draw off from the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, abate the ſtrength of digeſtion, and injure the brain.</p>
               <p>Omit a <hi>meal</hi> ſometimes; it acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates and ſharpens the ſtomach, concocts indigeſted matter, and makes the next <hi>meal</hi> relliſh better,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eat</hi> no late ſuppers, nor variety at once; a good ſtomach may endure it for a <hi>while;</hi> but the <hi>weaker</hi> is more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the injury; the <hi>beſt</hi> is prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in time.</p>
               <p>Let not the common cuſtom of <hi>meals,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nemo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis ſuae ſtudioſus aliquid co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medat, niſi ad hoc cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prius invitante deſiderio; &amp; ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo una cum reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioribus inteſtinis à praeſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pto cibo vacuatis. <hi>Avicen.</hi>
                  </note> invite you to eat; except your <hi>appetite</hi> concur with thoſe times: and keep a ſufficient diſtance between your times of eating, that you charge not the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach with a <hi>new ſupply,</hi> before the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer be diſtributed and paſſed away: and in keeping ſuch a diſtance, your ſtomach will be very fit and ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the next meal, the former being wrought off perfectly; no ſemi-dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted crude matter remaining to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110713:40"/>
with the next food: and that is one chief cauſe of crudities and a foul ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach; when a new load is caſt in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the former be gone off, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets much excrements, not much ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; clogs the body, and procures Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>The ſtomach that is empty, receives, cloſeth and embraceth food with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; will be eager and ſharp in dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and the body will <hi>attract</hi> and ſuck the aliment ſtrongly; each part as it paſſeth along will perform its office rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and ſufficiently; which they will not do, if often cloyed with depraved and indigeſted aliment, but ſlowly and with reluctancy: for although they do not act by reaſon, yet they have a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral inſtinct or endowment to diſcern their proper and fit object.</p>
               <p>If your body becomes <hi>lean,</hi> and your fleſh <hi>looſer</hi> then formerly; do not pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and feed your ſelf highly, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>recover</hi> and <hi>regain</hi> the loſt fleſh: for in ſo doing you add more miſchief, and make your body fouler then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Corpora impura quo plus nutries, eò magis lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. <hi>Hipp.</hi>
                  </note> and miſs of your purpoſe: and unleſs the former impediments, that hindered and fruſtrated nutrition, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110713:40"/>
in vain it is to expect it from the addition, and greater ſupply of food, or high nouriſhers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> Preſervation of <hi>Health</hi> in the choice of <hi>Drinks,</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Drinking.</head>
               <p>DRink for <hi>neceſſity,</hi> not for bad <hi>fellowſhip;</hi> eſpecially ſoon after meat, which hinders the due fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the ſtomach, and waſheth down before digeſtion be finiſhed: but after the firſt concoction, if you have a <hi>hot</hi> ſtomach, a <hi>dry</hi> or <hi>coſtive</hi> body, you may drink more freely then others: or if <hi>thirſt</hi> importunes you at any time, to ſatisfie with a moderate draught is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to forbear.</p>
               <p>Accuſtom youth &amp; ſtrong ſtomachs to <hi>ſmall</hi> drink; but <hi>ſtronger</hi> drink, and <hi>Wine,</hi> to the infirm and aged: it chears the ſpirits, quickens the appetite, and helps digeſtion, <hi>moderately</hi> taken: but
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110713:41"/>
being uſed in <hi>exceſs,</hi> diſturbs the courſe of Nature, and procures many Diſeaſes: for corpulent groſs and fat bodies, thin, hungry, abſterſive penetrating Wines are beſt, as <hi>white-Wine, Rheniſh,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>For lean thin bodies; black, red and yellow Wines, ſweet, full bodied and fragrant, are more fit and agreeable; as <hi>Malaga, Muſcadel, Tent, Alicant,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Drink,</hi> whether it be wholſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>warmed</hi> then <hi>cold,</hi> is much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted; ſome ſtifly contending for the <hi>one,</hi> and ſome for the <hi>other:</hi> I ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chuſe the middle way, with limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtinction, then impoſe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all as a rule to be obſerved under the penalty of forfeiting their health, the obſervations of the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>There are three ſorts of perſons, one cannot drink <hi>cold Beer,</hi> the other cannot drink <hi>warm;</hi> the third, <hi>either:</hi> You that cannot drink cold Beer, to you it is hurtful, cools the ſtomach, and checks it much: therefore keep to <hi>warm drink</hi> as a wholſom cuſtom: you that cannot drink warm Beer, that is,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110713:41"/>
find no refreſhment, nor thirſt ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, you may drink it cold, nor is it injurious to you: you that are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and can drink either; drink yours cold, or warmed, as the <hi>company</hi> does, ſince your ſtomach makes no choice.</p>
               <p>That <hi>warm drink</hi> is no bad cuſtom, but agreeable to Nature in the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; firſt, Becauſe it comes the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the natural temper of the body, and <hi>ſimilia ſimilibus conſervantur;</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing is preſerved by its like, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by its contrary. Secondly, Though I do not hold it the principal Agent in digeſtion, yet it does excite, is auxiliary, and a neceſſary concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of a good digeſtion, <hi>ut ſignum &amp; cauſa.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Omne frigus per ſe, &amp; pro viribus deſtruit;</hi> Cold in its own nature, and according to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duation of its power, extinguiſheth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat, and is deſtructive; but <hi>per accidens,</hi> and as it is in <hi>gradu remiſſo,</hi> it may contemperate, allay, and refreſh, where heat abounds, and is exalted.</p>
               <p>Therefore as there is <hi>variety</hi> of Pallates and Stomachs likeing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing beſt with ſuch kind of meats and drinks, which to others are utterly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110713:42"/>
diſguſtful, diſagreeing and injurious, though good in themſelves: ſo is it in Drink <hi>warmed</hi> or <hi>cold;</hi> what one finds a benefit in, the other receives a <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice;</hi> at leaſt does not find that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and refreſhment, under ſuch a qualification; becauſe of the various natures, particular appetitions, and <hi>idoſyncratical</hi> properties of ſeveral bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, one thing will not agree with all: Therefore he that cannot drink <hi>warm,</hi> let him take it <hi>cold,</hi> and it is well to him; but he that drinks it <hi>warm;</hi> does better. And this is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in Winter, when the extremity of cold hath <hi>congelated</hi> and <hi>fixed</hi> the ſpirits of the Liquor in a <hi>torpid</hi> inacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; which by a gentle warmth are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fettered, volatile</hi> and <hi>brisk;</hi> whereby the drink is more agreeable and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the ſtomachs fermenting heat; being ſo prepared, then to be made ſo by it.</p>
               <p>There are three ſorts of <hi>Drinkers:</hi> one drinks to ſatisfie <hi>Nature,</hi> and to ſupport his <hi>body;</hi> without which he cannot well ſubſiſt, and requires it as neceſſary to his Being. Another drinks a <hi>degree</hi> beyond this man, and takes a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110713:42"/>
larger <hi>doſe,</hi> with this intention,<note place="margin">Primum crater ad ſitim per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ad hilarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ad vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptatem, quartum ad inſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um dixit. <hi>Apuleius.</hi>
                  </note> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilerate and chear his <hi>mind,</hi> to baniſh <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>trouble,</hi> and help him to <hi>ſleep</hi> the better; and theſe two are lawful drinkers. A third drinks neither for the good of the <hi>body,</hi> or the mind, but to ſtupifie and drown both; by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the former bounds, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into exceſs, fruſtrating thoſe <hi>ends</hi> for which drink was appointed by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; converting this <hi>ſupport</hi> of life and health, making it a <hi>procurer</hi> of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and untimely death.</p>
               <p>Many ſuch there are, who drink not to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> Nature, but force it down many times <hi>contrary</hi> to natural inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and when there is a reluctancy againſt it: as <hi>Drunkards,</hi> that pour in Liquor, not for love of the <hi>drink,</hi> or that Nature requires it by <hi>thirſt,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to maintain the <hi>mad frollick,</hi> and keep the Company from breaking up. Some to excuſe this intemperance, hold it as good <hi>Phyſick</hi> to be drunk once a month, and plead for that liberty as a wholſom cuſtom, and quote the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a famous <hi>Phyſitian</hi> for it. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Opinion be allowable, and to be admitted in the due <hi>Regiment</hi> for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110713:43"/>
preſervation of health, is fit to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Omne ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae eſt inimicunt.</note>It is a <hi>Canon</hi> eſtabliſhed upon good reaſon; <hi>That every thing exceeding its juſt bounds, and golden mediocrity, is hurtful to Nature.</hi> The beſt of things are not excepted in this general rule; but are reſtrained and limited here to a due proportion. The <hi>ſupports</hi> of life may prove the <hi>procurers</hi> of death, if not qualified and made wholſom by this corrective.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> is no longer ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but a load and over-charge, if they exceed the <hi>quantum</hi> due to each particular perſon; and then they are not, what they are properly in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and by the appointment of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the <hi>preſervatives</hi> of life and health; but the <hi>cauſes</hi> of ſickneſs, and conſequently of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Drink</hi> was not appointed man, to diſcompoſe and diſorder him in all his faculties, but to <hi>ſupply, nouriſh,</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> them. Drink exceeding its meaſure, is no longer a refreſhment, to <hi>irrigate</hi> and water the thirſty body, but makes an inundation to drown and ſuffocate the <hi>vital powers.</hi> It puts a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110713:43"/>
man out of the ſtate of health, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents him in ſuch a degenerate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition both in reſpect of <hi>body</hi> and <hi>mind,</hi> that we may look upon the man, as go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the World, becauſe he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready gon out of himſelf, and ſtrangely <hi>metamorphoſed</hi> from what he was.</p>
               <p>I never knew <hi>ſickneſs</hi> or a <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> to be good preventing Phyſick; and to be drunk, is no other then an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound ſtate, and the whole body out of frame by this great change. What dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there between <hi>ſickneſs</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs?</hi> Truly I cannot diſtinguiſh them otherwiſe then as <hi>genus</hi> and <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies:</hi> Drunkenneſs being a raging Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, denominated and diſtinguiſhed from other ſickneſſes, by its <hi>procatar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> or <hi>procuring</hi> cauſe, <hi>Drink.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Drunkenneſs is a Diſeaſe or ſickneſs, will appear in that it hath all the requiſites to <hi>conſtitute</hi> a <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> and is far diſtant from a <hi>ſtate</hi> of health: for as health is the free and regular diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of all the <hi>functions</hi> of the body and mind; and ſickneſs, when the <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> are not performed, or weakly and depravedly: then <hi>Ebriety</hi> may proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid to be a Diſeaſe or ſickneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110713:44"/>
it hath the <hi>ſymptoms</hi> and <hi>diagno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick</hi> ſigns, of an <hi>acute</hi> and great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe: for, during the time of <hi>drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and ſome time after, few of the faculties perform rightly, but very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravedly and <hi>preternaturally:</hi> if we examine the <hi>intellectual faculties,</hi> we ſhall find the <hi>reaſon</hi> gone, the <hi>memory</hi> loſt or much abated, and the <hi>will</hi> ſtrangly perverted: if we look into the <hi>ſenſitive</hi> faculties, they are diſordered, and their <hi>functions</hi> impedited, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed very deficiently: the <hi>eyes</hi> do not ſee well, nor the <hi>ears</hi> hear well, nor the <hi>pallate</hi> relliſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>ſpeech</hi> faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and is imperfect; the <hi>ſtomach</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps vomits or nauſeates; his <hi>legs</hi> fail: Indeed if we look through the whole man, we ſhall ſee all the faculties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, and their functions either not executed, or very diſorderly and with much deficiency.</p>
               <p>Now according to theſe <hi>ſymptoms</hi> in other <hi>ſickneſſes,</hi> we judge a man not likely to live long; and that it is very hard he ſhould recover; the danger is ſo great from the many threatning <hi>ſymptoms</hi> that attend this ſickneſs, and <hi>prognoſticate</hi> a bad event: here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110713:44"/>
appears <hi>ſalutary;</hi> but from head to foot, the Diſeaſe is prevalent in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part; which being collated, the <hi>ſyndrom</hi> is <hi>lethal,</hi> and judgment to be given ſo.</p>
               <p>Surely then Drunkenneſs is a very great diſeaſe for the time; but becauſe it is not uſually <hi>mortal,</hi> nor laſts long; therefore it is ſlighted, and look't upon as a trivial matter that will cure it ſelf. But now the queſtion may be asked; Why is not <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> uſually <hi>mortal?</hi> ſince the ſame ſigns in other diſeaſes are accounted <hi>mortal,</hi> and the event proves it ſo. To which I anſwer; All the hopes we have that a man <hi>drunk</hi> ſhould live, is; firſt, From common <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> that it is not deadly: Secondly, From the nature of the <hi>primitive</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing</hi> Cauſe, ſtrong Drink or Wine; which although it rage, and ſtrangely diſcompoſe the man for a time, yet it laſts not long, nor is <hi>mortal.</hi> The <hi>ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briating</hi> ſpirits of the liquor, flowing in ſo faſt, and joyning with the ſpirits of mans body, make ſo <hi>high</hi> a <hi>tide,</hi> that overflows all the banks and bounds of order: For, the ſpirits of mans body, thoſe <hi>agents</hi> in each faculty, act ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110713:45"/>
regularly and conſtantly, with a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſupply; but being overcharged, and forced out of their natural courſe, and exerciſe of their duty, by the large addition of <hi>furious ſpirits;</hi> ſpurs the functions into ſtrange diſorders, as if nature were conflicting with death and diſſolution; but yet it proves not <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this, firſt, becauſe theſe <hi>adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious ſpirits</hi> are amicable and friendly to our bodies in their own nature, and therefore not ſo <hi>deadly injurious,</hi> as that which is not ſo familiar or noxious.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe they are very <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile, light,</hi> and <hi>active;</hi> Nature there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore does much ſooner recover her ſelf, <hi>tranſpires</hi> and ſends forth the <hi>overplus</hi> received; then if the <hi>morbifick</hi> matter were more ponderous and fixed; the <hi>gravamen</hi> from thence would be much worſe and longer in removing: as an over-charge of <hi>Meat, Bread, Fruit,</hi> or ſuch like ſubſtances not ſpirituous; but dull and heavy <hi>(comparativè)</hi> is of more difficult digeſtion, and layes a greater and more dangerous load upon the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, having not ſuch <hi>volatile brisk</hi> ſpirits to aſſiſt Nature, nor of ſo liquid
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110713:45"/>
a fine ſubſtance, of quicker and eaſier digeſtion: So that the <hi>ſymptoms</hi> from thence are much more dangerous, then thoſe <hi>peracute</hi> diſtempers ariſing from Liquors. So likewiſe thoſe bad <hi>ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms</hi> in other diſeaſes are more to be feared and accounted <hi>mortal</hi> (then the like ariſing from <hi>drunkenneſs</hi>) becauſe thoſe perhaps depend upon <hi>malignant cauſes;</hi> or ſuch as by time are <hi>radicated</hi> in the body; or from the defection of ſome <hi>principal part:</hi> but the ſtorm and diſcompoſure ariſing from <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi> as it is ſuddenly raiſed; ſo commonly it ſoon falls, depending upon <hi>benign cauſes,</hi> and a ſpirituous matter, that layes not ſo great an oppreſſion; but <hi>inebriates</hi> the ſpirits, that they act very diſorderly and unwontedly; or by the <hi>ſoporiferous</hi> vertue, <hi>ſtupefies</hi> them for a time, until they recover their <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gility</hi> again.</p>
               <p>But all this while, I do not ſee, <hi>that to be drunk once a month,</hi> ſhould prove good Phyſick: all I think that can be ſaid in this behalf, is; that by overcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtomach, <hi>vomiting</hi> is <hi>procured;</hi> and ſo carries off ſomething that was lodged there, which might breed Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:110713:46"/>This is a <hi>bad excuſe</hi> for good fellows, and a <hi>poor plea</hi> for <hi>drunkenneſs:</hi> for the gaining of one ſuppoſed benefit (which might be obtained otherwiſe) you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce twenty <hi>inconveniences</hi> by it. I do not like the preventing of one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe that <hi>may be,</hi> by procuring of one at the <hi>preſent certainly,</hi> and many here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after moſt probably: and if the diſeaſe feared, or <hi>may be,</hi> could be prevented no otherwiſe, but by this <hi>drunken means;</hi> then that might tollerate and allow it: but there are other wayes better and ſafer to cleanſe the body either <hi>upwards</hi> or <hi>downwards,</hi> then by overcharging with ſtrong drink, and making the man to <hi>unman</hi> himſelf; the evil conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of which are many, the benefit hoped for, but <hi>pretended;</hi> or if any, but very <hi>ſmall</hi> and <hi>inconſiderable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although, as I ſaid before, the <hi>drunken fit</hi> is not <hi>mortal,</hi> and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger perhaps not great for the preſent; yet thoſe <hi>drunken bouts</hi> being repeated; the <hi>relicts</hi> do accumulate, debilitate Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and lay the foundation of many <hi>chronick diſeaſes.</hi> Nor can it be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted otherwiſe; but you may juſtly conclude from the manifeſt irregular
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110713:46"/>
actions which appears to us <hi>externally;</hi> that the functions within alſo, and their motions are ſtrangely diſordered: for, the <hi>outward madneſs</hi> and unwonted actions, proceeds from the <hi>internal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes,</hi> and diſordered motions of the faculties: which general diſturbance and diſcompoſure (being frequent) muſt needs <hi>ſubvert</hi> the <hi>oeconomy</hi> and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of humane Nature; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ruine the Fabrick of mans body.</p>
               <p>The ill effects, and more eminent products of ebriety, are; firſt, <hi>A chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the natural tone of the ſtomach, and alienateing the digeſtive faculty;</hi> That inſtead of a good tranſmutation of food, a degenerate Chyle is produced. Common experience tells, that after a <hi>drunken debauch,</hi> the ſtomach loſeth its appetite, and acuteneſs of digeſtion; as <hi>belching, thirſt, diſreliſh, nauſeating,</hi> do certainly teſtifie: yet to ſupport nature, and continue the cuſtom of eating; ſome food is received; but we cannot expect from ſuch a <hi>ſtomach</hi> that a <hi>good digeſtion</hi> ſhould follow: and it is ſome dayes before the ſtomach recover its <hi>eucraſy,</hi> and perform its office well:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110713:47"/>
and if theſe miſcarriages happen but <hi>ſeldom;</hi> the injury is the leſs, and ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er recompenced; but by the <hi>frequent repetition</hi> of theſe ruinous practices, the ſtomach is overthrown and alienated from its integrity.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>An unwholſom corpulency and cachectick plenitude of body does follow: or a degenerate macilency, and a decayed conſumptive conſtitution.</hi> Great drinkers that continue it long; few of them eſcape,<note place="margin">A <hi>Caco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trophy,</hi> or <hi>Atrophy.</hi>
                  </note> but fall into one of theſe <hi>conditions</hi> and <hi>habit</hi> of body: for, if the Stomach diſcharge not its office a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; the <hi>ſubſequent digeſtions</hi> will alſo be defective. So great a conſent and dependance is there upon the <hi>ſtomach;</hi> that other parts cannot perform their duty, if this leading <hi>principal Part</hi> be perverted and debauched: nor can it be expected otherwiſe; for, from this <hi>Laboratory</hi> and <hi>prime office</hi> of digeſtion, all the parts muſt receive their ſupply; which being not ſuteable but depraved, are drawn into <hi>debauchery</hi> alſo, and a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate</hi> ſtate; and the whole body fed with a vitious <hi>alimentary ſuccus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that different <hi>products</hi> or <hi>habits</hi> of body ſhould ariſe from the ſame
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110713:47"/>
kind of debauchery, happens upon this ſcore. As there are different <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties</hi> and <hi>conditions</hi> of bodies; ſo the reſult from the ſame procuring cauſes ſhall be much different and various:<note place="margin">Quicquid recipitur, recipitur per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientis. <hi>Ax.</hi>
                  </note> one puffs up, fills, and grows <hi>hydropical;</hi> another pines away, and falls <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> from <hi>exceſs</hi> in <hi>drinking;</hi> and this proceeds from the different <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of parts: for, in ſome perſons, although the <hi>ſtomach</hi> be vitiated, yet the ſtrength of the <hi>ſubſequent digeſtions</hi> is ſo great, from the integrity and vigor of thoſe parts deſtinated to ſuch offices; that they act <hi>ſtrenuouſly,</hi> though their <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter</hi> be tranſmitted to them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and degenerate; and therefore do keep the body <hi>plump</hi> and <hi>full,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the juyces be <hi>foul</hi> and of a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved</hi> nature. Others <hi>è contra,</hi> whoſe parts are not ſo firm and vigorous; that will not act upon any ſcore, but with their <hi>proper object;</hi> does not endeavour a tranſmutation of ſuch <hi>aliene matter,</hi> but receiving it with a <hi>nice reluctance,</hi> tranſmits it to be evacuated and ſent forth by the next convenient ducture, or emunctory: and from hence the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is fruſtrated of nutrition, and falls
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110713:48"/>
away: So that the pouring in of much liquor (although it be good <hi>in ſua na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura</hi>) does not beget <hi>much aliment,</hi> but waſheth through the body, and is not aſſimilated.</p>
               <p>But here ſome may object and think; <hi>That waſhing of the body through with good Liquor, ſhould cleanſe the body, and make it fit for nouriſhment, and be like good Phyſick for a foul body.</hi> But the effect proves the contrary; and it is but reaſon it ſhould be ſo: for, ſuppoſe the Liquor (whether Wine, or other) be pure and good; yet when the <hi>ſpirit</hi> is drawn off from it, the <hi>remainder</hi> is but <hi>dead, flat, thick,</hi> and a <hi>muddy flegm.</hi> As we find in the deſtillation of Wine, or other Liquors; ſo it is in mans body: the <hi>ſpirit</hi> is drawn off <hi>firſt,</hi> and all the parts of mans body are ready <hi>Receivers,</hi> and do <hi>imbibe</hi> that <hi>limpid congenerous</hi> enlivener, freely and readily: but the <hi>remainder,</hi> of greateſt proportion; that heavy, dull, <hi>phlegmy part,</hi> and of a <hi>narcotick quality;</hi> lies long fluctuating upon the digeſtions, and paſſeth but ſlowly; turns ſowr, and vitiates the <hi>Craſes</hi> of the parts: So that this great <hi>inundation,</hi> and ſuppoſed waſhing of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110713:48"/>
the body, does but drown the faculties, <hi>ſtupefie</hi> or <hi>choak</hi> the ſpirits, and defile all the parts; not <hi>purifie</hi> and <hi>cleanſe.</hi> And although the more <hi>ſubtile</hi> and <hi>thinner</hi> portion, paſſeth away in ſome perſons pretty freely by <hi>Urine;</hi> yet the <hi>groſſer</hi> and worſe part ſtayes behind, and clogs in the <hi>percolation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A third injury, and common, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt prejudice from intemperate drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is; <hi>An imbecility of the Nerves;</hi> which is procured from the diſorderly motions of the Animal Spirits; being impulſed and agitated preternaturally by the <hi>inebriating ſpirits</hi> of ſtrong Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors: which <hi>vibration</hi> being frequent, begets a habit, and cauſeth a <hi>trepidati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of Members.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:110713:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VII. Exerciſe</hi> and <hi>Reſt,</hi> regulated and duly appointed.</head>
               <p>THat <hi>Exerciſe</hi> and due <hi>Motion</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to the preſervation of Health, and prolongation of Life, will appear, if we conſider the benefits that are procured by it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In general exerciſe it raiſeth the ſpirits, and puts them upon vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>action</hi> in all the Faculties.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It <hi>empties</hi> the <hi>ſtomach,</hi> and promotes the appetite for the next meal: the remainders after digeſtion, that <hi>accumulate</hi> to clog the ſtomach, is moved by Exerciſe, and <hi>excited</hi> to paſs away; and being thus diſcharged of thoſe <hi>relicts;</hi> the appetite grows ſharp, and craves food very ſtrongly.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It provokes <hi>expulſion</hi> of <hi>Excrements,</hi> and ſuffers not any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous matter to lodge in the body: For, by the <hi>turgid motion</hi> of the ſpirits,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110713:49"/>
the common <hi>ductures</hi> and conveyancies are <hi>dilated</hi> and <hi>expanded;</hi> which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the agitation of the body, gives a ready and free paſſage to any <hi>feculent</hi> or <hi>excremental</hi> matter that <hi>ought</hi> not long to be retained.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Exerciſe</hi> opens the Pores, and gives a <hi>free tranſpiration;</hi> which otherwiſe by too much reſt are <hi>occluded</hi> and ſhut up, contrary to the intention of Nature; having appointed theſe <hi>vents,</hi> and ſecret way of evacuation, to <hi>ventilate</hi> and cleanſe the habite of the body, which in a ſhort time would be very foul and impure, by <hi>congeſtion</hi> of ſuperfluous humours, if not purified and tranſpired by theſe exhaling ports.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Exerciſe, promotes, and adds much towards the nutrition of the body. For this we find generally, that active ſtirring people, are more freſh in countenance, more vegete and lively in ſpirit, more firm and ſolid in fleſh, and ſtronger in their limbs; then other perſons that live a ſedentary, idle and ſluggiſh life. And that it ſhould be ſo there is good reaſon; in as much as exerciſe gives a free paſſage for nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment to arrive at every member and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110713:50"/>
part of the body; and alſo excites the Archeus or ruling principle in each, for a more vigorous aſſimilation; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe does expedite and ſend away the ſuperfluities of every digeſtion, all which promotes and ſets forward a good nutrition.</p>
               <p>Exerciſes are various, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen, as each perſon phanſies, or the Company invites; as <hi>Dancing, Running, Ringing, Tennis, Hand-Ball, Foot-Ball, Riding, Fencing;</hi> with many others: ſome whereof are purely paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, as thoſe named; others neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry labours, as Digging, Sawing, and ſuch like. Exerciſe is to be choſen, ſuch as ſutes beſt with the Nature of each perſons body: Some require ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing of upper parts moſt, others of the lower parts, and ſome equally both: thoſe Exerciſes which generally are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious, in uſing and ſtretching all the parts, and which I prefer before others, are <hi>Tennis, Hand-Ball, Fenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Ringing.</hi> Yet I would not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon any contrary to their inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for in theſe caſes, that which is moſt delightful, will probably prove moſt beneficial.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:110713:50"/>Obſervations and Cautions to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred in exerciſing, are ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Exerciſe daily, in the morning chiefly; with an <hi>empty ſtomach</hi> alwayes; and after <hi>excremental evacuation</hi> if you can procure it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Vary exerciſe</hi> according to the condition of your body, and <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of the year: the ſtronger, <hi>phlegmatick</hi> bodies, and in cold Weather, admit of ſtronger and ſwifter motions: <hi>Cholerick</hi> hot bodies, weak, and the Summer ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; more mild and gentle.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be not <hi>violent</hi> in exerciſe; nor continue it longer beyond a <hi>pleaſure;</hi> but deſiſt with <hi>refreſhment,</hi> not a laſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and wearineſs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Put on ſome looſe garment, until your body be cool and ſetled in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat and temper; the Pores being opened by exerciſe, the cold is more apt to enter; from whence a greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice then you could expect benefit from your labour or paſtime.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Walk gently</hi> after Exerciſe, and ſettle by degrees; no ſuddain changes are ſuteable or profitable to Nature.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Eat not,</hi> untill you be fully redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110713:51"/>
to that temper and <hi>moderate heat,</hi> as when you began; and when the ſpirits are retired to their proper <hi>ſtations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this rational courſe the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that will accrue to you are theſe.</p>
               <p>Exerciſe <hi>rouſeth</hi> dull inactive ſpirits; gives ventilation, <hi>opens obſtructions</hi> by the motion, attenuation and penetration of the ſubtile ſpirits; <hi>agitates</hi> and <hi>vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſeth</hi> feculent ſubſiding humours; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates ſuperfluous moiſture; increaſeth <hi>natural heat;</hi> promotes <hi>concoction, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution</hi> and conveyance of aliment, through the narrow Channels and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages unto the ſeveral parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; procures <hi>excremental evacuations;</hi> ſtrengthens all the <hi>Members,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Nature long in her vigour and virdure.</p>
               <p>Having ſet out the times for <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe</hi> and <hi>Motion;</hi> the remainder is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted for <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Eaſe,</hi> with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and repaſt as Nature requires.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Quod ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quie durabile non eſt. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Reſt</hi> is as neceſſary to preſerve <hi>Health,</hi> and continue mans body in ſtrength and vigour, as Exerciſe. Theſe two, although much oppoſite in themſelves, yet both in their order and ſeaſons, are very ſuteable and agreeable to humane
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110713:51"/>
Nature, and both contribute to the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and long <hi>being</hi> of Man. Nothing conſtant is liking and congruous with our Nature; but <hi>viciſſitude</hi> is moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and delightful.</p>
               <p>When the body is wearied with <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> then <hi>reſt</hi> is refreſhing, and renews its ſtrength; but when ſatiated with <hi>reſt,</hi> does then thirſt after <hi>motion</hi> &amp; pleaſant <hi>exerciſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Interdum quies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieta eſt; quoties nos male habet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertia ſui impatiens <hi>Sen.</hi>
                  </note> Reſt is a burthen if forced upon <hi>Nature,</hi> longer then <hi>Nature</hi> does require; and that is but for a ſhort ſpace. So that the due timing of <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Motion,</hi> and limiting them to their hours and ſeaſons, moſt agreeable and delightful to humane Nature, is that which preſerves him in <hi>Health,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs</hi> his <hi>Being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Avoid <hi>idleneſs,</hi> and a <hi>ſluggiſh ſeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary life:</hi> for want of due action and wholſom motion; the body, like ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Waters, degenerates and corrupts. If <hi>Reſt</hi> exceeds, the vigor of Nature is abated; <hi>digeſtion</hi> not ſo good; <hi>diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of aliment to the ſeveral parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded and impedited, by reaſon of an obſtructed foul body: excrementitious ſuperfluities not freely tranſmitted and emitted; the ſpirits dulled, and all the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110713:52"/>
faculties of the body and mind, heavy and ſlow to action.</p>
               <q>Ignavia corpus habetat, labor firmat.</q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII. Sleep</hi> and <hi>Watching,</hi> Limited and Cautioned.</head>
               <p>THE Life of Man being conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in <hi>viciſſitudes,</hi> ſpends its whole courſe in theſe two different ſtates, <hi>Sleep</hi> and <hi>Watching:</hi> the one appointed for <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Eaſe,</hi> the other for <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Labour.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nemo dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dormit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licujus eſt pretii, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magis quam ſi non vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Quidam.</note> If he were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the firſt, his life were but the ſhadow of <hi>Death,</hi> not worth the name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: if in the latter, he could not hold out long, but be tyred and worn out. Therefore Nature hath wiſely contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that he ſhould not continue long in either, but ſhould be <hi>tranſient</hi> from one to the other, and weave out his life by theſe ſhort intervals. <hi>Watching, Action</hi> and <hi>Motion; Sleep, Reſt</hi> and <hi>Ceſſation;</hi> are equally requiſite for the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110713:52"/>
well-being of man: So that theſe two changes relieving one another, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a defence and ſupport of humane life.</p>
               <p>Sleep is a <hi>placid ſtate</hi> of body and mind, bringing refreſhment and eaſe to both. Sleep takes off the <hi>Body</hi> from <hi>action,</hi> and the <hi>Mind</hi> from <hi>care, thought</hi> and <hi>buſineſs;</hi> and gives a ceſſation and quiet interval from their <hi>Labour.</hi> That ſleep may prove moſt advantagious, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the intentions and deſignment of Nature, it muſt be regulated in theſe four particulars: the <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Limits,</hi> the <hi>Place,</hi> and the <hi>Manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Time moſt proper and fit for Sleep, and according to the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Nature, is the Night; when moſt of the Creatures alſo do take their reſt. At the ſhutting up of the day, and the Sun departed from the <hi>Horizon;</hi> the ſpirits are not ſo <hi>active</hi> and <hi>lively,</hi> but incline to a <hi>ceſſation,</hi> and then it is fit to give them their <hi>repoſe</hi> and <hi>reſt,</hi> and not conſtrain them longer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on duty: in the morning again, at the riſing of the <hi>Sun,</hi> they are freſh, brisk and agile; and then are no longer to be chained up in <hi>ſomnolent darkneſs</hi> but to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110713:53"/>
be ſet at <hi>liberty,</hi> and enjoy the bright light, which chears the ſpirits, and is a great enlivener to them.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Turpis qui alto ſole ſemiſomnis jacet,</l>
                  <l>Cujus vigilia medio die incipit. <bibl>
                        <hi>Sen.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Moderate ſleep <hi>refreſheth</hi> the <hi>ſpirits;</hi> fortifies and increaſeth <hi>vital heat;</hi> helps <hi>concoction;</hi> gives <hi>ſtrength</hi> to the body; pacifies <hi>anger; calms</hi> the ſpirits, and gives a <hi>relaxation</hi> to a troubled mind.</p>
               <p>Immoderate ſleep <hi>dulls</hi> the ſpirits; injurious to a good <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>memory;</hi> fills the <hi>head</hi> with ſuperfluous moiſture, and clouds the <hi>brain;</hi> retains <hi>excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> beyond their due time to be voided; and <hi>infects</hi> the body with their noxious fumes and vapours; an enemy to <hi>beauty,</hi> and changeth the freſh flower of <hi>Youth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Go early to <hi>ſleep</hi> (not with a full ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach) and early from <hi>ſleep;</hi> that you may riſe refreſhed, lively and active; not dulled and ſtupid.</p>
               <p>Avoid <hi>day ſleeps</hi> as a bad cuſtom; chiefly fat and corpulent bodies: but if your ſpirits be tired with much buſineſs and care; or by reaſon of old age, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:110713:53"/>
of Nature, extream hot weather,<note place="margin">So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridianus quibus conceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> labour or the like, that <hi>diſſipates</hi> the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and enervates; then a moderate ſleep reſtores the ſpirits to their vigor again, and is a good refreſhment; but rather take it <hi>ſitting</hi> then <hi>lying</hi> down.</p>
               <p>Night watching, and late ſitting up, <hi>tires</hi> and <hi>waſts</hi> the animal ſpirits, by keeping them too long upon duty; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitates Nature; changeth Youth, and a freſh florid countenance; heats and dries the body for the preſent; in time abateth natural heat;<note place="margin">Vigiliae longioris incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</note> breeds Rhumes and Crudities; and moſt injurious to thin lean bodies.</p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>place</hi> for ſleeping, take theſe <hi>cautions:</hi> Firſt, That you do not expoſe your ſelf to the open <hi>Air:</hi> for in the time of <hi>ſleep,</hi> Nature is not ſo well able to defend the body from external injuries of the <hi>Air;</hi> but lies more open to ſuch aſſaults, being off her guard, and retired to <hi>Reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Know alſo that it is a bad cuſtom to <hi>ſleep</hi> upon the <hi>ground,</hi> as many in the Summer ſeaſon do uſe to their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice: and thoſe whoſe condition of life neceſſitate them to it, (as <hi>Soldiers</hi>)
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:110713:54"/>
although for the <hi>preſent</hi> they eſcape the miſchief; yet afterwards, moſt are made ſenſible of the injury, by <hi>Aches, ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or <hi>weakneſs</hi> of <hi>Limbs,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infirmities that it procures.</p>
               <p>Sleep not in any <hi>damp place, Vault</hi> or <hi>Cellar,</hi> a ground Chamber, (much worſe unboarded) a new waſht Room, or new plaiſtered; but chuſe a <hi>high</hi> Room, <hi>dry, ſweet,</hi> well <hi>aired,</hi> free from <hi>ſmoke,</hi> and remote from any <hi>noiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let your Bed be <hi>ſoft,</hi> but not to <hi>ſink</hi> in; which ſucks from the body, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſts and impairs ſtrength: a Quilt upon a Feather-Bed, is both eaſie and wholſome.</p>
               <p>As for the manner or <hi>decumbiture,</hi> the body muſt lie eaſie, or ſleep will be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed: the head ſomthing <hi>elevated;</hi> the other parts as beſt likes every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but not upon the <hi>back,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly upon one <hi>ſide;</hi> but by <hi>turns:</hi> and be covered according to the Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and Seaſon of the Year.</p>
               <p>The <hi>mind</hi> alſo muſt be in a good po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, well compoſed and ſetled when you are in bed; or that will break off your <hi>ſleep</hi> before due time, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud you of your <hi>nights reſt:</hi> if you lie
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:110713:54"/>
down with roving troubled thoughts; they commonly will call you up before it is fit to riſe, and your ſleep not ſo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid and refreſhing. Therefore when you lay by your <hi>cloaths,</hi> lay aſide alſo your <hi>buſineſs, care</hi> and <hi>thoughts,</hi> and let not a wandring phanſie prevent your reſt, or awake you before due time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> Preſervation of Health, by Regular and Requiſite <hi>Evacuation</hi> and <hi>Retention.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL that the body <hi>receives</hi> is not fit to be <hi>retained;</hi> our food, though choicely pickt, and temperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, yet all does not turn into the ſubſtance of the body; but ſome part is to be <hi>ſeparated</hi> and ſent forth, the reſt to <hi>ſupply, nouriſh,</hi> and be <hi>aſſimila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> This regular courſe being conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, the body thrives, and is in good order; but if that which ſhould be <hi>evacuated</hi> and ſent forth, be <hi>retained;</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:110713:55"/>
or that which ought to be retained, be prodigally <hi>waſted,</hi> and injuriouſly <hi>emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> then the body ſuffers and decayes, when the regular <hi>oeconomy</hi> thereof is ſubverted. <hi>Hinc ingens morborum turba.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here we are to conſider of the various <hi>excretions</hi> that Nature does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and is <hi>beneficial;</hi> and of ſuch <hi>retentions</hi> as are <hi>injurious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Under this Head is compriſed excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by <hi>Stool,</hi> by <hi>Urine, menſtrual Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, Venus,</hi> by the <hi>Pores, Noſe</hi> and <hi>Ears:</hi> of which the former are of the greateſt concernment, and ſpecial care to be had of them.</p>
               <p>Excremental evacuations are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, proceeding from the ſeveral di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions; conveyed out by ſeveral <hi>Channels</hi> and <hi>Vents</hi> of Natures fabrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which duly evacuated, are no ſmal helps to the conſervation of health, and are the effects of a temperate and regular body.</p>
               <p>The <hi>retention</hi> of them beyond due time, argue diſcraſy of parts, or irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar living; and brings much detriment to the body, by their noxious inpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and putrid vapours, that infect and diſturb the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:110713:55"/>If the Belly be <hi>coſtive</hi> and <hi>bound</hi> up; if the Urine be <hi>ſuppreſt;</hi> the monthly Courſes <hi>ſtopt;</hi> the Pores <hi>occluded</hi> and ſhut up: the Soul will be ſtifled in the Body, and the Body polluted and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with its own Excrements: and as theſe are ſo, <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> in degree, ſwerving from rectitude; ſo it fares with the body <hi>better</hi> or <hi>worſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And on the contrary, if the <hi>Belly</hi> let paſs too ſoon and forceably, before the alimentary part be ſeparated, ſweep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down both together; if the <hi>Urine</hi> flows too freely, and drains the body; If the <hi>Female Courſes</hi> be immoderately current, and exhauſt the vital ſtream; If the <hi>Sperme</hi> be involuntarily iſſuing, and daily waſting; If the <hi>Texture</hi> be too lax and pervious, the Pores <hi>patent</hi> and <hi>evaporating;</hi> the damage is as great as the former, and as much to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as theſe evacuations are more or leſs <hi>enormous.</hi> So that nothing but <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> and an even courſe between theſe two extreams are conſervative of <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>longaevity.</hi> And that this may be ſo, all your <hi>actions</hi> and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>cuſtoms</hi> muſt be bounded by medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity: this is the Golden Chain that ties
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:110713:56"/>
all together; one Link whereof being broken, the whole is broken and diſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited; having a dependance and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al tye upon each other.</p>
               <p>As the diſcharging of Nature mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately and ſeaſonably, in all her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite <hi>evacuations,</hi> preſerves the body in <hi>health</hi> and <hi>ſtrength:</hi> ſo contrarily.</p>
               <p>Immoderate <hi>evacuations</hi> cauſeth weakneſs, debility of Nature by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtion, and procures ſeveral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, Cachexies, Conſumptions, Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To keep the body <hi>ſoluble</hi> is very good, that at leaſt <hi>once</hi> a day you may not miſs to have a ſtool; elſe the <hi>Faeces</hi> are hardned, the body heated, the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach moleſted, the appetite not ſo good, the head heavy, dull and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times pained; ſome groſſer matter which ſhould go away by <hi>ſeige,</hi> is brought by the Urinary paſſage; oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioning obſtructions, all which are very injurious and deſtructive to Health.</p>
               <p>Seaſonable and moderate <hi>Venus,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leviates Nature, and helps digeſtion: but <hi>immoderate,</hi> exhauſts the ſtrength
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:110713:56"/>
by effuſion of ſpirits; <hi>exſiccates</hi> and dries the Body, hurts the Brain and Nerves, cauſeth tremblings, dulls the ſight, <hi>debilitates</hi> all the faculties, haſtens old age, and ſhortens life. But of this more at large in my Treatiſe of <hi>Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Conſumptions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cibo vel potu repletis, ſuperfluè eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuatis, ſive exercitatis, coitus interdici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tempus optimum eſt manè, &amp; poſt dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hyeme &amp; vere frequentius permitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; aeſtate parciſſimè.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juvines ſanguinei &amp; pituitoſi libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius; parcius Melancholici, parciſſimè bilioſi, Senes, emaciati.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Menſtrual evacuations</hi> are proper to the Female Sex; and come to them at certain years, to ſome at fourteen or fifteen, to others at ſixteen or ſeventeen: and then Nature challengeth them monthly as her due; except ſhe hath <hi>conceived, nurſeth,</hi> or being grown <hi>old</hi> Nature does not require this evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And this is of ſuch concernment with them, that if this <hi>menſtrual Flux</hi> be not right in the ſeveral requiſites, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>times, quantity</hi> and <hi>quality,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:110713:57"/>
the whole body oftentimes is diſturbed; but alwayes ſome <hi>infirmity</hi> or <hi>complaint</hi> does follow: And therefore it much behoveth Women to have a ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that this <hi>courſe</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, according to each perſons proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of body; for all have them not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, nor is it to be expected: and when it happens otherwiſe, a <hi>due courſe</hi> is to be taken to reduce them into order, and procure them aright.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Flux</hi> ariſeth from a <hi>redundance,</hi> and is granted to Women for <hi>concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-ſake;</hi> that they might both nouriſh the <hi>foetus</hi> in the Womb, and have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſupply their own bodies: Therefore when there is no <hi>conception,</hi> Nature hath appointed a <hi>menſtrual eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation</hi> to ſpend the over-<hi>plus</hi> this way, during her capacity of having Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and when that time is paſt, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture taks up and makes no ſuch proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and then this <hi>evacuation</hi> ceaſeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:110713:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. X. The different</hi> ſtate <hi>and</hi> variation <hi>of Bodies.</hi> Commonly diſtinguiſhed by four <hi>Conſtitutions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat the <hi>Condition, Properties,</hi> and <hi>Habit</hi> of Bodies do much differ one from the other; and alſo the <hi>ſame</hi> by time doth vary and alter much from what it was, is that which I need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on the proof; every one almoſt, will confeſs the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and is convinced of this truth. But how this comes to paſs, and the reaſons of this difference and variation, is not unanimouſly agreed upon, but great diſſenting about the matter.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Galeniſts</hi> do compriſe the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of bodies under four <hi>Conſtitutions, Sanguine, Phlegmatick, Cholerick</hi> and <hi>Melancholick.</hi> And this they will have to ariſe from the difference of bodies in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:110713:58"/>
                  <hi>mixtion,</hi> according to the different pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions they receive of the four <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> participating more of ſome, then the other.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chymical Philoſophers;</hi> ſome of them will have the difference of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to aſſurge out of three Principles, <hi>Sal, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercury:</hi> Others increaſe that number, and will have have them five, <hi>Spirit, Salt, Sulphur, Water</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> But I muſt not now ingage in the controverſie between the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> and <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> or make another party to oppoſe both; but reſerve that as more proper for a <hi>Polemical Tract:</hi> This Work being not intended contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, but Canonical, I therefore paſs on to ſtate the Matter.</p>
               <p>Theſe four tearms of <hi>Sanguine, Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick, &amp;c.</hi> although I do not adhere to them in the common acceptation, and in every point as the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> uſe them; yet they being ſo familiar and well known to ſuch for whom chiefly this work is intended; I ſhall retain theſe names with diſtinction and limitation to ſerve our preſent purpoſe, rather then impoſe new words upon you, not ſo well underſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:110713:58"/>I do not therefore underſtand by <hi>Phlegm, Choler,</hi> &amp;c. that every body is compoſed of theſe four humours, as their conſtitutive parts, reſulting from <hi>proportionate</hi> and <hi>diſproportionate</hi> mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and combination of the four <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> But that perſons may participate of, or abound with a degenerate hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; and that the <hi>ſucculencies</hi> of the body may incline to ſuch a condition, <hi>affine</hi> and <hi>analogous,</hi> or having ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, as that which is aſſigned to, and called, <hi>Phlegm, Choler,</hi> &amp;c. may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed, and we may call them by ſuch names. But you muſt alſo take notice, that the degenerate matter in mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is ſo various, that you muſt not think to reduce all ſuch depraved Jui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces exactly to theſe three heads, of <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Phlegm,</hi> and <hi>Melancholly;</hi> and if you add twice three more, the number would not be ſufficient: But ſince there is not <hi>peculiar appellations</hi> to diſtinguiſh all preciſely by, better have ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral tearms then none.</p>
               <p>The variation of bodies, in relation to <hi>Temperament, Habit,</hi> and <hi>Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> does ariſe <hi>immediatè</hi> from the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of <hi>digeſtions,</hi> and the different
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:110713:59"/>
                  <hi>products</hi> from thence: ſo that one and the ſame perſon ſhall by time be of <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent conſtitutions,</hi> according as the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the body are performed well or ill.</p>
               <p>The changing or eſtabliſhing of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions <hi>procatarcticè,</hi> does depend upon ſubjection and obedience to the <hi>Diaetitick Rules.</hi> As every one is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered prudently and regularly, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently and incongruouſly, ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to this or that <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> If a man live idle, plentifully feeding, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging himſelf in raw Fruits, and ſleeps much; this diſpoſeth him to be <hi>Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick:</hi> that is, his digeſtions ſhall not be ſo good; and there will be <hi>crude</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts abounding, ſuch as is called <hi>Phlegm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man be of an <hi>active cogitative</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, eager in buſineſs, giving himſelf little reſt, accuſtomed to Wine and high ſeaſoned Meats: This manner of life fires and heats the body; the <hi>Juices</hi> then will not be ſo <hi>mild, temperate,</hi> and <hi>balſamick:</hi> but <hi>acrid, bot</hi> and <hi>ſharp;</hi> and this perſon then may be ſaid to be of a <hi>cholerick</hi> conſtitution or condition of body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:110713:59"/>If a freſh <hi>ſanguine</hi> perſon, of a pure wholſom body; be oppreſſed with care and grief, live a ſedentary life, or too much given to <hi>ſtudy</hi> and ſerious <hi>contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation,</hi> and feed groſly. This courſe of life ſhall change and alter the beſt conſtitution; the <hi>ſanguine</hi> brisk airy perſon ſhall by theſe means, be of a <hi>dull</hi> heavy diſpoſition, and ſad mind; the body alſo ſhall degenerate from its purity, the humours more fixed and feculent. The Soul being the great <hi>Spring,</hi> or <hi>Wheel</hi> that keeps all the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in motion, upon which they do depend, <hi>primò &amp; principaliter,</hi> as the Fountain of all Vital Actions: If this be <hi>dejected</hi> and taken off its <hi>ſpeed,</hi> the functions are then performed very <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily,</hi> as if <hi>weights</hi> and <hi>clogs</hi> were hung upon them; and then the <hi>elaboration</hi> of food is not well performed, and a pure alimentary Juice produced; but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate <hi>ſuccus</hi> of a heavy oppreſſing nature not duely fermented by the <hi>Spleen (dyſcraſyed</hi> by the preceding Cauſes) from whence a <hi>melancholly</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is begotten, and may ſo be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated for diſtinction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:110713:60"/>The diverſity of <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> being thus underſtood, we may make uſe of, and retain theſe diſtinguiſhing tearms, at this time to ſerve the buſineſs in hand; ſince they are ſo familiar by uſe, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be apprehended, by ſuch for whom this is intended. But although I can cloſe with them in relation to this purpoſe I am now upon, to order and appoint a <hi>Diaetetick Regiment</hi> for diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent bodies; yet I think them not of that concernment, for a Phyſician to tye himſelf ſtrictly to their obſervance, in the <hi>deſignment</hi> of <hi>Cures;</hi> theſe <hi>noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> being too ſuperficial and remote from the <hi>quiddity, eſſence</hi> and <hi>ſpring</hi> of the Diſeaſe; are but <hi>Characteriſtical</hi> and <hi>Signal,</hi> to note how, and which way the vital Powers do deviate and ſwerve from their integrity; are but the <hi>Producta Morbi,</hi> the Products and Effects, ſeparable, and the Diſeaſe may remain behind.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I cannot allow them, as they are ſeverally injoyned in the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodus Medendi</hi> for indications, to ſute Purgatives <hi>electivè,</hi> and other Medicines to, by peculiar <hi>appropriations;</hi> nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with ſome <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> that are foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:110713:60"/>
upon this Doctrine by the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> to ſteer them in their <hi>Therapeuticks;</hi> which indeed runs them upon great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in the Cure of moſt Diſeaſes; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo nice in <hi>temperaments, humours</hi> and <hi>qualities,</hi> and eying them ſo much; that they neglect the ſpring from whence they do ariſe,<note place="margin">Natura eſt morborum medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix. <hi>Helm.</hi>
                  </note> and where the greateſt <hi>ſtreſs</hi> of Cures do lie. <hi>Morbi in initiis vitalibus radicem habent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although I have diſtinguiſhed food for ſeveral <hi>conſtitutions</hi> or <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of body, as moſt proper and fit for them, and commonly moſt <hi>agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>appetible;</hi> yet I do not thereby ſtrictly enjoyn, or reſtrain any one of a <hi>diſſenting appetite,</hi> from ſome things greatly coveted and ſuteable by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, although appointed for another perſon of a different <hi>conſtitution:</hi> but that every perſon ſeeing the general <hi>Rule,</hi> may ſomething be guided there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; and examining his peculiar proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Body, undiſcernable to others; whether it will comply freely, or with reluctance. In ſuch caſe where there is a refuſal of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> as not ſuting, but diſguſtful; you are not to impoſe upon your Nature forcibly, though
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:110713:61"/>
injoyned by the <hi>general Rule:</hi> But where you are at a ſtand in things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, what to chuſe when either will comply and ſute your appetite, then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Rule</hi> as advantagious. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the ſtrong <hi>robuſt</hi> bodies, <hi>active</hi> and <hi>laborious,</hi> are not ſo ſtrictly enjoyned to obſervance, as <hi>tender weak</hi> bodies, ſoon diſcompoſed and altered by ill dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, or <hi>incongruous</hi> for their <hi>condition</hi> of body.</p>
               <p>If a perſon have a cold, wateriſh, <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> Stomach; thoſe <hi>Meats,</hi> and <hi>Drinks,</hi> and <hi>Sauces,</hi> are not ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable and requiſite for him, as will well agree and ſute with a <hi>Cholerick, hot,</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> parching Stomach. A <hi>Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick</hi> man moſt commonly takes no delight in Milk and Whey, cold Meats, and cooling Drinks, or cooling Sauces: but he loves ſeaſoned hot Meats, ſtrong Drinks, Spices, and hot Hearbs, to make his Meat ſavory and acceptable to his Stomach: But the <hi>Cholerick</hi> Man ſhall delight in the other; and they ſhall ſute beſt, being temperately and diſcretely uſed. So that a <hi>Diaetetick Regiment,</hi> well appointed and obſerved, is <hi>phyſical</hi> to <hi>dyſcraſyed</hi> and <hi>diſtempered</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:110713:61"/>
bodies, to <hi>contemperate</hi> and <hi>allay</hi> the the <hi>luxuriance</hi> of ſome predominant Humour; and ſomething diſpoſe the faculties to produce the <hi>alimentary Jui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of another nature: which by time will alter and change the <hi>conſtitution</hi> or <hi>condition</hi> of Body from what it was, and reduce it nearer to what it ought to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> Praecautions <hi>and</hi> Rules, Appointed for the <hi>Sanguine</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; or pureſt State and Condition of Body.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Conſtitution</hi> does reſult from the integrity of the faculties, and due <hi>Craſes</hi> of the Parts, performing their offices rightly: When Food is well <hi>elaborated</hi> and <hi>tranſmuted</hi> in ſuch manner as is proper for each <hi>digeſtion;</hi> then a good <hi>conſtitution</hi> and good <hi>habit</hi> of body is eſtabliſhed. The Maſs of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:110713:62"/>
blood then hath its pure tincture, and all the liquors of the body their peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar <hi>properties</hi> ſuteable to the intentions of Nature: But if the <hi>Craſes</hi> of the <hi>Parts</hi> be perverted by a <hi>ſpontaneous</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and imbecility of the <hi>faculties;</hi> or otherwiſe procured to <hi>irregularity,</hi> by bad <hi>food, intemperance,</hi> and the <hi>Diae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetick Rules</hi> not obſerved; then the <hi>alimentary Juices</hi> do degenerate from their purity; the maſs of Blood, and <hi>nervous liquor</hi> are depraved, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and whole habit of body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and changed for the worſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſanguine</hi> perſon enjoyes the beſt ſtate and condition of body; does not abound or is moleſted with <hi>crude, Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick</hi> or <hi>acrid Cholerick Juices,</hi> or otherwiſe degenerate; but hath the <hi>ſucculencies</hi> of body in their right and proper natures, as is moſt fit for every veſſel and part of the body: hence it is that this perſon is more <hi>freſh, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, lively,</hi> and <hi>florid;</hi> of a more <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> mind, and <hi>good diſpoſition,</hi> having pure blood, and other good Juyces to ſupply the Body; from whence the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> are generated both plentifully, and of a <hi>good</hi> extraction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:110713:62"/>This <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of Body is beſt preſerved and continued ſo from degeneration, by a good <hi>Diaetetick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment;</hi> diſpoſing all the requiſite ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Life, Cuſtoms and Actions whatſoever; that they be <hi>moderate, ſeaſonable</hi> and <hi>ſuteable</hi> to ſuch Natures, contributing their aſſiſtance wholly, and not being any wayes detrimental, by their ill management.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sanguine Perſon</hi> will continue long in that condition and good ſtate of Body; by a due obſervance of <hi>Dyet, Exerciſe</hi> and <hi>Reſt, Sleep</hi> and <hi>Watching, Excretions</hi> and <hi>Retentions, paſſions</hi> of <hi>Mind:</hi> For any of theſe irregular and unſuteable, will alter and change the beſt tempered body, into ſome other depraved condition anſwerable to their Cauſes: as the intemperate <hi>Air</hi> of a hot <hi>Climate,</hi> or ſudden change of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not regarded; <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> Exerciſe, <hi>night-watchings, ill-dyet,</hi> &amp;c. introduceth a depraved alteration and degeneration of the blood: and therefore moſt commonly ſickneſs ſoon follows ſuch injurious Courſes. I might here forbid the ſmoaking of Tobacco; the common <hi>Purgatives</hi> falſly denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:110713:63"/>
but rather and more properly Corruptives; which ſtamp an ill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon the <hi>parts,</hi> and vitiate the alimentary Juyces of the Body: but the injuries procured from Tobacco, and theſe Drugs, are declared at large in my Tract of the <hi>Scurvy;</hi> Therefore I need not repeat here.</p>
               <p>For the Election and Choice of <hi>Food,</hi> for <hi>quantities</hi> and due <hi>times</hi> in <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking;</hi> for the choice of <hi>Air,</hi> and <hi>place</hi> of Abode; for <hi>Exerciſe, Sleep, &amp;c.</hi> conſonant and moſt agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this conſtitution and beſt ſtate of Body; are to be ſought in the general <hi>Hygiaſtick Rules</hi> before mentioned, which are moſt proper and applicable to this <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> of Body; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Rule or Standard to meaſure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by: And by how much others va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from this <hi>temperature</hi> &amp; good <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Body; by ſo much are they to be accounted <hi>intemperate</hi> and <hi>deviating</hi> from integrity; and do therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſome particular <hi>Rules</hi> or <hi>Exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> from the general, to regulate them apart; becauſe <hi>bodies</hi> in a right and good <hi>ſtate</hi> are not to be governed by the ſame ſtrictneſs of <hi>Law;</hi> but muſt have ſome
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:110713:63"/>
                  <hi>allowance</hi> and <hi>exceptions,</hi> which ſhall be obſerved in the particular conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XII.</hi> Diaetetick Regiment, Aſſigned to the Phlegmatick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> Perſon is ſuch whoſe nature is not ſo <hi>vigorous</hi> and <hi>acute</hi> in the digeſtive faculties; and makes a tranſmutation of food not ſo perfect as the <hi>Sanguine,</hi> but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>crude</hi> and <hi>raw.</hi> This Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on abounding with <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and being more cool in <hi>tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> (except preternaturally diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the <hi>Archeus</hi> diſturbed) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly hath a ſlower <hi>Pulſe;</hi> not ſo live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>active</hi> and <hi>brisk</hi> as the Sanguine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; prone to ſleep and eaſe; of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour <hi>paler;</hi> by hot things <hi>benefitted,</hi> by cold things <hi>prejudiced.</hi> And thus it is
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:110713:64"/>
by reaſon the <hi>vital powers</hi> are remiſs and ſluggiſh; the ſeveral functions of the body are not performed vigorouſly and compleatly.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of body being fallen a degree from the integrity of Nature, and ſwerving from the beſt condition and ſtate of body, which is the <hi>Sanguine;</hi> and finding by theſe <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> how Nature is defective, and which way declining: You ought ſo to order all your <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>cuſtoms,</hi> as may tend to the <hi>rectifying</hi> of this defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, and be auxiliary for a <hi>reduction</hi> to the beſt ſtate; at leaſt prevent what may ſucceed <hi>worſe,</hi> and ſtop the <hi>increaſe.</hi> And herein it will be no ſmall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to know what is <hi>aſſiſting</hi> and <hi>help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to Nature in this caſe, and what is <hi>injurious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meats</hi> agreeable and convenient for this condition of body, are ſuch as be <hi>light</hi> and <hi>digeſt</hi> well, becauſe the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs <hi>ferment</hi> is not ſo <hi>acute;</hi> yet if the Stomach covets what is not of <hi>facil</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, let it be made <hi>ſavory</hi> and <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned:</hi> And then a <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> raw ſtomach may better venter upon ſuch. But <hi>Brawn, Pig, Gooſe, Duck,</hi> water-foul,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:110713:64"/>
and ſuch like, are not agreeable to a Phlegmatick Stomach: Alſo <hi>Eeles, freſh Herrings, Makerel, Lobſter, freſh Salmon, Sturgeon,</hi> are injurious and difficult to be digeſted. But if you muſt pleaſe your pallate, drink Wine with theſe meats for a corrective.</p>
               <p>Let your dyet be warm Meats, oftner <hi>roaſt</hi> then <hi>boyled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Butter, Oyl,</hi> and <hi>Honey</hi> is good for you; <hi>Muſtard, Salt</hi> and <hi>Spices</hi> are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for your uſe: eſpecially with meats of ſlow digeſtion, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with much moiſture, and are apt to clog the Stomach.</p>
               <p>Refuſe <hi>Milk</hi> and <hi>Milk</hi> Meats, <hi>curd</hi> new <hi>Cheeſe, Butter-milk</hi> and <hi>Whey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Olives, Capers, Broom-buds, Sampire</hi> are good Sauce; alſo <hi>Garlick, Onions, Leeks</hi> in Broths, ſeaſonings or Sauces, for a reliſh, but not raw.</p>
               <p>Refrain cold Hearbs and Sallads; as <hi>Lettice, Purſlan, Violet-leaves,</hi> &amp;c. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Sorrel,</hi> which although cold, yet a ſharpner of the appetite: but freely uſe <hi>Mint, Sage, Roſemary, Time, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jerome, Parſley, Penny-royal,</hi> and ſuch hot Hearbs.</p>
               <p>Abſtain from raw Fruits; <hi>Apples,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:110713:65"/>
Pears, Plums, Cucumbers, Mellons, Pum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions,</hi> &amp;c. But you eat may <hi>Wall-nuts, Filbirds, Almonds</hi> blanched, <hi>Cheſ-nuts, Fiſtick-nuts, Dates, Figs, Raſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Drink <hi>ſtrong</hi> Beer more frequently then <hi>ſmall;</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Sack.</hi> Not <hi>French Wine</hi> if you be Rheumatick.</p>
               <p>Indulge not yourſelf in lying long in <hi>Bed;</hi> or afternoon ſleeps; and too much <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Eaſe:</hi> they dull the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, increaſe flegm and ſuperfluous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
               <p>But frequent <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> and moderate abſtinence in <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink;</hi> are great preſervatives of your Health.</p>
               <p>Chuſe a warm <hi>Air</hi> and dry <hi>Soil,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from <hi>Waters;</hi> the beſt place for your Abode.</p>
               <p>Hot <hi>Baths</hi> are profitable; ſeaſonable and moderate <hi>Venus</hi> a friend: the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cheriſheth the ſpirits, opens the pores for a tranſpiration and emiſſion of ſuperfluous moiſture: the latter ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates and raiſeth the ſpirits, <hi>alleviates</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and helps Concoction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:110713:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIII.</hi> The <hi>Cholerick Conſtitution</hi> Regulated.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Cholerick</hi> Perſon is more <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> than the <hi>Phlegmatick;</hi> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and <hi>precipitate</hi> in action; froward, haſty and angry; lean of body and ſlender: the <hi>Veins</hi> big, a hard <hi>Pulſe,</hi> and quick: of colour <hi>pale</hi> or <hi>ſwarthy;</hi> propenſe to waking and ſhort ſleeps; ſubject to Feavers, or febrile aeſtuation upon ſmall occaſions.</p>
               <p>That ſome bodies are in this <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> is apparent and certain: but whether by <hi>innate</hi> Principles ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, or otherwiſe procured and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitious;</hi> we will not controvert here: but ſhall proceed as granted, that a <hi>Diaetetick</hi> Regiment, <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill</hi> mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſhall make this perſon or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of body, <hi>better</hi> or <hi>worſe.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I adviſe ſuch to theſe obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Uſe a cool and moiſtning dyet; moſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:110713:66"/>
frequently boyled meats, rather than roſt or baked; but fryed or broiled meats never.</p>
               <p>Eat Broths often made with cooling Hearbs; <hi>Rice-milk, Cock-broth,</hi> or <hi>Barly-broths</hi> with <hi>Raſins, Currants</hi> and <hi>Prunes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For fleſh, chuſe young tender and jucy; as young <hi>Beef, Veal, Mutton, Lamb, Kid, Pork, Green-geeſe, Turkie, Capon, Chickens,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Obſerve fiſh dayes as good dyet: and then you may eat freſh <hi>Salmon, Lobſter,</hi> freſh <hi>Herrings, Crabs, Prauns,</hi> freſh <hi>Cod, Thornback, Soles, Plaiſe, Whiting, Smelt, Oiſters, Pike, Trout, Tench,</hi> and other freſh fiſh; Eeles not excepted which are unwholſome to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>But refrain ſalt Meats, and dryed; as <hi>Bacon, old Ling, Haberdine, ſalt Cod,</hi> pickled or red <hi>Herrings;</hi> pickled <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops, Oyſters, Anchoves, Sturgeon,</hi> hand <hi>Beef,</hi> dryed <hi>Tongues,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Milk and Milk meats are pleaſant and good; as <hi>Cuſtard, White-pots,</hi> new <hi>Cheeſe,</hi> freſh <hi>Cheeſe</hi> and <hi>Cream.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For your Sauces uſe <hi>Verjuce, Sorrel,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:110713:66"/>
Orange, Lemmon, Apples, Goosberries, Currans, Prunes,</hi> pickled <hi>Cucumbers:</hi> as boyled <hi>Veal</hi> and <hi>green-ſauce;</hi> roſt <hi>Veal</hi> and <hi>Orange;</hi> boyled <hi>Mutton</hi> with <hi>Verjuce</hi> and its own juce; roſt <hi>Mutton</hi> and <hi>Cucumbers;</hi> green-Geeſe and <hi>Gooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries;</hi> Stubble Gooſe and <hi>Apples;</hi> Pig and <hi>Currants;</hi> Pork and <hi>green-ſauce;</hi> boiled Chickens with <hi>Goosberries</hi> or <hi>Sorrel-ſops;</hi> Calves feet ſtewed with <hi>Currans</hi> and <hi>Prunes:</hi> And your meat thus coock'd, is both food and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</p>
               <p>Take a lawful freedom, and pleaſe your ſelf with theſe fruits; <hi>Citrons, Pomegranats, Limes, Oranges, Lemmons, Quince, Pearmains, Pippins, Cherries, Mulberies, Grapes, Damſins, Bullaces, Prunellaes, Reſpaſs, Currans, Barberries, Strawberries:</hi> they cool and quench thirſt, contemperate and aſwage hot cholerick humours, and give a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment to the parched ſpirits.</p>
               <p>Eat Sallads of <hi>Lettuce, Sorrel, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlane, Spinage,</hi> and <hi>Violet</hi>-leaves; they are medicamental aliment; but be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in <hi>Muſtard, Salt</hi> and <hi>Spices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Butter-milk, Whey</hi> and <hi>Sider</hi> allayes preternatural heat; checks the effre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:110713:67"/>
of Choler, and are refreſhing.</p>
               <p>Refuſe the fat, and brown out-ſide of meat: alſo the cruſt of Bread: and be ſparing in <hi>Butter</hi> and <hi>Oyl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Drink <hi>Wine, Spirits,</hi> and <hi>ſtrong Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors,</hi> but as <hi>Phyſick;</hi> to refreſh and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt a weak ſtomach, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>Faſt not, but ſatisfie the Stomach when it <hi>vellicates</hi> and calls for meat; biting <hi>choller</hi> muſt have ſomething to feed on, or it will diſturbe the body.</p>
               <p>Cheriſh and indulge <hi>ſleep,</hi> it cools and moiſtens; but let it not exceed in length, which puts Nature by her due times for neceſſary evacuations.</p>
               <p>Too eager and conſtant in <hi>ſtudy,</hi> or late ſitting up: both <hi>exaſperates</hi> this condition of body, and makes it worſe.</p>
               <p>Uſe very gentle <hi>Exerciſe;</hi> be not laborious or toyling, but take your <hi>eaſe;</hi> avoid <hi>violent</hi> motion, for it fires the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and heats the body, which is very injurious to this Conſtitution.</p>
               <p>Frequent <hi>venus</hi> is moſt pernicious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cold Baths</hi> is profitable, and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth much; by cooling the <hi>blood,</hi> allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpirits, and concentring them.</p>
               <p>Banniſh <hi>anger</hi> immoderate <hi>care, pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhneſs</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:110713:67"/>
and <hi>fretting,</hi> which diſcompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſpirits, heats and waſts them; augments <hi>Choller,</hi> dryes the body, and haſtens old Age.</p>
               <p>Refrain <hi>Tobacco</hi> as a very injurious cuſtom; it exaſperates Choler by heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drying, and evacuating dulcid <hi>Phlegm;</hi> which contemperates, bridles and checks the fury of <hi>acrid bilious</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIV.</hi> The <hi>Melancholy Conſtitution,</hi> Stated and Cautioned.</head>
               <p>BY <hi>Melancholy Conſtitution,</hi> I here underſtand ſuch a condition of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as is procured, and moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the conſequent of <hi>habituated Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy,</hi> or a <hi>melancholy</hi> heavy <hi>Soul,</hi> and a <hi>dyſcraſied Spleen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To paſs by the controverſies that might ariſe here from the diſtinction of <hi>melancholly</hi> by the <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> as one of the four <hi>conſtituent</hi> humours: I ſhall take for granted on both ſides, as well
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:110713:68"/>
Chymiſts as them; that the aforeſaid cauſes do beget ſuch a <hi>conſtitution</hi> or <hi>condition</hi> of body, as may well require a peculiar <hi>Diaetetick Regiment,</hi> as an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay or mitigation of thoſe <hi>preternatural Symptoms</hi> that neceſſarily follow ſuch <hi>Cauſes:</hi> at leaſt that they may not be aggravated by an injurious courſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
               <p>A <hi>melancholly, ſtudious</hi> and <hi>ſedentary</hi> life, does much abate and ſuſpend the <hi>emanative vigour</hi> and <hi>activity</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> equally diſtributed <hi>(geometricè)</hi> amongſt the ſeveral <hi>faculties,</hi> as the ſpring of their motion and actions: from which abatement and depreſſion of their power, the <hi>functions</hi> are not <hi>diſcharged</hi> ſo exactly and unblamably; but more or leſs, according to the agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>remiſſion</hi> of thoſe Cauſes. Now as the <hi>Spleen</hi> is more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently the ſeat of that <hi>paſſion;</hi> and commonly a part moſt apparently inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, leading the reſt into diſorder: We ſhall appoint ſuch a government, or prudent election and modification of ſuch things compriſed in the <hi>Diaetetick</hi> part of <hi>Phyſick;</hi> as may beſt ſute with ſuch a condition of body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:110713:68"/>The <hi>melancholly ſplenetick</hi> perſon, whoſe digeſtive faculties are <hi>debilitated,</hi> muſt feed more tenderly and nicely than another; elſe that <hi>flatulency</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion</hi> (which commonly does at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this condition of body) will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated and much more moleſting: For by a groſs and plentiful feeding, are thoſe evils increaſed.</p>
               <p>Let not your common <hi>dyet</hi> be of ſuch Meats as are hard and difficult to digeſt; that lie long upon the ſtomach, and require a ſtrong <hi>inciſing ferment</hi> for <hi>ſeparation</hi> and <hi>tranſmutation:</hi> as Meats <hi>long ſalted, dryed, fryed,</hi> or <hi>broyled,</hi> &amp;c. but keep to ſuch as are <hi>light</hi> and of <hi>facil</hi> digeſtion, that ſoon yeelds in <hi>fermentation,</hi> and is <hi>tranſmuted,</hi> without great labour and trouble. Meats thus diſtinguiſhed, you will find ſet down in the 59, 60, and 61 pages preceding, where you may make election.</p>
               <p>If you have a hot and dry coſtive body, uſe <hi>Barley-broths,</hi> with <hi>Prunes, Raſins</hi> and <hi>Currans:</hi> and you may eat ſometimes <hi>Pippins, Permains, Cherries, Reſpas, Straberries,</hi> and ſuch like good fruits to cool and moiſten.</p>
               <p>Take not a <hi>full</hi> meal at Supper, nor
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:110713:69"/>
                  <hi>late;</hi> but eat <hi>ſparingly:</hi> And if that be too much, as may eaſily be diſcovered, then forbear Suppers wholly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Capers, Broom-buds</hi> and <hi>Sampire,</hi> are good Sauce; they pleaſe the Pallate, quicken the Appetite, open Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and help Digeſtion: all which are profitable for this condition of body.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Borrage, Bugloſs, Endiue, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chory, Baum, Fumiterry, Mary-gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowers, Violets, Clove-gilliflowers</hi> and <hi>Saffron,</hi> are of good uſe.</p>
               <p>Drink <hi>Sider</hi> ſometimes, and ſmall <hi>White-Wine;</hi> alſo <hi>Whey,</hi> if your ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach agrees with it.</p>
               <p>Keep the body <hi>ſoluble;</hi> your Head will be more free from <hi>pains, fumes,</hi> and <hi>heavineſs:</hi> Alſo the lower Region of the Body will not ſo freequently be diſturbed with <hi>flatulent rumblings, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> and <hi>windy eruptions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cheriſh <hi>Sleep;</hi> it refreſheth the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, pacifies a troubled mind, baniſheth cares, and ſtrengthens all the faculties: but <hi>tireſome waking</hi> in the night, is a great enemy to a melancholly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>Fly Idleneſs, the Nurſe of Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly; but exerciſe often, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:110713:69"/>
buſineſs, or recreations.</p>
               <p>Walk in the green <hi>Fields, Orchards, Gardens, Parks,</hi> by <hi>Rivers</hi> and variety of places.</p>
               <p>Change of <hi>Air</hi> is very good.</p>
               <p>Avoid <hi>ſolitarineſs,</hi> and keep <hi>merry</hi> Company.</p>
               <p>Be frequent at <hi>Muſick, Sports</hi> and <hi>Games.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Recreate the ſpirits with <hi>ſweet, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant</hi> and <hi>delightful</hi> ſmells.</p>
               <p>Baniſh all paſſions as much as in you lies; <hi>fear, grief, diſpare, revenge, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, jealouſie, emulation,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <q>Opus eſt te Animo valere ut Corpore poſſis.</q>
               <p>Give not your ſelf to much <hi>ſtudy,</hi> nor <hi>night-watchings;</hi> two great enemies to a melancholly perſon.</p>
               <p>Refrain <hi>Tobacco,</hi> though a ſeeming pleaſant Companion; the <hi>phanſie</hi> is pleaſed but for a <hi>ſhort time;</hi> and the ill effects are <hi>durable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:110713:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XV.</hi> The various <hi>Dyſcraſies</hi> or <hi>Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> in general.</head>
               <p>MAN is made up of two grand Parts, <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body:</hi> the one <hi>Active, ruling</hi> and <hi>governing;</hi> the other <hi>Paſſive, obeying</hi> and <hi>inſtrumental:</hi> The one hath its due <hi>Craſis, tranquility</hi> and <hi>placidneſs:</hi> The other due <hi>organization</hi> and <hi>fabrication:</hi> But both are ſubject to diſorder, diſcompoſure, and inapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, for the regular performance of their Actions and Offices.</p>
               <p>Great diſcoveries have been made of that Part of <hi>Man,</hi> which preſents it ſelf to the <hi>eye:</hi> We have viewed his Fabrick; and I may ſay exactly, Witneſs the <hi>excellent Anatomical</hi> pieces that are <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,</hi> wherein are diſcovered and laid open all the contrivances of this rare <hi>Machine:</hi> But the <hi>Spring</hi> that ſets all on work; the <hi>intrinſick</hi> mover, the <hi>Soul,</hi> lies much in darkneſs, and acts as it were, behind the Curtain. Whoſe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:110713:70"/>
                  <hi>deficiencies</hi> and <hi>aberrations</hi> are little ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, except in the irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>paſſion;</hi> and then only in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>moral</hi> rectitude: And therefore in our Phyſical Diſcourſes, I find the Body to be accuſed of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and failing throughout the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of Diſeaſes; and that the <hi>indiſpoſition</hi> of <hi>Organs</hi> to act, is the <hi>ſole</hi> or <hi>main</hi> cauſe of the irregularity and deficiency of the Functions. And that the <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the Soul to act <hi>ad extra,</hi> does depend wholly upon the <hi>capacity</hi> and <hi>aptitude</hi> of the inſtrumental parts.</p>
               <p>But I am otherwiſe perſwaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: That as there is great difference of <hi>Souls</hi> in <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>moral</hi> goodneſs; why not then in <hi>natural</hi> abilities and integrity, relating to <hi>health</hi> and <hi>ſickneſs?</hi> And therefore it is very rational to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, that many defects or diſorders in the Functions, and ruinous decayes of the Body, does ariſe and ſpring forth from the <hi>pravity</hi> and <hi>debility</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> by its lapſid nature: And that the firſt motions, <hi>ab intra,</hi> or <hi>emanations</hi> of the Soul, are and may be infirm and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, when the <hi>Organs</hi> are in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitude and aptitude for regular moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:110713:71"/>
But to clear this out, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it to the full; I muſt ravel into the whole Doctrine <hi>de Anima,</hi> and aſſert contrary to the old <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> (which will be found very erroneous) but that will take up a whole <hi>Tract,</hi> too big for this place; and muſt be the work of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time. Therefore I paſs on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paſſions</hi> of mind may be conſidered, either in relation to what is <hi>divine, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> or <hi>natural.</hi> Paſſions reſpecting the two firſt, are either <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil,</hi> as their <hi>object</hi> do's diſtinguiſh them: but in the latter they are ill, and produce bad effects, as they in degree are more or leſs <hi>turbulent, violent</hi> and <hi>durable.</hi> What concerns the <hi>Paſſions</hi> in the two former reſpects, is not our buſineſs in hand; but as they ſtand in relation to <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Sickneſs;</hi> what diſorders they produce in the regular <hi>oeconomy</hi> of the Body, how the Functions are depraved, debilitated or ſuſpended by them is our task.</p>
               <p>The Diſeaſes or <hi>Dyſcraſies</hi> of the Soul moſt <hi>viſible,</hi> are the <hi>perturbations</hi> and <hi>paſſions,</hi> wherein the Soul is put by her <hi>genuine</hi> ſtate of placidneſs and ſerenity; and that <hi>aequanimous</hi> diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:110713:71"/>
of her <hi>energy</hi> into the Members and Parts of the Body, from thence diſordered and diſproportioned. <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> draws off the <hi>Soul</hi> from exerciſing and executing the <hi>functions</hi> of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: For whereas the power of the Soul is <hi>equally</hi> or <hi>proportionably</hi> divided into all the <hi>faculties</hi> in her natural <hi>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> ſtate and government: On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when <hi>Paſſion</hi> is <hi>predominant,</hi> much of that power is drawn away, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended in the proſecution and ſupport of this <hi>Paſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paſſions</hi> puts the ſpirits upon ſeveral motions: ſometimes <hi>contracts</hi> them, as in <hi>Grief, Fear,</hi> or <hi>Deſpare:</hi> Sometimes <hi>dilates</hi> them as in <hi>Joy, Love,</hi> and <hi>Deſire:</hi> Sometimes drives them <hi>furiouſly,</hi> as in <hi>Anger:</hi> wherein alſo the humours are <hi>fluctuating</hi> ſometimes this way, and ſometimes that way; according to the nature of the Paſſion, which hath its peculiar <hi>motion</hi> and <hi>current.</hi> And as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſeaſes have their <hi>Diagnoſtick</hi> Signs to diſtinguiſh them, and whereby they may be known: So likewiſe the <hi>Paſſions</hi> have their <hi>peculiar Characters</hi> of diſtinction; that it is not difficult to know under what <hi>paſſion</hi> a man labours.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:110713:72"/>
We judge of other ſickneſſes very much by the <hi>Face,</hi> what alteration there: So by the <hi>Countenance</hi> we may know what Paſſion is <hi>predominant;</hi> each put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on a different <hi>aſpect,</hi> and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf in another <hi>ſhape</hi> and <hi>viſage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paſſion</hi> in <hi>exceſs,</hi> although it be the perturbation and <hi>ſickneſs</hi> of the mind; yet it is not confined there, but is <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated</hi> to the Body, which partakes and ſhares in the <hi>morbous</hi> effect. If the <hi>Mind</hi> be diſtempered and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, the <hi>Body</hi> cannot continue in <hi>health.</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven with each other, and <hi>conjunct</hi> in their Operations, that they act toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, enjoy and ſuffer together: They are ſo linked and conjoyned, as Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of each others ill and wellfare, that the one is not affected, but the other is drawn into conſent; mutually act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, enjoying and ſuffering until death. Hence it is, a diſeaſed Body makes a heavy drooping mind; and a wounded, diſturbed or reſtleſs mind, makes a youthful healthy body to decay and languiſh. Who therefore deſires the health and wellfare of the body, muſt
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:110713:72"/>
procure Eaſe, Reſt, and Tranquility of mind.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <p>That you may the better know, and rightly underſtand how <hi>paſſions</hi> of the <hi>mind,</hi> redound and reflect upon the <hi>body</hi> to the decay and ruine of it, and <hi>abbreviating</hi> mans life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider that the <hi>Body</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Souls energy,</hi> is dead, and moves not at all: by vertue of the <hi>Souls</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with it, and <hi>informing power;</hi> the Body acts with various motions and opperations; and according to the <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> with <hi>organical</hi> aptitude and fitneſs of the Body, is the exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiteneſs and perfection of their operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The <hi>Soul</hi> then is <hi>Agent,</hi> the <hi>Body paſſive,</hi> receiving the influx virtue and power from the Soul, who is <hi>Rectrix</hi> and <hi>Gubernatrix,</hi> to whom the Rule and Government belongs. It is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent therefore, ſince the <hi>Body</hi> cannot act any thing of it ſelf for its conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without the energy and aſſiſtance from the <hi>Soul,</hi> whoſe care is for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating and moderating the <hi>Body</hi> in all actions <hi>external</hi> and <hi>internal;</hi> then the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:110713:73"/>
                  <hi>diſtractions, inactivity, wandrings,</hi> and <hi>neglects</hi> of the Soul, does tend to the ſubverſion of this due order and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and conſequently the ruine and diſſolution of the body, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a conſtant ſupply of daily repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and a <hi>regular tuition</hi> for its ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and maintenance.</p>
               <p>Now the Soul tranſported by paſſion from its <hi>genuine Craſis</hi> of placidneſs and tranquility, and reduced into a <hi>turbulent, unquiet</hi> and <hi>diſtempered</hi> ſtate; is that condition of incapacity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſs for government for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and many damages ariſe thereby, as in each paſſion particularly hereafter will appear.</p>
               <p>In a <hi>threefold</hi> manner the <hi>Soul</hi> is put beſides her ſelf in the regularity of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> and is incurious of the wellfare of the Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> is either carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by ſome <hi>delightful object;</hi> as for ſomething vehemently deſired; and deſerting, as it were, the body to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after that thing deſired and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>extending</hi> her power and ſtrength out of the body, to lay hold, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to obtain, and bring within the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:110713:73"/>
                  <hi>Sphere</hi> and <hi>Circle</hi> of her enjoyment, as in the Paſſion of Love.</p>
               <p>Or <hi>ſecondly,</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> is in <hi>fury</hi> and diſquieted within, by the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of ſomething aſſaulting and diſturbing; to which the <hi>Soul</hi> hath a <hi>contrariety</hi> and <hi>antipathy</hi> againſt: as in the paſſions of <hi>Fear, Hatred, Revenge, Anger:</hi> And this diſquietude and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance is continued by repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their cauſes in the <hi>phantaſie;</hi> which ſtill preſent themſelves to the <hi>Soul,</hi> by way of a freſh <hi>aſſault,</hi> which feeds the Paſſion, and continues the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper.</p>
               <p>Or <hi>thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Soul</hi> is languiſhing, heavy and inactive, altogether <hi>indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> to the government and tuition of the body; and perhaps deſirous to be <hi>diſcharged</hi> and ſhake it off, being weary of the burthen; taking no delight in their <hi>partnerſhip</hi> and ſociety, as in <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly deſpair</hi> and <hi>grief.</hi> In all which caſes you ſhall find the <hi>Body</hi> to ſuffer great <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>detriment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>firſt Caſe:</hi> When the <hi>Soul</hi> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enates her ſelf, wanders away with a <hi>vehement deſire</hi> to procure and obtain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing moſt agreeable and delightful,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:110713:74"/>
the <hi>Soul,</hi> as it were, <hi>contracts</hi> her ſelf, and <hi>unites</hi> all her force; ſtands at <hi>full bent</hi> after this beloved; diſchargeth all her thoughts upon it, and ſpends her ſtrength in <hi>deſire</hi> and <hi>longing;</hi> until at laſt ſhe pines away with a tedious and ſtarving expectation, if the beloved thing be not obtained. In the interim the <hi>oeconomy</hi> and government of her own <hi>manſion</hi> the Body is neglected; the ſpirits, which are accounted the Souls <hi>immediate Inſtruments</hi> in every Faculty, at leaſt a conſiderable part, is inticed away, and called off from their proper and peculiar <hi>works</hi> and <hi>duty;</hi> perhaps to enlarge and increaſe the <hi>vigour</hi> of ſome other <hi>faculty,</hi> more <hi>immediately</hi> ſubſervient and attending the Souls new deſign and buſineſs; preferred far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a good <hi>concoction,</hi> due <hi>excretion, nutrition,</hi> ſeaſonable <hi>reſt,</hi> or what elſe; and thoſe <hi>ſpirits</hi> remaining which have the burthen of theſe duties <hi>incumbent</hi> on them, have ſo ſmall and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſupport and ſupply of <hi>influence</hi> from the Soul, to direct and back them in their performance; that the <hi>functions</hi> are executed <hi>weakly</hi> and <hi>depravedly,</hi> to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:110713:74"/>
the great prejudice and damage of the Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concoction</hi> now is not ſo good, nor the <hi>Appetite</hi> ſo quick; the <hi>ſtomach</hi> calls not for a new ſupply, as yet not being well diſcharged and quit of yeſterdayes proviſion: the <hi>ſtomach</hi> now is weary of dreſſing and preparing long Dinners for the Body; <hi>Lenten</hi> and <hi>faſting</hi> dayes are its vacation from trouble.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Separation</hi> now is not ſo good; the <hi>excrementitious</hi> and <hi>nutritious</hi> part walk hand in hand together, and paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction or due examination: the <hi>watch</hi> now is not ſo ſtrict at the <hi>Ports</hi> and privy paſſages, to diſcern what is fit to paſs <hi>this way,</hi> and what the <hi>other,</hi> or what to reject and keep out; but <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> receive what preſents it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſtribution</hi> now is not ſo good; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liment</hi> tires by the way, wanting <hi>ſpirits</hi> to convey and bring it to its journeys end; and exerciſe to jog it on through the <hi>anguſt</hi> Meanders, and more difficult paſſages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sanguification</hi> is now degenerated and vitiated; the preceding requiſites
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:110713:75"/>
and fit <hi>praevious</hi> diſpoſition in order thereto, being wanting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Membrification</hi> or <hi>Aſſimilation</hi> is now changed for a <hi>Cachectick</hi> and depraved habit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Excretion</hi> and <hi>Evacuation</hi> of what is ſuperfluous and unfit longer to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the body; is not ſent away in due time, but ſtayes for a Paſs; the <hi>Governeſs</hi> is now taken up with other matters; neglects due orders and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to the <hi>expulſive faculty</hi> for their emiſſion.</p>
               <p>All neceſſary and wholeſome <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> are now neglected and diſregarded: the Soul too oft is wandring and gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abroad, and beſt when ſhe is ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from home; but neglects the <hi>air<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of her Cottage, and perfuming it with freſh <hi>aetherian</hi> breath. The Soul is now alwayes reſtleſs and diſturbed; nor ſhall the <hi>Senſes,</hi> her <hi>Attendants,</hi> take their due <hi>repoſe;</hi> but keeps an unquiet houſe at midnight.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>ſecond Caſe:</hi> The regular and due <hi>order</hi> of <hi>government</hi> in the Body is ſubverted and changed; when the Soul in the forementioned paſſions, of <hi>Fear, Anger, Hatred,</hi> and <hi>Revenge;</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:110713:75"/>
and <hi>alarum'd</hi> by the aſſault, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach or appearance of ſome evil or injury: the <hi>Soul</hi> then ſummons the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> together, and commands them from their common duties; calls them to her <hi>aid</hi> and <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> for ſecurity from danger, to repulſe the violence offered, or revenge the injury; hurry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them here and there, from one part to another in a tumultuous manner, if the aſſault be ſuddain and ſurprizing: ſometimes inward to ſupport the <hi>heart,</hi> to give courage and reſolution, which by their ſuddain concourſe and conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Center, cauſeth great <hi>pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitations,</hi> and almoſt <hi>ſuffocation:</hi> or elſe commanding them to the out-works; into the external parts, to repel the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion and violence of the evil preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or approaching, or to revenge the quarrel: the <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Arms</hi> then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a double or trebble ſtrength; the <hi>Muſcles</hi> being full and diſtended with agile <hi>ſpirits</hi> for their activity &amp; ſtrength in motion. The <hi>Eyes</hi> then are ſtaring full, and ſtretch'd forth with a croud of <hi>inflamed ſpirits,</hi> darting forth their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſpending their ſtrength upon the Adverſary and Object of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:110713:76"/>
The <hi>Tongue</hi> then is ſwelled with ſpirits and big words, that wanting a larger room for vent, tumbles out bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and imperfect ſpeeches, and ſcarce can utter whole words. The <hi>Legs</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> then have an Auxiliary ſupply, and double portion of <hi>ſpirits</hi> conveighed into their <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Sinews,</hi> to increaſe their agility and ſtrength, to come on or off. But in the mean time the <hi>Heart</hi> perhaps is almoſt fainting, ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deprived of, and deſerted by, thoſe lively <hi>vigorous ſpirits,</hi> which did inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and quarter there for its <hi>Life-Guard,</hi> protection and ſupport; but are now called off their <hi>Guard</hi> and common duties, imployed in Forreign Parts, commanded here and there as the <hi>emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> occaſions preſents it ſelf to the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs</hi> of this <hi>Microcoſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>third caſe</hi> mentioned: the due order, government, and neceſſary exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of offices belonging to the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and maintenance of the body, and preſervation of life, is neglected and weakly performed.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Soul</hi> being darkned and overſpread with a cloud of <hi>ſadneſs,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes her ſelf to a ſullen <hi>incurious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbency</hi>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:110713:76"/>
and retiredneſs; willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign up and caſt off the government and tuition of the body; and as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then which ſhe now delights not to bear about, begins to looſe her hold, who before had embraced and clipt ſo cloſe; ſuſpending the virtue of her <hi>energy</hi> and vigorous <hi>emanations;</hi> acting faintly and coldly, thoſe neceſſary mutual performances, without regard to their former friendſhip, or their future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct preſervation. The <hi>Body</hi> now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſink with its own weight, and preſs towards the <hi>Earth</hi> the natural place from whence it came. That ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therian ſpirit which before had boyed it up, and took delight to ſport it to and fro; is now ready to let it fall and grovel downwards, to leave it whether it muſt go. The wonted <hi>pleaſures</hi> of their <hi>partnerſhip</hi> and <hi>ſociety,</hi> is now diſguſted and rejected: <hi>Food</hi> now hath loſt its <hi>reliſh,</hi> and is become unſavory: <hi>Sleep</hi> which before was pleaſant, as a holy day in the fruition of reſt and eaſe, is now compoſed of nothing but trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome unquiet <hi>dreams;</hi> linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome fighting intervals, to meaſure out the weary night by. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:110713:77"/>
and ſporting Recreations is now accounted druggery and laborious toyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: unwilling is the <hi>Soul</hi> to move her yoak-fellow, farther then the enforcing <hi>Law</hi> of Nature, and neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and urgeth. Their joynt ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which before were duly and unanimouſly performed; are now <hi>ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, abated</hi> or <hi>depraved,</hi> by the <hi>retracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reluctance</hi> and indiſpoſed ſadneſs of the <hi>Soul</hi> to act: the wonted <hi>vigorous</hi> emanations of the Soul, and her radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant influence upon the ſpirits is now ſuſpended, ſubducted and called back. Theſe miniſtring attending <hi>Spirits</hi> and nimble <hi>Agents,</hi> which at a beck were alwayes ready, agile and active in the execution of her commands; now want Commands to ſtir, and Warrants to act by: but in a <hi>torpid</hi> and <hi>ſomnolent</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition, unfit for action, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite performance of their duties, and in a <hi>ſympathizing</hi> complyance with the Soul, the <hi>excitrix</hi> and <hi>rectrix</hi> of their motions; are ready to reſign their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and give over working; that what they now do, is faintly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſly performed, with much deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and depravation. When the <hi>Soul</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:110713:77"/>
is pleaſed and merry, the <hi>ſpirits</hi> dance and are chearful at their work; but when ſhe <hi>droops</hi> and <hi>mourns,</hi> the <hi>ſpirits</hi> are <hi>dull, heavy</hi> and <hi>tired,</hi> the <hi>Functions</hi> weakly and inſufficiently executed.</p>
               <p>From the preceding Diſcourſe may eaſily be collected; that the <hi>Diſtempers</hi> and <hi>Alienations</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> from her <hi>genuine Craſis</hi> of ſerenety and quietude, is of great diſadvantage to <hi>Health;</hi> for as much as the neceſſary <hi>Functions</hi> of the Body from hence are diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and inſufficiently performed; theſe perturbations alſo, impreſſing upon the Body various <hi>preternatural</hi> effects; forming the <hi>Ideas</hi> and <hi>Characters</hi> of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes upon the <hi>ſpirits,</hi> are by them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, implanted and propagated in the body: likewiſe the <hi>morbifick</hi> Seeds, and ſecret Characters of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes which lay dead and inactive; are by the <hi>oeconomical</hi> diſturbance and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation</hi> of mind, <hi>awakened, moved,</hi> and ſtirred up to hoſtility and action, which otherwiſe would have layen <hi>dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant:</hi> as by <hi>grief, fear, anger; hyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical paſſions, ſwoonings, epilepſies,</hi> &amp;c. are often procured: and it is evident, and commonly obſerved by infirm and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:110713:78"/>
diſeaſed people; how paſſion <hi>agravates</hi> and heightens their diſtempers; and according to the <hi>temper</hi> of their <hi>mind</hi> will their bodily infirmities be <hi>agrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> or <hi>abated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall draw up this Diſcourſe into three <hi>Corollaryes;</hi> being the <hi>Epitome</hi> of what hath been aſſerted and aimed at.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is no <hi>perturbation</hi> or <hi>paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of mind, whether little or great; but it works a <hi>real effect</hi> in the Body more or leſs, according to the nature and ſtrength of the paſſion; and by how much the more <hi>ſuddain, great, often,</hi> and of <hi>longer duration</hi> the paſſion is, by ſo much are the impreſſions and effects worſe, more durable and indeleable. You cannot be <hi>angry,</hi> or <hi>envious,</hi> or <hi>melancholly,</hi> or give way to any ſuch paſſion, but you cheriſh and feed an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy that <hi>preys</hi> upon your <hi>life;</hi> and you may be aſſured that paſſion makes as great, nay greater alteration within the body, then the change of your countenance appears to outward view, which is not a little; although but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or reflection of the inward di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper and diſorder: And were it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible by any <hi>perſpective</hi> to ſee the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:110713:78"/>
and diſcompoſure within made by a paſſionate troubled mind; the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> would be ſtrange, and much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from that <hi>placidneſs</hi> and <hi>tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of an indiſturbed quiet Soul.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Strong and vehement paſſions or affections of the mind too intent upon this or that object, whether <hi>deſirable,</hi> and to be enjoyed, or <hi>formidable,</hi> and to be avoided; <hi>alienates, ſuſpends</hi> and draws off the wonted <hi>vigour, influence,</hi> and preſervative power of the Soul due to the body; whereby the <hi>functions</hi> and neceſſary operations are not duly and ſufficiently performed, but <hi>intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtively, remiſly,</hi> and <hi>weakly:</hi> Nor is the dammage onely privative, but alſo introduceth and impreſſeth upon the ſpirits a <hi>morbifick Idea,</hi> which is <hi>ens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale &amp; ſeminale,</hi> producing this or that effect, according to the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the <hi>Idea</hi> received, and apti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the recipient ſubject. <hi>Phanſies</hi> and <hi>Idea's</hi> are let in naked, but they ſtreight are inveſted and cloathed in the body, have a real exiſtence, and are <hi>entia realia;</hi> though at firſt concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but <hi>entia rationis:</hi> as the longing of a <hi>pregnant</hi> Woman, being but the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:110713:79"/>
                  <hi>Idea</hi> of a thing in her mind, begets va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and real diſtemprs in her body, if not ſoon ſatisfied; and ſometimes <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractarized</hi> upon the <hi>Embryo</hi> in the Womb. Likewiſe a good ſtomach is taken off its meat ſuddenly, by the coming of ſome unwelcome bad news; the appetite is gone, now the <hi>Soul</hi> is <hi>diſquieted,</hi> and the Body really affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and altered: Let this ſad <hi>tydings</hi> be contradicted, and the Soul ſatisfied of the truth to the contrary; it ſets a <hi>new impreſſion</hi> upon the <hi>ſpirits,</hi> they ſtrait are <hi>cheared, lively</hi> and <hi>active;</hi> the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach calls for meat and drink, and the faculties reſtored to their wonted ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Whereby it appears, the two paſſions of <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>grief,</hi> as they are <hi>oppoſite</hi> in their <hi>objects,</hi> ſo are their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects wrought in the Body, as far diſtant and different.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A <hi>cogitative</hi> or <hi>contemplative</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to intent alwayes, or unſeaſonably employing the mind ſeriouſly and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly either in <hi>real</hi> or <hi>fictious</hi> matters, <hi>fabricating Idea's</hi> upon the ſpirits; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs and hinders other neceſſary offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and opperations conſervative of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, enervates and weakens their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:110713:79"/>
in duty, impares <hi>Health,</hi> and haſtens <hi>old Age:</hi> but thoſe that live moſt <hi>incurious,</hi> and void of <hi>ſtudious</hi> thoughts, too <hi>ſerious</hi> cogitations, and <hi>diſqueting</hi> paſſions; preſerve the ſtrength of Nature, and integrity of all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; protract the <hi>verdure</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> of youth, <hi>much longer</hi> from declenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and decay: for by how much the <hi>rational faculty</hi> is over buſie, diſturbed and intempeſtively exerciſed; draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>full vigour</hi> of the Soul into the diſcharge of that faculty, and robbing other inferiour functions of their <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary influential</hi> ſupply, and <hi>emanative</hi> power from the <hi>Soul;</hi> by <hi>ſo much</hi> the other <hi>faculties</hi> are impoveriſhed and abated; their executions more <hi>languid</hi> and <hi>depraved:</hi> and therefore it is a <hi>cloſe</hi> Students life, a <hi>careful</hi> or <hi>paſſionate</hi> mind, diſpoſeth to, and introduceth many infirmities; <hi>enervates</hi> and <hi>debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates</hi> nature, <hi>abbreviates</hi> and ſhortens her courſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:110713:80"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVI. Perturbations</hi> or <hi>Paſſions</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> particularly.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Of Anger.</head>
                  <p>THis Paſſion is a great Diſeaſe, if we conſider the <hi>preternatural ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> and <hi>alterations</hi> it maketh: for the <hi>functions</hi> of the body are <hi>diſordered</hi> and <hi>diſcompoſed</hi> by it, and the whole man changed from what he was. In giving judgement upon Diſeaſes, ſo much worſe is that perſon to be accounted, whoſe <hi>alteration</hi> is <hi>greater</hi> from what he was in a ſtate of <hi>health;</hi> and as the <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> perverted are <hi>more</hi> in number, and <hi>ſuperior</hi> in dignity.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> does not take up one <hi>particular</hi> part for its quarters; but it ſeaſeth the <hi>whole</hi> Man. All the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are diſordered, and every <hi>part</hi> is diſcompoſed and diſturbed. Take a
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:110713:80"/>
view of an <hi>angry</hi> Man; or rather a Man in the <hi>fury</hi> and <hi>perturbation</hi> of <hi>Anger:</hi> his <hi>Reaſon</hi> is ſuppreſt or ſuſpended; he acts not rationally, but as a <hi>mad</hi> man: his <hi>face</hi> is changed; his <hi>eyes</hi> ſtaires and ſparkles; his <hi>Tongue</hi> ſtammers; his <hi>Heart</hi> pants; his <hi>Pulſe</hi> beats high and quick; his <hi>Breath</hi> is almoſt gone; the <hi>Blood</hi> and all the <hi>Humours</hi> boyl; and the <hi>Spirits</hi> are agitated to and fro by <hi>guſts</hi> like an impetuous Wind; he <hi>trembles</hi> all over, and this <hi>ſtorm</hi> ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the whole <hi>Fabrick</hi> of mans body.</p>
                  <p>Surely this is a <hi>great Diſeaſe,</hi> that thus diſcompoſeth, and puts the <hi>whole man</hi> out of frame and order: ſuch ſtorms as theſe do much weaken and <hi>enervate</hi> the ability of the Faculties; diſorder their regular performance and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Offices; but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially infirm <hi>Parts</hi> are made ſenſible of the prejudice, and <hi>cholerick</hi> lean bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. An <hi>inflamation</hi> of any <hi>particular</hi> part is a great Diſeaſe; but <hi>Anger</hi> is an inflamation of the <hi>whole;</hi> and were this diſtemper to continue <hi>long,</hi> a man were in as much danger of <hi>life,</hi> as in the higheſt <hi>Feaver.</hi> Therefore take the <hi>Poets</hi> counſel.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:110713:81"/>
                     <l>Principiis obſta —</l>
                     <l>— Ne frena animo permitte Calenti.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Stat.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fear.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fear</hi> whether <hi>ſuddain</hi> and violently ſeazing, or <hi>gradually</hi> approaching and threatning an evil to come: both ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and debilitate Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fear</hi> ſuddainly ſurprizing, chaſeth the <hi>ſpirits</hi> to and fro from their reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and faculties, ſometimes <hi>compreſſing</hi> and driving them to the <hi>heart,</hi> cauſing violent palpitations and ſuffocation: or <hi>ſcattering</hi> them from the Fountain of Life, into the external parts, making a diſſolution almoſt to <hi>exanimation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such frightful <hi>ſurprizes</hi> as theſe, are very dangerous, and ſeldom happen, but they leave ſome ſad <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>Impreſſions</hi> behind.<note place="margin">Etiam fortes viri ſubitis terrentur. <hi>Tacit.</hi>
                     </note> Againſt this <hi>fear</hi> there is no remedy, having ſurprized and ſeized the Perſon before <hi>deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> can <hi>interpoſe</hi> to prevent it, or prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration made couragiouſly to meet, or valiantly to ſtand againſt this ſhock of <hi>terror.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fear</hi> that gives warning before the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:110713:81"/>
evil comes: and threatens as yet afar off: that <hi>Soul</hi> which then yeelds up her <hi>courage</hi> and ſtrength of reſiſtance, is <hi>diſarm'd</hi> by her own <hi>phanſie,</hi> and <hi>van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed</hi> by her ſelf: is conquered with nothing in <hi>Being,</hi> but with the <hi>fear</hi> of ſomething that <hi>may be.</hi> The evil, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to come, and poſſibly may be prevented and <hi>never come;</hi> yet it is made a <hi>preſent</hi> calamity: the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being received, and the <hi>Soul</hi> ſinks under them; make a <hi>preſſure</hi> upon the Soul as really afflicting as the evil it ſelf.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Multos in ſumma pericula</l>
                     <l>miſit timor ipſe mali.
<bibl>
                           <hi>Luc.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Such <hi>fears</hi> as theſe ought to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away, and manfully reſiſted; that which <hi>may be,</hi> is as far from us ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as that which <hi>never ſhall</hi> be. The fear of things that <hi>never</hi> come; are ten to thoſe that come to paſs.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quid juvat dolori ſuo occurrere?</l>
                     <l>Satis citò dolebit cum venerit.
<bibl>
                           <hi>Sen.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>As <hi>Anger</hi> ſwells the <hi>Soul,</hi> and thruſts forward the <hi>ſpirits</hi> into the exterior parts, to oppoſe and to revenge the ill: On the contrary, <hi>Fear</hi> makes the Soul to <hi>ſhrink,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirits</hi> to give
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:110713:82"/>
back. By this contraction of the <hi>Soul,</hi> her wonted <hi>vigorous emanations</hi> in all the faculties are ſuſpended; whereby the functions of the Body are remiſly and depravedly performed: the <hi>ſpirits</hi> retire inwards, the <hi>face</hi> grows pale, wan and thin; and the <hi>Soul</hi> pines and languiſheth with the <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of a ſeeming future <hi>evil,</hi> and the proſpect of a <hi>dubious impending fate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plura ſunt quae nos terrent quam quae premunt; &amp; ſaepius opinione quam re la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boramus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What if the evil threatned be too great for you to encounter with now: yet either your power may be <hi>enlarged</hi> before it comes; or that may be <hi>leſſened</hi> and <hi>reduced</hi> within the compaſs of your <hi>ability</hi> to reſiſt, and power to contend with.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quic quid humana ope majus eſt,</l>
                     <l>Diis permitte curandum.
<bibl>
                           <hi>Symach.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Care.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Care</hi> is a mixt <hi>paſſion,</hi> made up of <hi>Deſire</hi> and <hi>Fear.</hi> There is in <hi>Care</hi> a deſire of <hi>getting,</hi> and a fear of <hi>loſing:</hi> the anxiety between theſe two, <hi>ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates</hi>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:110713:82"/>
and weakens the ſtrength of the <hi>Soul:</hi> ſhe ſpends her ſelf in <hi>projection</hi> to <hi>acquire</hi> and get: and labours conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually alſo under the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>loſs:</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that <hi>already gotten,</hi> or of that which is in <hi>poſſibility,</hi> and <hi>likely</hi> to be obtained.</p>
                  <p>Being thus diſquieted, and alwayes in an unſatisfied condition; the Body is enfeebled and checkt from thriving: <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink</hi> will not nouriſh, if they be not changed duly, in the dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and <hi>aſſimilated</hi> into the ſubſtance of the Body, by the <hi>energy</hi> of a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Soul, in a placid ſtate of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; not drawn off <hi>unſeaſonably</hi> and conſtantly, with <hi>perplexing</hi> thoughts. Alwayes plodding in <hi>mind</hi> is not good: if your <hi>purſe</hi> gains and thrives by it; I am ſure your <hi>body</hi> looſeth and grows worſe. The <hi>Poet's</hi> advice in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is good ſometimes, being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly uſed.</p>
                  <q>Nunc vino pellite curas.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Hor.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>And another well admoniſheth from <hi>perplexing</hi> your ſelves with future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances and proviſions:
<q>
                        <l>Hodierna cura tantum;</l>
                        <l>Qui cras futura novit?
<bibl>
                              <hi>Anacr.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:110713:83"/>An indiſturbed free <hi>mind,</hi> not <hi>loaded</hi> with the thoughts of many years to come, but bearing onely the burthen of the <hi>day;</hi> holds out much longer, and preſerves the faculties in ſtrength and vigour: but <hi>immoderate</hi> care, and a <hi>thoughtful</hi> life, wears out the faculties much ſooner; <hi>tires</hi> the ſpirits by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying them their due times for refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſt and eaſe; diſables them from duty, and the true performance of their Offices; heats and waſtes the <hi>ſpirits,</hi> and <hi>exſiccates</hi> the nutritious juces of the Body; which changeth a freſh counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance into <hi>paleneſs;</hi> degenerates a good Conſtitution, and pines the Body: but moſt injurious to <hi>thin, lean,</hi> and <hi>cholerick</hi> Perſons. Thoſe too much thus addicted, and cumbred with care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thoughts, may ſometimes imitate this example for a Remedy.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nunc potemus laeti jucunda confabulantes;</l>
                     <l>Quae vero poſt erunt, diis ſint curae.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Theog.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Revenge, Jealouſie, <hi>and</hi> Envy.</head>
                  <p>Theſe Diſeaſes of the <hi>mind</hi> are as
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:110713:83"/>
painful Ulcers, continually lancinating, corroding or inflaming: they gnaw and eat like a <hi>Cancer;</hi> they take away the nouriſhment from <hi>food,</hi> and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from <hi>ſleep:</hi> the anguiſh of theſe <hi>ſores,</hi> render every thing unpleaſant and unſerviceable for the wellfare and ſupport of the Body: ſo that theſe ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the <hi>mind,</hi> make the <hi>Body</hi> to pine and languiſh, introducing a ſecret Conſumption, waſting the Spirits and nutritious moiſture, and enfeebling all the faculties.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Revenge</hi> (beſides the trouble and diſquietneſs of ſpirit) expoſeth a man to a <hi>greater miſchief,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Multis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> injuriis obiicit, dum una dolet. <hi>Sen.</hi>
                     </note> then what he hath received.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jealouſie</hi> is a ſecret tormentor, that gauls the <hi>mind</hi> with continual <hi>ſuſpition,</hi> and raiſeth <hi>ſuggeſtions,</hi> that afflict the Soul with <hi>anxiety</hi> and <hi>reſtleſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Envy</hi> is a <hi>Wolf</hi> in the Breaſt that muſt be ſatisfied, or it ſucks the <hi>blood,</hi> and feeds upon the <hi>vitals.</hi> This <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> pines and ſtarves a man in the midſt of <hi>plenty:</hi> and he <hi>withers</hi> away in the <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine</hi> of anothers proſperity.</p>
                  <q>Invidus alterius rebus marceſcit opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Hor.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:110713:84"/>Theſe <hi>perturbations</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> of the <hi>mind,</hi> will not let the <hi>body</hi> thrive; for if that be <hi>ſick,</hi> the Body cannot be in <hi>health.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Love <hi>and</hi> Deſire.</head>
                  <p>Theſe two, although they ſeldom go alone; and <hi>deſire</hi> follows cloſe at the heels of <hi>Love:</hi> yet they may be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and diſtinguiſhed thus. <hi>Love</hi> is a delight, complacency and ſuteable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with the thing loved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deſire,</hi> is the longing for, or ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of the <hi>Soul</hi> to obtain, procure and bring into enjoyment. <hi>Deſire</hi> gives <hi>wings</hi> to the <hi>Soul,</hi> and ſeemingly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and brings her to the thing deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ſo that all her ſtrength is ſpent in <hi>out-goings</hi> and <hi>ſtretchings forth</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and joyn with the object of deſire.</p>
                  <q>—Quò non poſſum Corpore, mente feror.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Ovid.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Deſire,</hi> being inordinate and impetuous, ſeldom goes alone, but is attended with other Paſſions: as <hi>Hope, Fear, Melancholly, Deſpair,</hi> one or more for their conſorts, with which the <hi>mind</hi> is <hi>racked</hi> and <hi>torn,</hi> and variouſly
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:110713:84"/>
affected as the ſeveral <hi>Paſſions</hi> acts their <hi>Parts</hi> by turns. Sometimes <hi>Love</hi> is <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>venturous;</hi> at another time <hi>cowardly</hi> and <hi>fearful:</hi> ſometime <hi>hoping,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>deſpairing;</hi> ſometimes <hi>brisk,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>ſad</hi> and <hi>heavy.</hi> So that the <hi>Soul</hi> is toſſed up and down, and filled with the diſquietneſs of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive mixt Paſſions, attending upon <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Deſire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor is the <hi>Soul</hi> onely diſturbed and hurried away by this Paſſion of <hi>Deſire;</hi> but the <hi>Body</hi> alſo is reſtleſs and unquiet: going from one place to another; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſatisfied <hi>Here,</hi> turns away, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to find more content <hi>There. Deſire</hi> is very ſollicitous and troubleſom, and importunate at <hi>unſeaſonable times;</hi> ſo that the <hi>bed</hi> does not give <hi>reſt</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> ſleeps, but is toſſing and turning there from <hi>ſide</hi> to <hi>ſide:</hi> and when <hi>up,</hi> cannot <hi>ſtand</hi> ſtill, or <hi>ſit</hi> ſtill; this thorny de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is alwayes <hi>ſpurring</hi> on from one place to another; but which way to take, this giddy <hi>Paſſion</hi> cannot well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve: notwithſtanding theſe <hi>perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> the <hi>doubts</hi> and <hi>difficulties</hi> of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, the <hi>Soul</hi> is led away with an <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis fatuus</hi> of fervent zeal; deſerts her
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:110713:85"/>
own <hi>manſion,</hi> the Body, and follows af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with an eager proſecution of <hi>enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> never at home but as a <hi>Priſoner;</hi> and Priſoners are but bad houſe-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: the <hi>body</hi> needs muſt languiſh and <hi>decay,</hi> when the Soul thus delights and ſtrives to run away.</p>
                  <p>By the continuance of theſe Paſſions <hi>interfering</hi> and <hi>complicating</hi> with each other; the regular <hi>oeconomy</hi> and <hi>tuition</hi> of the Body is neglected; that decayes, grows lean and conſumptive: the <hi>face</hi> grows pale, the <hi>appetite</hi> abates, and <hi>ſleep</hi> departs, or is but ſhort and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with troubleſome <hi>dreams</hi> and <hi>wakings:</hi> the vigour and ſtrength of the faculties is <hi>ſpent</hi> in <hi>deſiring,</hi> and by the <hi>diſquietneſs</hi> of the other attending <hi>Paſſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For a remedy and check to the <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſs</hi> of this inordinate affection and immoderate deſire; take theſe <hi>conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> to calm, allay, and regulate your paſſion.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That you cheat your ſelf in ſetting too <hi>high</hi> a <hi>price</hi> upon the <hi>object</hi> of your affections, and lay out more in <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation</hi> then the <hi>income</hi> of your deſire obtained can poſſibly make a return:
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:110713:85"/>
that it is far greater <hi>in non habendo,</hi> then it will be <hi>in fruendo;</hi> it will be much leſs when you have, then it ſeems to be now you have it not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the <hi>Delirium</hi> and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency of your deſire, does not haſten the accompliſhment of your aymes, but rather <hi>retards</hi> or <hi>fruſtrates:</hi> for the extremity and ſtrength of <hi>paſſion</hi> debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litates and ſuppreſſeth <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the chief contriver and manager of your deſign; puts you upon <hi>inconſiderate, immature</hi> and <hi>raſh</hi> attempts; and makes you more <hi>unfit, incapable,</hi> and <hi>unable</hi> to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect your purpoſe; for <hi>Paſſion</hi> is always <hi>ſpurring,</hi> but <hi>Reaſon</hi> hath its <hi>ſtops</hi> and <hi>pauſes,</hi> keeps due times for onſets and progreſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That prudent and vigorous <hi>action;</hi> not innane hungry <hi>volition,</hi> or thirſty <hi>deſire,</hi> though ever ſo great, can acquire the ſatisfaction of your hopes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the <hi>ardency</hi> &amp; <hi>heighth</hi> of <hi>deſire,</hi> will not <hi>imbetter, ſweeten,</hi> or add to the heighth of your <hi>enjoyment,</hi> but rather <hi>abate</hi> and leſſen it in your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and eſteem: for what thing ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you purchaſe, and are miſtaken and deceived in, you will not value at that
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:110713:86"/>
rate you <hi>firſt prized</hi> it, but at the worth you <hi>now find</hi> it. Vehement and lofty deſires ſcrew you up to ſuch a heighth of expectation, <hi>mountain high;</hi> but you muſt deſcend into <hi>fruition,</hi> that's low as the <hi>valley;</hi> and when you find your ſelf in a <hi>bottom,</hi> and your <hi>Sails</hi> not ſo filled and puft out, as formerly by the freſh gailes and blaſts of a ſtrong deſire; your top-fails then begin to <hi>flap</hi> and <hi>flag</hi> when you come in to the ſtill calm of <hi>fruition,</hi> and your lofty ſpirits and high thoughts will <hi>lower amain</hi> when you Anchor in the <hi>Harbour</hi> of <hi>Enjoyment:</hi> for in <hi>appearance</hi> it was great, when at a diſtance ſeemingly; but now you are come <hi>nearer,</hi> it is much leſs and <hi>inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable really;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Non ea jam mens res haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, quae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideranti erat.</note> and what ſwelled you full in the <hi>proſecution</hi> of attaining; will not fill you now with <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> but prove <hi>aery</hi> when you graſp it, and ſoon emptied in enjoyment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That <hi>ſtatutum eſt,</hi> it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed you <hi>muſt,</hi> or you <hi>muſt not</hi> obtain the thing deſired; which to a <hi>rational creature,</hi> is ſufficient without other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, to <hi>qualifie,</hi> moderate and <hi>blunt</hi> the keen edge of <hi>deſire,</hi> and <hi>curb</hi> the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of an impetuous affection: but
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:110713:86"/>
not to <hi>cowardiſe, daunt</hi> or <hi>ſtop</hi> a laudible active proſecution, to attain a <hi>noble, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous</hi> and lawful end, with a <hi>moderate ſubmiſive</hi> deſire.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—quiſquis in primo obſtitit</l>
                     <l>Repulitque amorem, tutus ac victor fuit.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Sen.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <l>Qui blandiendo dulce nutrivit malum,</l>
                     <l>Serò recuſat ferre quod ſubiit jugum.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Melancholly, Grief <hi>and</hi> Deſpair.</head>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Paſſions</hi> being neer alied, we may rank them together, as the <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> and <hi>Attendants</hi> upon <hi>adverſity</hi> and <hi>misfortunes:</hi> whoſe properties are to <hi>rob</hi> and <hi>ſteal</hi> away from the <hi>Soul,</hi> that <hi>viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> enlivening <hi>power,</hi> which roborates and quickens all the faculties in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. When theſe <hi>Paſſions</hi> are predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the <hi>energy</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> is abated, and all the <hi>functions</hi> inſufficiently, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and depravedly performed.</p>
                  <p>A dark Cloud of <hi>Melancholly</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreading the <hi>Soul;</hi> ſuffocates &amp; choaks the <hi>Spirits,</hi> retards their <hi>motion</hi> and <hi>agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> darkens their <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>light:</hi> theſe inſtruments in each faculty being thus diſabled, their offices in every part of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:110713:87"/>
the body are <hi>faintly</hi> executed, whereby the whole body <hi>decayes</hi> and <hi>languiſheth:</hi> witneſs the common ſymptoms of a dejected ſad condition: a <hi>pale thin</hi> face, <hi>heavy dead</hi> eyes, a <hi>ſlow</hi> weak <hi>pulſe,</hi> loſs of appetite, <hi>weakneſs, faintneſs, reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs;</hi> a weight or compreſſion about the region of the <hi>heart,</hi> with continual <hi>ſighing</hi> or <hi>palpitation:</hi> theſe are the <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> wrought in the Body, by <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly</hi> and <hi>Grief,</hi> which are to be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as great decayers of Nature, and great enemies to <hi>Beauty, Health,</hi> and <hi>Strength.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Hope, Joy <hi>and</hi> Mirth.</head>
                  <p>But embrace and cheriſh theſe, as the <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports</hi> of your <hi>life;</hi> which raiſeth the <hi>Soul</hi> to the higheſt pitch, and ſtretcheth forth her <hi>power</hi> to the <hi>utmoſt.</hi> Theſe enlivening affections are the greateſt friends to, &amp; preſervatives of <hi>health</hi> and <hi>ſtrength.</hi> In this <hi>ſerene</hi> ſtate of the <hi>Soul,</hi> all her endowments and abilities are advanced, both <hi>rational, ſenſitive</hi> and <hi>natural:</hi> the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs and delight of the <hi>Soul</hi> puts the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> upon activity, and excites them to a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>operation</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> in all the functions: preſerves <hi>youth</hi> and <hi>beauty,</hi> makes the body freſh, plump, and fat, by expanding the ſpirits into the external parts, and conveighing nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to repair and repleniſh the utmoſt bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and confines of the Microcoſm.</p>
                  <q>— dum fata ſinunt vivite laeti.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Sen.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
